<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvver of a true Christian to the proude challenge of a counterset Catholike. By VVilliam Fulke Doctor in diuinitie</title>
            <title>Two treatises written against the papistes. Part 1</title>
            <author>Fulke, William, 1538-1589.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1577</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 245 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122230</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857382</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857382</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23111</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01336)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23111)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 243:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvver of a true Christian to the proude challenge of a counterset Catholike. By VVilliam Fulke Doctor in diuinitie</title>
                  <title>Two treatises written against the papistes. Part 1</title>
                  <author>Fulke, William, 1538-1589.</author>
                  <author>Albin de Valsergues, Jean d', d. 1566. Notable discourse.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 110 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Vautrollier dwelling in the Blacke Friers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1577.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Another issue of the first part of STC 11458, "Two treatises written against the papistes", with revised preface and title, which is a reply to and reprinting of a version of part 2 (by William Allen, but often attributed to Edward Rishton) of "A notable discourse" by Jean d'Albin de Valsergues.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rishton, Edward, 1550-1586.</term>
               <term>Allen, William, 1532-1594.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23111:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23111:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSVVER OF A TRVE CHRISTIAN TO THE PROVDE CHALLENGE OF A counterfet Catholike.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By VVilliam Fulke Doctor in diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Thomas Vautrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier dwelling in the Blacke Friers. 1577.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:23111:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23111:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS short trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) hath lyen by me neare hand or altogether tenne yeres ſpace, vvrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at the requeſt of a godly &amp; learned friend of myne, in aunſvver to a proud challenge of a Papiſt againſt the Proteſtant. VVhich though at the firſt and many yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I determined not to publish, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the ſame challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to haue ben priuate, or in fevve mens handes: yet novv of late that I haue ſeene it in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe godly gentlemens handes, to
<pb facs="tcp:23111:3"/>vvhom it hath bene deliuered by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, belike to peruert them, and of vvhom alſo I haue bene deſired to au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvver it, and am further credibly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the ſame is in print, &amp; eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of many ignorant Papiſtes, to be ſo vnanſvverable, that although it hath bin proteſted, by gentlemen of great vvorship, and credit, that they haue ſeene the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſvvere therof in vvriting, yet they vvil not beleue, that any man dare ſet his penne to the paper, once to attempte the matter: I haue novve thought good to put it in print, as it vvas vvritte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the firſt. Nothing dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, by Gods help, but I shall be able to ſtand to the defence, if the Challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vvill proceede to mainteyne his challenge any longer. And vvhereas the ſame of late hath bene ioyned vvith my confutation of the doctrine
<pb facs="tcp:23111:3"/>of purgatory, and yet is deſired of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to be ſet forth in ſeuerall, becauſe the argument is more generall, it is thought good to ſatisfie their deſire, &amp; to ſpare their exſpenſes, that being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued in the matter of purgatory, doe yet ſtagger in the challenge of the Church. The breuity that I haue vſed (as I vnderſtand) is miſliked of ſome men, vvhich vvoulde haue vvished a larger diſcourſe, but ſeeing the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenger requireth shortnes, if this that is vſed be ſufficient to ſatisfie his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds or any of them, a longer trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe vvere but ſuperfluous. If he thinke him ſelfe not throughly aunſvvered, (&amp; declare the ſame) in all or in part, that vvhich is novve omitted shall then God vvilling be ſupplied. In the meane time vſe this (gentle Reader) and fare vvell in the Lorde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:23111:4"/>
            <head>The faultes of this impreſſion are thus to be amended: The firſt figure ſignifieth the page, the ſecond the line.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Pag. 3. line 35. Lithuania reade Lithuanda.</item>
               <item>5.3. vvriting r. vvritinges.</item>
               <item>10.10. the ſcripture, reade the booke of ſcripture.</item>
               <item>13.17. then, reade thou and line 19. you, reade thou.</item>
               <item>15. line the laſte. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erius. reade Liberius.</item>
               <item>19.4. you, reade the, and line 10. Ca. line. 58. reade Carolines. 8. and line 19. Mercamas, r. Marranias.</item>
               <item>22.9. fauour, reade honor.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.26. the prince, reade the printers.</item>
               <item>24.1. put out and.</item>
               <item>25.9 not for his, r. for his.</item>
               <item>29.10. vnitie of minde, r. vnitie of faith &amp; minde.</item>
               <item>30.3. in the places aboue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed. in diuerſe places of his epiſtles, a. lib. 3. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 14. and 15.16. &amp;c.</item>
               <item>41.30. Rhenes, r. Rhemes.</item>
               <item>49.5. the the, r. that the. &amp; the 12. r. &amp; the Catho. &amp;c.</item>
               <item>52.13. in Brytish, reade in the Brytish.</item>
               <item>63.14. about the articles, r. about the chiefeſt articles.</item>
               <item>64.20. put out (that hilde.) and the 24. here, rea. ſore.</item>
               <item>67.21. vvhich can not, rea. vvhich you can not.</item>
               <item>68.4. in a name, reade in a manner.</item>
               <item>69.4. prorſus opinemur, r. prorſus non opinemur. and 34. vniuerſally, r. vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalitie and 36 vvhich you do, r. vvhich you do not.</item>
               <item>70.17. propone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da, r. praepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da. &amp; 22. in a r. in the. &amp; 24. vvhen. r. vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the.</item>
               <item>71.20. vvhere, ręa. vvere, and the 22. to, reade in.</item>
               <item>78.26. that you ſavv a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard church, r. that you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a baſtard church haue.</item>
               <item>87.34 Commentualls, rea. Conuentualles.</item>
               <item>91.32. that he rea. then he.</item>
               <item>92.30. cultiued, r. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued.</item>
               <item>97.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. your, reade youres.</item>
               <item>99.13. there, rea. therefore. &amp; 14. vinci, reade v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icè.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:23111:4"/>
            <head>AN ANSVVER OF A TRVE CHRISTIAN TO A COVNTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FAIT CATHOLIKE.</head>
            <div type="proposition">
               <head>The propoſition of the Aduerſarie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hrist did commit at his departure hence, the teſtimony of that truth, for which he died, and the conuerſion of the Nations to the beleefe in him, to the true church of God, which then ſtoode principally, and almoſt onely in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Apoſtles and a fewe more, that by their preachings, and thoſe afterward of their calling, the Chriſtian religion might be planted in all Nations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at Ieruſalem, and ſo proceeding to the coaſtes and corners of the earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>AN ANSVVERE TO THE PROPOSITION.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Graunt that our Sauiour Chriſt, at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture hence, commaunded his Apoſtles as principal members of his Church, though not the greateſt part of it, to preach the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which he confirmed by his death vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all nations, beginning at Ieruſalem, and ſo forth according to his ſaying: <hi>Goe therefore and teach all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghoſt: Teaching them to obſerue all thinges what ſo euer I haue commaunded you. Matth.</hi> 28. Whereuppon I cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the Papiſt, that if he be able to proue that the doctrine of poperie is all that trueth, and nothing but that trueth, for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:23111:5"/>which Chriſt dyed, and which he commaunded the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to teach, I will acknowledge the popiſh church to be the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <div n="1" type="article">
                  <head>The firſt article conteyneth 3. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Firſt I aske of the proteſtant what Church that was, which conuerted all theſe cuntries that be now Chriſtian, to the faith of Chriſt?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IF you meane by Chriſtians, true Chriſtians, and by the faith of Chriſt, the true faith of Chriſt, I anſwere: only the true Church of Chriſt, hath had the worde of God and ſacraments, as meanes which God vſeth, to ſubdue al na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vnto the obedience of the faith, as was the primitiue Church of the Apoſtles, which hath continued vnto this daye by ſucceſſion, not of perſonnes, and places, but of faith and truth, wherefore if the Papiſt can proue, that we holde not the ſame faith and trueth, vnto which the Apoſtles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted the nations, we refuſe to be called the Church or Congregation of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>But if by Chriſtians and Chriſtian faith, you meane all them that profeſſe the name of Chriſt, in the whole worlde, I aunſwere, that the true Church of Chriſt, did not conuert them all, for in Aethiopia, there are yet people, conuerted by the falſe apoſtles, which taught circumciſion, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the lawe, in which hereſie they continue vnto this day, and it is manifeſt by all hiſtories, that the nations of the Alanes, Gothes, and Vandales, were firſt conuerted by the Arrians.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>And let him ſhew vnto me, that euer his Church conuerted any people, or lande in the earth, from Idolatrie, or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility, or Iudaiſme, to the true Religion of Chriſt, or that this his fayth was taught to any Nation in ſteede of true Chriſtianity.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVE are members of that Church, which conuerted all landes in the earth that are conuerted, from Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:23111:5"/>Gentility, Iudaiſme, or hereſie, to the true Religion of Chriſt, and we affirme that the Apoſtles taught none other faith in ſteede of true Chriſtiantie, but that which we hold, as we are readie to proue by the worde of God: And at this daye the moſt parte of Europe, is conuerted from Idolatrie, hereſie, and Antichriſtianitie, vnto the ſame true faith, that we mainteine, as in England, Scotland, Ireland, France, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, Denmarke, Suetia, Bohemia, Polonia, by publike au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, in Spaigne, and Italie, a great numbre vnder perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and tyrannie. Alſo of the Iewes, no ſmall numbre are conuerted to our religion, ſince the riſing vp of the Goſpell in our dayes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>Or any Church, but the common Catholike Church to haue don that, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BEcauſe you meane by the common Catholike, not the true Catholike, but the popiſh church: Firſt I denie that euer the popiſh church conuerted any people, to the true faith. Secondly, I denie that the popiſh church hath conuerted all nations, to the profeſſion of Chriſt: For, it is ſhewed before, that the falſe Apoſtles, and Arians, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted ſome nations to the profeſſion of Chriſtes name, but yet to falſe religion, And it is alſo manifeſt by hiſtories, that the Grecians, whome the papiſtes counte no parte of their church, but ſchiſmatikes, conuerted the Moſcouites firſt of all, vnto the profeſſion of the name of Chriſt, which yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in their religion, being neither the true faith, nor yet popiſh religion. As for the popiſh church, as it is certeine, that it hath peruerted and corrupted all partes of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, or Weſterne Church, with Idolatry and falſe religion, ſo it ſhalbe harde for the papiſtes to proue, that it hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted any Nation from Gentility to the popiſh religion, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſome partes of Germanie, and them by force of armes, rather than by preaching, and teaching, as appeareth by the conuerſion of <hi>Liuonia, Anno Domini</hi> 1200. of <hi>Pruſſia, Anno Domini</hi> 1254. and <hi>of Lithuania, Anno Domini</hi> 1386. wherefore I conclude that ſeeing I haue ſhewed that our Church, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:23111:6"/>the true doctrine of the Apoſtles, is that which conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all nations to true religion, and that the popiſh church, hath not conuerted any people to true religion, nor all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the profeſſion of the name of Chriſt, this chalenger, whoſoeuer he be, do the recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="article">
                  <head>The ſecond article conteyneth 4. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>I aſke of him what Church it was, which hath induced the Chriſtian people through the whole worlde, to geue moſt humble credit in all points, to the holy bookes of the Byble?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Aunſwere, it was the Church of Chriſt, and not the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh church, which hath commended the bookes of holy Scripture, to be beleued of all true Chriſtians where ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they be, although it be the office of the holy Ghoſt, to open the hartes of men, and to forme them that they may beleue the ſcripture to be true, like as it is the office of the ſcripture or worde of God, to trie and examine, whether it be the ſpirite of God that perſwadeth vs to beleue any thing, ſo the ſpirite beareth witneſſe to the worde and the worde to the ſpirite. As for the popiſh church it coulde not induce the Chriſtian people to geue credit to the ſcripture in all pointes, becauſe ſhe is contrarie to the ſcripture in many pointes: and euen in the cheefeſt pointes of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, namely in pointes concerning the glorie of God, and the ſaluation of mankinde, geuing the glory of God to dead men, and dumbe Images, and denying the mercy of God, pourchaſed by the onely ſacrifice of Chriſtes death, to be the onely cauſe of mans ſaluation. Finally ſeeing it is manifeſt by the aunſwere to the firſt article, that the popiſh church did not conuerte all nations, to the profeſſion of the Chriſtian faith, it is euident thereby, that the popiſh church did not induce all them, that are called Chriſtians, to geue credit to the bookes of the holy Bible, as this chalenger woulde haue it to be thought.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>VVhat Church hath had the diſcerning &amp; ſeuering of them from other writinges of all ſortes?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:23111:6"/>
                     <p> THe Church of Chriſt, hath not an abſolute authority to allow or refuſe bookes of the ſcripture, but a iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to diſcerne true writinge from counterfaicts, &amp; the word of God, of infallible verity, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> writing of men, which might erre, &amp; this iudgement ſhe hath, not of her ſelfe, but of the holy Ghoſt: as for the popiſh Church, it can not be ſaid to haue this iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of diſcerning the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture of God from other writings, not only becauſe ſhe is ſo blind that ſhe can not diſcerne betwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Canonical bookes of the ſcripture, from the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> writings, as appereth by receauing the bookes of the Machabees, Eccleſiaſticus, &amp;c. to be of equall authoritie with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bookes of the Law, Pſalmes, &amp;c. but alſo becauſe ſhe is ſo preſumptuous, as to compel men to beleue, that Cuſtomes, and traditions, writinges of doctors, decrees of Popes, and Councells, are equall with the authoritie of God his worde, yea are of force, to alter and change the lawe of God, and the inſtitution of Chriſt, ſet forth vnto vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture. And although ſhe boaſt that ſhe receaueth all the bookes of ſcripture, yet this proueth no more that ſhe is the Church of Chriſt, than was the churches of the Arrians, Donatiſtes, Nouatians, Euthychans, &amp; other heretikes, which receiued the Bible, as well as the Popiſh church.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>VVhat Church hath had the cuſtodie of them, and moſt ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath preſerued them, for the neceſſary vſe of God his people, and from the corruption of aduerſaries, as well of Iewes, as heretikes of all ſortes?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe prouidence of God, hath alwayes preſerued the Scripture, both from the violence of tyrants, &amp; from the falſhoode of heretikes, and hath neuer ſuffred the true Church, to be deſtitute of the neceſſarie vſe thereof. But the popiſh church, hath not kept the ſcripture for the neceſſary vſe of the people, which hath ſo kept it in an vnknowen tongue, that the people coulde haue no vſe, much leſſe the neceſſary vſe thereof: wherefore if this be a note of the Catholike Church, to kepe the worde of God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:23111:7"/>for the neceſſarie vſe of God his people, it is plaine that the popiſh church is not the Catholike Church, which hath kept the ſcripture ſo, that God his people coulde haue no vſe thereof.</p>
                     <p>And if the only cuſtodie of the ſcripture from corruption of heretikes, be a ſure note of the Church, why is not the Greeke Church, the Catholike Church, which vnto this day hath kept the ſcripture as ſafely as the popiſh church? why are not other Eſtern Churches of Aſia, which neuer acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the Pope, or popiſh religion, true Churches, which likewiſe haue preſerued the ſcripture, as we haue ſeen of late, that the newe Teſtament is printed in the Syrian tongue, at themperours charges, for the encreaſe of Chriſtian faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. And finally, why are not the Iewes, the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, which haue kept the old Teſtament in Hebrue, more faithfully than euer the Papiſtes. And becauſe they boaſt of ſafe preſeruing of the ſcriptures, all men, that are learned in the tongues can teſtifie, in how corrupt a Latin tranſlation they haue kept the ſcriptures, both of the olde and of the new Teſtament.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="demand">
                     <head>4 <hi>And let the Proteſtant declare to me, that their Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath had from time to time, or euer had right herein, or any other Church, ſauing the Catholike Church, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>OVr Congregation, which is the body of Chriſt, hath euer had, both right and poſſeſſion of the ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble treaſure of the word of Chriſt her heade: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by this, that our Church and Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion beleueth nothing but that ſhe learneth in it, acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth that all thinges profitable to ſaluation, are ſufficiently conteined in it, and finally in all thinges ſubmitteth her ſelfe to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of it. But the popiſh church, which beleueth many thinges contrarie to the ſcripture, teacheth many thinges beſide the ſcripture, neceſſary to ſaluation, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth to haue her faith, doctrine, and ceremonies, to be iudged by the ſcripture, neither hath, neither euer had, any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:23111:7"/>right to the ſcripture, though ſhe haue neuer ſo many bookes of them in poſſeſſion. Wherefore theſe thinges conſidered, this chalenger doth recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="article">
                  <head>The third article conteyneth 5. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Shew me why our common knowen Church, did not as well corrupt the text of the Teſtament, as the true religion conteyned in the ſame?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THere may be diuers good reaſons ſhewed, why your Church, commonly knowen to be the church of Antichriſt, did not as well corrupt the text of the Teſtament, as the true religion conteined therein. Firſt, becauſe ſhe coulde not, the copies thereof being ſo many, by the prouidence of God diſperſed throughout the worlde. Secondly, becauſe ſhe thought it not ſo needefull, hauing other meanes to worke her deuiliſh deuiſe: For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhe coulde not corrupt the ſcripture, yet it made the leſſe matter, becauſe ſhe founde meanes to diminiſh, and controll the authority therof by aduancing decrees of men, Popes, and Councells, to be equall or of greater authoritie than the ſcripture. Thirdly, becauſe ſhe woulde be leſſe in feare, to be reproued by the ſcripture, ſhe prouided that the knowledge thereof, ſhoulde be hidden from the vnlearned people by a ſtrange tongue, and from the learned, by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious mazes of queſtions, deuiſed by her Canoniſtes, and Sententiaries. Fourthly, becauſe ſhe ſubmitted all interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the ſcripture, to her owne iudgement, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore woulde not be controlled by the iudgement thereof, but woulde alwayes expound it, as it liked her beſt. As ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by <hi>Ockam,</hi> and <hi>Duns,</hi> who though they confeſſe, that tranſubſtantiation, ſeemeth to them, contrary to the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and reaſon, yet they beleued it, becauſe of the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the church, and for none other cauſe. Theſe are the reaſons, why the Romiſh church did not, as well corrupt the text of the Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as the true Religion. And yet how cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt that Latine tranſlation is, which they woulde needes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:23111:8"/>thruſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, is ſufficiently knowen to all learned men, euen in ſuch texts, as are the moſt coulerable places for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Popiſh doctrine. I will geue one example for all: They alleage the text 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>Qui ſtat, videat ne cadat.</hi> He that ſtandeth, let him take heede he fall not, againſt the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainetie of faith, whereas the Greeke hath, not he that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, but, he that thinketh he ſtandeth, let him take heede he fall not: Thus the popiſh church cannot altogether ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe her ſelfe, from corrupting of the text of the Teſtament, whether it was of fraude, or of ignorance, or of negligence, the Lorde knoweth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>Shew me why, ſhe kept not ſo ſafely, and faithfully, the true ſenſe of God his word, as ſhe preſerued the word it ſelfe?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BEcauſe it was againſt her owne eſtimation, and profit, which are the chiefe endes for which popiſh Prelates mainteyne popiſh religion. Take away the Popes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue, which is contrary to the ſenſe of God his word, downe goe Cardinalls, Legates, Prothonotaries: downe goeth all the Court of Rome, take away workes of ſuperero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, which are contrary to the Scripture, downe goe Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beys, Priories and Chantries. Take away the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, &amp; Purgatory, which are contrary to the word of God, downe goeth the eſtimation, and gaynes of all the popiſh clergie: And this is the cauſe, why the popiſh church kept not ſo ſafely, and faithfully, the true ſenſe of God his word, as ſhe preſerued the word it ſelfe, although ſhe preſerued not the word it ſelf, in ſuch ſafetie as becommed the Church of Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>Shew me why, we ſhould beleue the Papiſtes, as you terme them, for the word it ſelf, and rather you Proteſtants tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, for the meaning of the word.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WE doe not chalenge credit to our ſelues, in any poynt, ſo preſumptuouſly as the Papiſtes, that men muſt beleue it becauſe we affirme it. But becauſe we proue it to be true, by the worde of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:23111:8"/>God. And therefore for the meaning of the word, you ſhould beleue vs rather than them, becauſe our groundes &amp; proues are better then theirs, or elſe we require not to be beleued better than they.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="demand">
                     <head>4 <hi>Shew me why, you beleued our Church, telling you this to be God his booke, &amp; will not credit her, auouching this to be the true and vndoubted ſenſe of the ſame booke?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IF we had no better ground to perſwade vs, of the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of God his booke, than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtimony of your Church, you may be ſure we would not beleue it. But becauſe we haue moſt ſtedfaſt aſſurance of God his ſpirite, for the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of that booke, with the teſtimony of the true Church in all ages. If you ſay it is God his booke, we beleue you not, becauſe you ſay ſo, but becauſe we know it to be true. But if you bring out a falſe ſenſe, we beleue you not, becauſe we know it to be falſe, &amp; are able to proue by the word of God, that it is contrary to the meaning of the holy Ghoſt. To be plaine with you, we geue as much credit to your Church, as to the deuill. When the deuill ſayth: it is written: <hi>He ſhall giue his angells charge ouer thee, and with their handes they ſhall hold thee vp that thou daſh not thy foote againſt a ſtone.</hi> We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that this is the worde of God. But when he auoucheth this to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaning of it, that we may caſt downe our ſelues from a Church ſteeple, without daunger, we doe not beleue him, becauſe we know this ſenſe is contrary to an other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which ſayth: <hi>Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God.</hi> So when you ſay theſe wordes are the Scripture of God: <hi>This is my body:</hi> We beleue it, becauſe we knowe it to be true. But when you ſay this is the meaning of theſe wordes. <hi>This bread is turned into my naturall bodye,</hi> we beleue you not, becauſe it is contrary to all places of Scripture, which proue the trueth of Chriſt his humanitie or naturall body. Thus I ſhewe you why we beleue you, if you ſay the Scripture is God his word, namely becauſe we know it to be true, &amp; why we beleue you not, ſaying this is the meaning of it, that is, becauſe we knowe by the word of God that it is falſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="demand">
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:23111:9"/>
                     <head>5 <hi>Laſt of all, Shew me why, you beleued the olde known church, affirming this to be the word of God, and will not beleue her, affirming Luther to be an heretike, ſhew me good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Scripture for theſe thinges, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IF you meane by the olde Church the primitiue Church, whoſe teſtimony of the word of God we allow &amp; beleue, I deny that the primitiue Church did affirme <hi>Luther</hi> to be an heretike, or the doctrine that he taught, which we hold, to be hereſie, but I am able to proue, that the primitiue Church, from which you haue receiued the Scripture, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth your doctrine to be hereſie, &amp; your Church y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of Antichriſt.</p>
                     <p>But if by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old knowne Church, you meane the Church of old, knowne to be the Church of Antichriſt, which is the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh church, we beleue the deuill if he ſpeake the trueth, and we beleue not an Angell comming from heauen, if he bring any other Goſpel, than <hi>S. Paule</hi> deliuered to the Galathians. Therefore when your church affirmeth <hi>Luther</hi> to be an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, ſeeing we know that <hi>Luther</hi> did not obſtinately, and malitiouſly erre, in any article of faith, concerning the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of religion, we doe not beleue her: and ſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe is a partiall witneſſe againſt him, whome God vſed to diſcouer, ſo much of her wickedneſſe, to her great hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance, there is no credit to be geuen vnto her, when ſhe goeth about to deface him, by ſclaunderous names, and falſe accuſations. Thus I haue ſhewed theſe thinges that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, both by good reaſon, and alſo by ſcripture: Therefore if I may beleue you, you recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="article">
                  <head>The fourth article conteyneth 3. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>I demand, what Church hath mightely gonne through, borne downe, and fully vanquiſhed, all hereſies in times paſt, aſwell againſt the bleſſed Trinitie, as other Articles of our religion?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:23111:9"/>
                     <p> I Aunſwere, the true Catholike Church, hath alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted all falſe opinions, contrary to the worde of God, as her duty was, and fought againſt them with the ſworde of the ſpirite, which is the worde of God, and by the aide of God obteyned the victorie, and triumphed ouer them. So did <hi>Paule</hi> ouercome the Iewes <hi>Act.</hi> 18. So did the fathers of the primitiue Church, from time to time, confute hereſies, by the ſcriptures, and declare in their writinges, that by them they are to be confuted, for examples ſake of a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, I will alleage a few. <hi>Hylarius,</hi> writing of the bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie againſt heretikes <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. ſayeth: <hi>Ceſſent ita<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> propriae ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum opiniones, ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſe vltrà Diuinam conſtitutionem, humana iudicia extendant: Sequamur ergo aduerſus irreligioſas, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias de Deo inſtitutiones, ipſas illas diuinorum dictorum authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, &amp; vnumquod<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> eorum ipſo de quo quaeritur auctore tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimus.</hi> Wherefore let opinions propre to men geue place, and let not mens iudgements ſtretche them ſelues further than God his conſtitution. Therefore againſt theſe vnreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and vngodly opinions of God, let vs follow the very authority of God his ſayings, and handle euery one of them, by the aide of him, about whome the queſtion is: Thus <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius,</hi> woulde haue hereſies againſt the Trinitie, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, not by mens iudgement, but by God his word. <hi>Baſilius magnus,</hi> very often teſtifieth, that he woulde haue all good thinges, proued by the ſcripture, and all euill thinges confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſame, In his moralles <hi>Diſt.</hi> 26. Euery worde or deede, muſt be confirmed by the teſtimonie of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for the perſwaſion of good men, and the confuſion of wicked men: And in his treatiſe of Faith: we know, that we muſt now, and alwayes, auoide euery voice or opinion, that is differing from the doctrine of our Lorde. And in his ſhort definitions to the firſt interrogation: whether it be lawefull or profitable for a man to permit vnto him ſelfe, to do or ſay any thinge, which he thinketh to be good, without the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of the holy Scripture? he aunſwereth: foraſmuch as our Sauiour Chriſt ſayeth: that the holy Ghoſt ſhall not ſpeake of him ſelfe, what madnes is it, that any man ſhoulde preſume to beleue any thing, without the authoritie of God
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:23111:10"/>his worde. By theſe, and many other places, it is manifeſt, that <hi>Baſilius,</hi> woulde haue hereſies and falſe opinions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by the holy Scriptures.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> vpon <hi>Luke cap.</hi> 16. ſayeth, that the ignorance of the ſcriptures, hath bred hereſies, and brought in corrupt life, yea it hath turned all things vpſidown, by which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, by what meanes he would haue hereſies kept away, namely by knowledge of the ſcriptures. It were to long to reherſe all the places of <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> by which his minde ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that he would haue the Church, ſought onely in the ſcriptures, and heretikes confuted, onely by the ſcriptures, to whoſe onely authoritie in many places, he profeſſeth that he him ſelfe will be bounde, as <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 19. <hi>ad Hieronymum. Epiſt.</hi> 48. <hi>Vincentio. Epiſt.</hi> 111. <hi>Fortunatiano. Epiſt.</hi> 112. to <hi>Paulina, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Fauſtum. lib.</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Contra Creſconium Grammaticum, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 31. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32. <hi>de Baptiſmo contra Donatiſtas lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>De meritis &amp; remiſſione peccatorum, contra Pelagianos lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>De naturae &amp; gratia cap.</hi> 61. <hi>De gratia Chriſti contra Pelagium cap.</hi> 43. <hi>De nuptijs &amp; concupiſcentia lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 29. In theſe places, <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> preferreth the authority of the Canonicall ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, before all writinges of Catholike Doctors, of Byſhops, of Councells, before all cuſtomes, and traditions. But that he would haue the true Church ſought onely in the ſcriptures, it is manifeſt, by theſe places, firſt in his 48. Epiſtle to Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius. <hi>Nos autem ideo certiſumus, neminem ſe a communione omnium gentium iuſtè ſeparare potuiſſe, quia non quiſquam no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum in iuſtitiae ſua, ſed in ſcripturis Diuinis quaerit Eccleſiam.</hi> ſpeaking of the Donatiſtes, he ſayeth. We are ſuer, that no man could iuſtly ſeparate him ſelfe from the communion of all Nations, becauſe none of vs ſeeketh the Church in his owne righteouſneſſe, but in the holy Scriptures. So if the Papiſtes woulde not preſume of their owne righteouſneſſe, but ſeeke the Church of Chriſt in the ſcriptures, they would not ſeparate them ſelues from the communion of Chriſtes Church, now by God his grace inlarged farther than the Popiſh church. Alſo in his booke <hi>De vnitate Eccleſiae. cap.</hi> 2. he hath theſe wordes. <hi>Inter nos autem &amp; Donatiſtas quaeſtio eſt, vbi ſit Eccleſia. Quid ergo facturi ſumus? in verbis noſtris
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:23111:10"/>eam quaeſituri, an in verbis capitis ſui Domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſtis puto quod in illius potius verbis eam quaerere debemus, qui ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas eſt, &amp; optimè nouit corpus ſuum.</hi> The queſtion is betwene vs, and the Donatiſtes, where the Church ſhoulde be, what ſhall we doe then? ſhall we ſeeke her in our owne wordes, or in the wordes of her heade our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt? I thinke we ought rather to ſeeke her in his words which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Truth, and beſt knoweth his owne body. So the queſtion is at this daye, betwen the Papiſtes and vs, where the church is, let vs ſeeke in God his worde, there we ſhall eaſily finde her. To the ſame intent, he ſpeaketh in the third, fiueth, and ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenth Chapters of the ſame treatiſe. Furthermore, that he woulde haue heretikes confuted onely by the ſcriptures, he ſheweth likewiſe in many places of his workes: for wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt <hi>Maximinus</hi> the Arian, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. a place com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly and often cited, he ſayeth: but nowe, neither muſt I preiudicially bring forthe the Councell of Nice, nor then the Councell of Arimine, for neither am I bounden to the authoritie of the one, nor you of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, but let matter with matter, cauſe with cauſe, reaſon with reaſon, contend by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the ſcriptures, not proper to any, but indifferent witneſſes to both partes. If <hi>Auguſtine</hi> would not oppreſſe the Arrians, by the authoritie of the Nicene Councell, which was the firſt, and the beſt generall Councell, that euer was, but only by the ſcriptures, how much leſſe woulde he charge them with other authorities, that the Papiſtes alleage, beſide the authoritie of holy ſcriptures. And in his booke <hi>De Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Eccleſiae</hi> againſt the Donatiſtes the 16 chapter: <hi>Sed vtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſi Eccleſiam teneant, non niſi diuinarum ſcripturarum Canonicis libris oſtendant, quia nec nos &amp;c.</hi> But whether they holde the church or no: let them ſhew none other wiſe, but by the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall bookes of holy Scripture, for we our ſelues doe not ſay, that men ought to beleue vs, that we are in the Church, becauſe we holde that Church which <hi>Optatus</hi> of <hi>Mileuitum,</hi> or <hi>Ambroſe</hi> of <hi>Millayn,</hi> or innumerable other Byſhops of our communion, haue commended to vs, or becauſe it is ſet forth by the Councels of our felowe byſhops, or becauſe ſo many myracles of hearing requeſts, or healinges, are don in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:23111:11"/>the holy places, which our fellowſhip doth frequent in the whole worlde, ſo that the bodies of Martyrs, which were hidden ſo many yeares (which thinge if they will aſke they may heare of many) were reuealed vnto <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and that at the ſame bodies, one that had bene many yeares blinde, very well knowen in the citie of <hi>Millayn,</hi> receyued his eyes, and eye ſight, either becauſe this man dreamed, or that man was rauiſhed in the ſpirite, and hearde a voice, that he ſhould not ioyne himſelfe to <hi>Donatus,</hi> or that he ſhoulde departe from the faction of <hi>Donatus:</hi> for when ſoeuer ſuch thinges are don in the Catholike Church, they are to be allowed, becauſe they are don in the Catholike church. but the church it ſelfe is not therfore proued to be Catholike, becauſe theſe thinges are done in it. By this <hi>Auguſtine</hi> declareth firſt that heretikes muſt be confuted, onely by the ſcriptures, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly that neither Councells, ſucceſſion of byſhops, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſality, miracles, viſions, dreames, nor reuelations, are the notes to trie the Catholike church, but onely the ſcriptures. Moreouer in his booke <hi>De Paſtoribus cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Quaerit infirmus Eccleſiam &amp;c.</hi> A weake perſon ſeeketh the Church, he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and ſeeketh the church, what ſayeſt you? The church is of <hi>Donatus</hi> ſide. Enquire for the ſhepheards voice, Reade me this out of ſome Prophet, reade me this out of ſome Pſalme, rehearſe me it out of the lawe, rehearſe it out of the Goſpell, rehearſe it out of the Apoſtle, out of them do I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe the Church diſperſed ouer all the worlde. And a litle after: <hi>Tu accuſas non Euangelium &amp;c.</hi> Thou accuſeſt, not the Goſpell, thou accuſeſt not the Prophet, not the Apoſtle of whome this voyce ſpeaketh to me I beleue him other I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue not. But thou wilt bring forth decrees, I will alſo bring forth decrees, ſhoulde I beleue thine? beleue thou mine like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. I beleue not thine, neither do thou beleue mine, then let mens writings be layd away and let Gods worde ſounde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twen vs: bring me one place of ſcripture for <hi>Donatus</hi> ſide &amp;c. Theſe places maye ſufficiently declare by what meanes this doctor thought the Church ſhoulde ouerthrowe hereſies, namely by the worde of God onely, which thing alſo <hi>Leo,</hi> the firſt byſhop of Rome, in his <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 10. <hi>ad Fabianum contra
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:23111:11"/>Eutychen</hi> plainely confeſſeth ſaying: <hi>Sed in hanc inſipientiam cadunt, qui cum ad cognoſcendam veritatem &amp;c.</hi> But thoſe men fal into this foly, which when they are hindred by any doubt to knowe the trueth, haue not recourſe to the voyces of the Prophets, not to the writings of the Apoſtles, not to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Goſpell, but to them ſelues. And therefore they become, maiſters of error, becauſe they haue not bene ſchollers of trueth. Of the ſame iudgement was the whole Councell of Conſtantinople the ſixt, as appeare <hi>Actione</hi> 18. <hi>Si igitur omnes ſimpliciter &amp;c.</hi> Therefore if all men from the beginning woulde haue ſimply and without ſubtiltie taken vpon them the preaching of the Goſpell, and haue bene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with the conſtitutions of the Apoſtles, ſuerly matters ſhoulde haue bene well, and in good caſe, neither ſhoulde painefull contention, haue bene exerciſed againſt the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of hereſies, nor againſt the fauorers of prieſts. Here the Councell confeſſeth, that the heretikes and ſchiſmatikes grow ſo faſt, becauſe they were not beaten downe, by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell and authority of the ſcriptures. Thus I haue declared by example, and authority of theſe Fathers, that the true Church of Chriſt, hath conuicted all heretikes, onely by the ſcripture.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>And what Church it was, that hath alwayes ſtande ſtill, and ſtedfaſt, whileſt all other Congregations, as well of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, as Anabaptiſtes, Aerians, Nouatians, Vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, Iouinians, and the reſt haue decaied.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe true Church of Chriſt, hath alwayes ſtoode ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, and vnſeparable, from Chriſt her heade, when all heretikes haue bene, and ſhal be confounded. But the true Church hath not alwaies floriſhed in word<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peace and tranquilitie: for vntill the tyme of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, which was <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 339. the Church had ſmall reſt from cruell perſecution in moſt places: and ſoone after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnder the Emperors <hi>Conſtantius, Conſtans,</hi> and <hi>Valons,</hi> it was greatly infected with the hereſie of <hi>Arius,</hi> what time alſo <hi>Tiberius</hi> Biſhop of Rome, was infected with the ſame hereſie.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:23111:12"/>After that when <hi>Iulianus</hi> the <hi>Apoſtata,</hi> was Emperor, the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Idolls were opened, and gentilitie againe reſtored, ſo that the Church ſuffered great detriment. To be ſhort, when the barbarous Goathes, Vandales, Alanes, and other Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous or heretical nations deſtroyed the Empire, the Church of God ſuffered a great Ecclipſe. But when <hi>Mahomet,</hi> in the Eaſt, &amp; Antichriſt the Pope, in the Weſt, ſeduced the world with moſt deteſtable hereſie, then was fulfilled that which was reuealed to <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in the 12. of the <hi>Apocalyps, the woman clothed with the Sonne,</hi> which you your ſelf confeſſe to be the Church, <hi>was ſo perſecuted by the Dragon, that ſhe fled into the wildernes, there to remaine a long ſeaſon.</hi> Where ſhe hath not decayed, but ben always preſerued, vntil God ſhould reueale Antichriſt, and bring her againe into open light, which (his holy name be prayſed) is now brought to paſſe in our dayes, to our ineſtimable comfort, and his euerlaſting glory.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>And if it can be proued that either the Proteſtants Church or any other Church but ours, hath mightely ouerthrowne theſe foreſayd ſectes, and other of all ſortes, I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT hath bene already proued ſufficiently, that the true Catholike Church which is ledde onely, by the worde of God, as a moſt infallible rule, hath ouerthrowne hereſies of all ſortes. But the popiſh church which refuſeth the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weapon, by which hereſies are cut downe, to be ſufficient for that purpoſe, neuer was nor ſhall be ſtrong enough to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with heretikes, therefore ſhe practiſeth to vanquiſh thoſe whom ſhe counteth for heretikes, not by authoritie of the Scriptures, but by fire and ſworde, and cruell warre, as appeareth by her dealing with the Waldenſes, Albigenſes, Bohemians, and in our dayes with the true Chriſtians. But where her power of fire and ſword could not preuayle, there hath ſhe not ouerthrowne ſuch as ſhe condemneth for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, namely the Grecians church, &amp; all other churches of Aſia, and Aphrica, which vnto this day will not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge her doctrine to be Catholike, nor her authoritie to be lawefull. Wherefore ſeeing the Popiſh church neither
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:23111:12"/>hath confuted thoſe that are heretikes in deed, nor ſubdued thoſe whom ſhe counteth to be heretikes, if you be as good as your worde, you recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="article">
                  <head>The fiueth article conteyneth 3. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Againe, what Church is that, which hath exerciſed by Chriſtes appointement, Diſcipline, vpon offendors in all degrees?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ONely the Church of Chriſt, by Chriſtes appointe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hath exerciſed true diſcipline vpon offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, Although by meanes of perſecution, ſhe could not alwayes practiſe the ſame as ſhe would.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>And for that purpoſe, hath continually executed lawes and Canons Eccleſiaſticall, with Excommunication, Degrada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuſpenſion, and ſuch like.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe Church of Chriſt only, hath had lawful authority to exerciſe diſcipline: but as it is ſaid before, ſhe hath not continually practiſed the ſame, becauſe ſhe could not, being hindered by perſecution, and diſperſion. Concerning excommunication, ſhe hath practiſed it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word of God, and againſt ſuch offendors, as the ſcripture iudgeth worthy of that ſeuere puniſhment: As for degradation, and ſuſpenſion, it may be doubted what you meane by them: if you vnderſtand by degradation, that ſuch perſons as the Church hath tried vnmeet, either for doctrine or manners, to execute the office of preaching, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the ſacraments, ſhe hath diſplaced and reiected from that charge: ſhe hath alſo practiſed drgradation: And if you meane by ſuſpenſion, that when the accuſation of a mans doctrine or life was vncerteine, that ſhe hath willed him to ceaſe from executing his office, vntill his cauſe were tried either good or euill, ſhe hath alſo vſed ſuſpenſion: but if by degradation and ſuſpenſion, you meane thoſe fooliſh and wicked ceremonies, which the popiſh church now vſeth and ſo termeth, I deny that euer the true Church of Chriſt had to do with ſuch degradations and ſuſpenſions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:23111:13"/>
                     <head>3 <hi>Proue me this geere to procede from Proteſtants, or from any other Church than the Catholike, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is proued before, that true diſcipline belongeth to the true Church, wherof we are a part, which Church is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proued to be the ſpouſe of Chriſt, becauſe ſhe is ruled in all thinges by his onely voice: And therefore all congregations of heretikes, which departe from the true worde of God, though they take vpon them, to exerciſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, by excommunication or otherwiſe, it is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, and leſt of all the Popiſh church, where remaineth nothing of diſcipline and excommunication, but the very names: for what call you popiſh diſcipline? is not that it which they vſe in Lent, whiſking men on the heades, and women on the handes, with white roddes which they them ſelues call diſcipline? Or is it the ſeuere puniſhment that they vſe againſt offendors by excommunication, ſuſpenſion, interdighting &amp;c. Firſt, it is manifeſt they haue no excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication by Chriſtes appointment, for neither it is exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the perſons appointed by Gods worde, nor againſt ſuch offendors only as God his word appointeth: for wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as our Sauiour Chriſt appointeth the order of that diſcipline, to the Congregation of ſuch as are wiſe, godly, and carefull of mens health, which firſt ſhal labor by fatherly admonition and wholeſome exhortation, to bring the offendors to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, whome if they refuſe to heare, they are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted for hethens and publicanes, the Pope contrariwiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreth the ſame to profane and vnreligious officers, which are more deſirous to gaine the fees of abſolution, than by bringing the party to repentance, to ſaue him from excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication. Moreouer whereas by Gods worde, excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication is the laſt and moſt greuous puniſhment, that the Church can enioyne againſt any, of whom there is any hope of ſaluation, and therefore ought not to be practiſed but for haynous offences, the Popiſh church maketh it ſerue for euery trifling matter, yea for pettie debts and all, then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in interdightings &amp; ſuſpenſions of places, as churches
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:23111:13"/>and townes, yea whole realmes, for one mans faulte: what likelineſſe hath this vnto the diſcipline of Chriſtes church ſet forth in the ſcriptures, and practiſed by the fathers? with what face can you Papiſtes affirme, they haue diſcipline, in their Church, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all penaunces for moſt horrible offences, may be bought out for money, and an open market thereof ſet vp at Rome, with the prices rated, what men muſt pay for euery thing that they buye: as abſolution for him that hath killed his father, or mother, brother, ſiſter, or wife Turones 4. Ducat. 1. Ca. line. 5.8. For an heretike before he haue abiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red 36. Turones. and 9. ducates. For a witche 6. Turones. 2. ducates. For a prieſt that is a Sodomite, or hath lyen with brute beaſtes 36. Turones. 9. ducates. For a nonne that hath bene a common whore both within and without her Abby, with diſpenſation that ſhe may be able to receiue any digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, in her order, yea to be Abbeſſe, 36. Turones. 9. ducates. And ſo for all other offences, with diſpenſations, inhibitions, rehabilities, licences, relaxations, commutations, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>perinde Valeres Marcamas</hi> and the deuill and all for money: wherefore except you be to impudent, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this to be Chriſtian diſcipline, be as good as your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="article">
                  <head>The ſixth article conteyneth 3. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Againe from what Church, did all the ſolemne ceremonies, and obſeruations, all feſtiuall dayes, all faſtes, all diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and varieties of ſeruice, by diuerſities of ſeaſons, and times of the yeare, (proceede.)</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FIrſt you muſt vnderſtande, that we deteſt and abhorre all your beggarly ceremonies, which you counte holy and ſolemne obſeruations: for we know, that God is not to be worſhipped with ſuch thinges but that the true worſhippers muſt worſhip him in ſpirit &amp; veritie <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. And ſeeing we know God, or rather are knowen of him, we will not regarde the weake and beggarly elementes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are deſtitute of God his worde, which onely is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:23111:14"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="19" facs="tcp:23111:14"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:23111:15"/>able to geue them ſtrength and eſtimation? as for your feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uities, in the honour of creatures, we doe likewiſe abhorre them. we honour the Sainctes as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſayeth for imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but we do not worſhip them for Religion. <hi>De vera Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligione cap.</hi> 55. Where he alſo ſaith. <hi>Quare honoramus eos cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, non ſeruitute.</hi> We honor them with loue, and not with ſeruice. And as he doth often affirme, that it is Idolatry to builde churches in the honour of Sainctes, ſo is it as great Idolatry, to inſtitute feſtiuall dayes, in the fauour of the ſame Sainctes. As for the feſtiuall dayes that were vſed in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, although they might haue bene omitted, without any hurt of Chriſtian Religion, yet were they not kept in the honour of creatures, as they are of the Papiſtes, but only for the memorie of the Martyrs, and other Saincts, that their good life might be followed. Your faſtes are alſo abhominable: for they are nothing elſe but abſtinence from meates, created of God to be receiued with thankesgeuing, which <hi>S. Paule</hi> affirmeth to be the doctrine of Diuells 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. Alſo your diſtinctions and varieties of ſeruice, becauſe they conſiſte moſt of blaſphemous prayers to dead Sainctes, and ſometimes to damned ſpirites, with fooliſh leſſons, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſes, verſicles, &amp;c. Lewde lies and vncertaine tales, which you reade and ſing, as God his ſeruice, they are all abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. In vaine do they worſhip me, ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt, teaching for doctrine the preceptes of men. <hi>Math.</hi> 15. Alſo it was decreed in the Councell of Laodicea, the 59. chapter, that nothing ſhould be ſong or reade in the Church, but the Canonicall bookes of holy Scripture: wherefore if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande whence your ceremonies, feſtiuall dayes, faſtes, and varieties of ſeruice did proceede? I aunſwere plainely, out of the bottomles pit of hell.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>From whence did all thinges, yet indifferently for moſt part, obſerued, and allowed, on both ſides, from whence did they proceede?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IF you had vttered what thinges you meane, that are ſo indifferently allowed on both ſides, we might better haue aunſwered: but ſeeing you haue not, we muſt coniecture
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:23111:15"/>what you meane: if you meane any thinge that is allowed without controuerſie on both ſides, it did either proceede from the ſcripture of God, or from the primitiue Church or elſe it a thing meerely indifferent, but if it haue no grounde in holy Scripture, nor example of the primitiue Church, nor iudged meerely indifferent, it not indifferently obſerued for the moſt parte, nor yet allowed on both ſides.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>And if it can be proued, that the Proteſtants Congregation, or any other Church, but ours, hath inſtituted and ordered all theſe, or any of theſe, for the comelineſſe and honour of God his houſe, I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Haue aunſwered before, that the Proteſtants Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, geueth you leaue to bragge, that you are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentors of all theſe Idolatrous ſuperſtitions, &amp; falſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of God, and yet becauſe you offer ſo liberally to recant, if it can be proued that any Church but yours, hath inſtituted and ordered all theſe thinges, you ſhall he are what can be ſaide. Firſt, your great doctor <hi>Durande,</hi> plainely affirmeth that many of your ceremonies, and ſolemnities, had not their firſt inſtitution of your church, but were taken of the Iewes or Gentiles: And it may eaſily be proued, that many of your ceremonies, were inſtituted of heretikes, as your holy water which you ſay you vſe to put men in minde of their baptiſme, was deriued of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heretikes called Heme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robaptiſtae, which were, <hi>baptized euery daye. Epiphan. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. Of the Oſſenes, you tooke the great eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of water, ſalt, oyle, breade, &amp;c. and vſe to ſweare by them, as they did. <hi>Epiph. contra Oſſenes</hi> 19. Of the ſame here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, you receiued the ſuperſtition of reliques, for they vſed to take the ſpittle, and other filth from the bodies of <hi>Marthys,</hi> and <hi>Marthana,</hi> which were of the ſeede of <hi>Elxai,</hi> that is, great Sainctes with them, and vſed them to cure diſeaſes, as <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> witneſſeth, at Canterbury were kept the clowtes,
<note place="margin">In peregrina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis ergo.</note> that <hi>Thomas Becket</hi> did occupy to wipe of his ſweate, and to blow his noſe on, which were kiſſed as holy reliques, and thought alſo to be holſom for ſicke folkes: of the ſame heretikes you
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:23111:16"/>learned to commande the people to pray, in an vnknowene tongue, as <hi>Elxai,</hi> the great Pope of thoſe heretikes ſayde: <hi>Nemo quaerat interpretationem, ſed ſolum in oratione haec dicat.</hi> Let no man ſeeke the interpretation, but onely ſaye theſe wordes in his prayer. Which wordes were in a ſtrange tong, either the Hebrue, or the Arabike. <hi>Epiphan. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> 19. Likewiſe the Marcoſians when they baptized, vſed to ſpeake certaine Hebrue wordes, that the ignorant people might maruell the more at them, as you doe in Baptiſme <hi>Ephata, &amp;c. Epiph. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>haer.</hi> 34. To make the Images of Chriſt, and of the Apoſtles, and to ſenſe them, you learned of the heretikes called Gnoſtici, and Carpocratirę, <hi>Epip. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. in the preface <hi>Epiph. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>haer.</hi> 27. and <hi>Irenaeus lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 23. Of the Valentinians, you learned to haue in price the ſigne of the croſſe, and to abuſe the places of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the ſame ſuperſtitious vſe: as, God forbidde that I ſhoulde reioice but in the croſſe of Chriſt, &amp;c. <hi>Irenaeus lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Epiphan. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>haereſ.</hi> 31. Of the Heracleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, you learned to annoynte men at the point of death, with oyle, and balme, and to caſt water vpon dead men, with inuocations. <hi>Epiph. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>haereſ.</hi> 36. Of the Cayanes, you learned to call vpon Angels. <hi>Epiph. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>haereſ.</hi> 38.</p>
                     <p>Of the Marcioniſtes, you learned to giue women leaue to baptize. <hi>Ep. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tom. Haer.</hi> 42. <hi>George,</hi> Biſhop of Alexandria, inuented beares to carry deade corpſes, charging all men to vſe them for his owne aduantage, as doe you Papiſtes your bearing clothes &amp; other toyes for funerall pompes. <hi>Ep. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Haer.</hi> 76. Of the Colliridianes, you learned to make i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of the virgine <hi>Marie,</hi> &amp; worſhip them &amp; her, with of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of candells, &amp;c. as they did of cakes, &amp;c. <hi>Ep. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Haer.</hi> 79. Of the Meſſalians or Martirians, you learned to ſhaue your beardes and to let your lockes grow long. <hi>Ep. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Haer.</hi> 80. Of the Pharizees, you receaued your ſuperſtitious maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king garments, which you call <hi>amictus dalmaticus,</hi> and <hi>pallia,</hi> as witneſſeth <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> in his epiſtle to <hi>Acacius,</hi> and <hi>Paulus.</hi> Laſt of all what ſay you to the ceremonies, feſtiuities, faſtes, and ſolemnities, vſed in the Greeke Church, and in the other Oriental Churches, if they be ſufficient to make their church
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:23111:16"/>Catholike, why doe you count them heretikes, and Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes? if they be not ſufficient, why doe you reaſon of the inſtitution of the like, to proue your Church Catholike? You ſee that proued which you deſired, play the honeſt man ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="article">
                  <head>The 7. article conteineth 3. demaundes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Further I aske them, what Church that is, which hath brought forth out of her wombe, ſo many noble perſonages, of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, Confeſſors, Doctors, Virgines, and holy Sainctes, of all ſortes, all which both they and we doe outwardly profeſſe, by the continuance of the Callendare, which yet is vſed euery where, to be Sainctes in heauen.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FVrther I aunſwere you, that all true Sainctes, whether they were Patriarches, Prophets, Apoſtles, Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſtes, Martyrs, Confeſſors, Doctors, Scholars, Virgins, wiues, widowes, married, or vnmarried, are all children of that Church, in whoſe fellowſhip we reioyce to be, and are our deare brethren and ſiſtern begotten in Ieſu Chriſt by the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, and we all hold of one head Ieſus Chriſt, as members of his myſticall body. We all beleue to be receaued into that glory that they are, by the onely meane that they were, that is by the mercie of God in Chriſt Ieſus. But as for the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the Callendar, we haue litle reſpect vnto it, yea no regard at all, to vſe it either as a recorde, or as a regiſter of thoſe whom we acknowledge to be Sainctes in heauen. Let the Prince make you aunſwere, for the continuance of ſuch calle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, for we haue not to do with them. Neuertheleſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you ſpeake of a Callendar, that is vſed euery where, you declare that you haue ſmall experience in Callendars, for euery cuntry hath them diuers in moſt dayes, except holy dayes, and in ſome cuntry Callendars, ſuch dayes are feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall to thoſe Saincts, that haue not their names in Callendars of other cuntries, yea it may be doubted whether they haue their names in the booke of life. If you ſawe a Bohemians Callendar, perhaps if you ſhoulde ſee <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi> and <hi>Ierom</hi>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:23111:17"/>of <hi>Prage,</hi> which your church condemned for heretikes, and haue as ſolemne feaſtes, in the Callender as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paule,</hi> wherefore we acknowledge thoſe to be Sainctes in deede, not whoſe names are continued in the Callendars of men, but are written in the booke of life of the Lambe, that was ſlaine from the beginning of the worlde. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 13.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>And if it can be proued by any man of the Proteſtancy, that theſe were either, of the Proteſtants Congregation, or beleefe when they were aliue.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is ſufficiently proued againſt you, of the Papiſtrie, that all they, whome we acknowledge to be Sainctes in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, are members of the ſame myſticall bodie of Chriſt, that we are, and hold the onely foundation that we hold, which is Ieſus Chriſt, and although ſome of them, builded ſtraw and ſtubble vpon the ſame foundation, yet the Lorde hath not imputed it unto them. But wheras the Patriarches, Prophetes, and Apoſtles were cheefe lightes and pillers of the church of Chriſt, the daye is yet to come, and euer ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, that all you of the Papiſtrie, ſhalbe able to charge vs with one pointe of our faith, contrary to the doctrine of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches, Prophetes, and Apoſtles.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>Or canonized and allowed for Sainctes by the Proteſtantes Church, when they were deade, or by any other Church, then I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>OVr Church doth take all them that ſhew the fruicts of a liuely faith, to be Sainctes, while they be aliue, as well as after their death, and we ſay with Dauid: <hi>All my delight is in the Sainctes, that are in the earth Pſal.</hi> 16. and with S. Paule: <hi>VVe labour to comprehend with all Sainctes, what is the length, breadth, depth, and heigth, and to know the loue of Chriſt. Epheſ.</hi> 3. Finally the ſcripture teacheth vs, to call all them that are ſanctified in the bloude of Chriſt, and called to the felowſhip of the Goſpell, holy and Sainctes of God. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wherefore, your Popiſh church
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:23111:17"/>doth great iniury to the Sainctes of God, firſt, becauſe ſhe doth not ſo accompt them while they liue, and ſecondly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe referreth the canonization of them only to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope, who not for their holy life, maketh them Sainctes, but for the holy honger of golde, as appeare by Pope <hi>Iuly</hi> 2. who woulde not canonize king Henry the ſixt, at the requeſt of king Henry the ſeuenth, vnder an vnreaſonable ſumme of money. If that ſumme of money had bene paide, he ſhoulde haue bene a ſainct, though he had not deſerued, not for his vertue. And becauſe that ſumme of money was not paide, he might not be canonized, although his godlineſſe neuer ſo much deſerued. Againe of what force your Canonization is to be eſteemed, we may learne by a fact of Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. who condemned, digged vp, and burned the bodie of <hi>Hermannus in Ferraria,</hi> 30. yeares after his buriall, who had bene worſhipped for a ſainct aboue 20. yeares before, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth <hi>Platina</hi> and other. <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth canonized Pope <hi>Liberius,</hi> which was an Arrian, as <hi>S. Hieronym</hi> teſtifieth, Moreouer if I ſhoulde likewiſe demande of you, what Pope canonized <hi>Peter, Paule,</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, yea moſt of the Martyrs of the primitiue Church, you ſhall neuer be able to ſhew me either what Pope did it, or that any Pope did it: For ſeeing none may canonize but the Pope in your church, and you can not proue that the Pope hath canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed the Apoſtles and cheefe Martyrs, you can not proue that your church hath canonized the Apoſtles and principall Martyrs. But it is manifeſt that your canonization is taken from the heathen Senate of Rome, which chalenged autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to make Gods, whome they them ſelues thought beſt. And if I ſhoulde rippe vp the moſt parte of thoſe Sainctes, which haue bene canonically canonized by the Pope, it were an eaſie matter to finde them heretikes, traitors, Necro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancers, Whoremongers, and whores, as you may reade in <hi>Bales Votaries</hi> aboundantly, beleuing his reporte no farther than he alleageth his Author, where you maye finde it. Wherefore it were wiſedome for you, not to depend vpon the Pope his Canonization, but vpon God his approbation, and to recante.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="article">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:23111:18"/>
                  <head>The 8. article conteyneth 3. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>And becauſe Chriſt as S.</hi> Paule <hi>ſayeth, hath eſtabliſhed in his Church ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prechers, ſome Teachers, and Doctors euen vntill his comming againe, I aſke the Proteſtant, what Church that is, which is able to ſhew &amp; proue, the continuance and vſe of the ſaide functions euer ſence Chriſtes time by plaine accompt of orderly Succeſſion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Aunſwere the Papiſt, <hi>that Chriſt hath geuen to his Church ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophetes, ſome Euangeliſtes, ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and Teachers. Epheſ.</hi> 4. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. And we are able to ſhew &amp; proue, that we continue in that vnitie of faith and knowledge of the Sonne of God, for which ende ſuch offices were ordeyned. But whereas you require, that we ſhould ſhew you the continuance of thoſe functions by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ſucceſſion from Chriſtes his time vntill our dayes, you declare how ſmall ſkill you haue in vnderſtanding the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for the offices of <hi>Apoſtles, Euangeliſtes, and Prophetes,</hi> were not appoincted to continue alwayes in the Church, but for a time, vntill the Goſpell had taken roote in the worlde. Moreouer, whereas you requier an orderly ſucceſſion, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to perſons, or places, you are neuer able to proue, that any ſuch thing was promiſed to the Church, that we ſhould ſhew you the performance there of in our Church. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we doubt not, but God hath alway ſtirred vp ſome faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full teachers, that haue inſtructed his Church in the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie poinctes of Chriſtian Religion. Although the worlde and the church of Antichriſt did not alwayes ſee them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>And is able to name you by the hiſtories of all ages, the notable perſonnes of all the forſaide ſtates, in their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment and miniſterie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>A Gaine I anſwere you, that you are not able to name, me any text of ſcripture, by which you can proue, that al theſe offices muſt haue perpetual co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:23111:18"/>in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of Chriſt, nor yet that any of them ſhould kepe an ordinarie ſucceſſion of place or perſons: But contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, ſeeing it was prophecied that the church ſhould flie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wildernes, that is, be driuen out of the ſight and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the wicked, and be ſo narrowly perſecuted of the Romiſh Antichriſt for a longe ſeaſon, it were a token our church were not the true church, if we could name ſuch no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table perſons as you ſpeake of, in all ages floriſhing in their gouernment and miniſterie. And it is a good argument, that the Popiſh church is not the church of Chriſte, becauſe it was neuer hidden ſence it firſt ſprang vp, in ſo much that you can name all the notable perſons in all ages in their gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and miniſterie, and eſpecially the ſucceſſion of Popes, you can reherſe in order vpon your fingers, in which bead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roole, neuertheleſſe you muſt name many tyrants, many traytors, one whore, many whoremongers, many Sodomites, many murtherers, many poyſenors, many ſorcerers, and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cromancers, and from <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, all blaſphemous heretikes, and Antichriſtes. But our church, which hath not had ſo many regiſters, chroniclers, and remembrancers hath perhaps fewer, but yet honeſter men to name: we can name <hi>Peter, Paule, Mathew, Iohn, &amp;c. Marke, Luke, Timothe, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabus, Epaphras, &amp;c. Inſtinus, Irenaeus, Cyprianus, Athanaſius, Hylarius, Ambroſius, Auguſtinus, &amp;c. Gyldas, Bertramus, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilius de Padua. Ioan. de Ganduno, Bruno Andagauenſis VVick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, Iohn Hus, Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prage, &amp;c.</hi> With the firſt, namely Apoſtles, Euangeliſtes, and Prophets, we conſent wholly in all pointes of doctrine, with the reſt, in the cheefe and moſt ſubſtantiall articles of faith, alwayes agreeing with any man, ſo farre as he agreeth with the worde of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>And if he can proue vnto me, that their Church hath neuer lacked the ſame appointed officers, or that any Church or Congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but ours hath kept that charge, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FOr ſome of thoſe officers I haue twiſe aunſwered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that they were not ordeined, to continue alwaies, with the church, wherefore they are not to be exacted
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:23111:19"/>of vs, but ſuch officers as are neceſſary for the conſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God his people in the vnitie of faith and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, our Church hath neuer lacked, although in time of the great defection and Apoſtaſie whereof <hi>S. Paule</hi> doth propheſie 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. there were but few, as there were but fewe members of Chriſt his Church notwithſtanding that through iniurie of the time, the remembraunce of all their names is not come vnto vs. And although we could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe in order as many ſucceſſions in our Church as the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes boaſt of in theirs, yet were that nothing to proue it to be the Church of Chriſt, which muſt be tried onely by the Scriptures, as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſayth in his booke <hi>de vnitate Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae,</hi> againſt the Donatiſtes <hi>cap.</hi> 16. <hi>Sed vtrum ipſi Eccleſiam te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neant, non niſi diuinarum Scripturarum canonicis libris oſtendant, quia nec nos propterea dicimus nobis credere oportere quod Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae ſumus, quia ipſam quam tenemus commendauit Mileuitanus Optatus, vel Mediolanenſis Ambroſius, vel alij innumerabiles no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae communionis Epiſcopi, &amp;c.</hi> But whether they holde the Church or no, let them ſhew none otherwiſe, but by the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall bookes of holy Scripture, for we our ſelues doe not therefore ſay that men muſt beleeue vs that we are in the Church becauſe we hold the ſame Churche, which <hi>Optatus</hi> of Mileuitum hath commended, or <hi>Ambroſe</hi> of Millayn, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Biſhops of our communion. Euen ſo we require at the Papiſtes handes that ſhewe them ſelues to holde the Church not by ſucceſſion of Biſhops, or rehearſing of their names, but onely by the Scriptures: for although we did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe innumerable names of Biſhops in orderly ſucceſſion on our ſide we would not require men to beleue vs, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe we proue the doctrine of our Church by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Scriptures. But as for the popiſh church, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath nor euer had any of thoſe officers which <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of, for Apoſtles, Euangeliſtes, and Prophets, ſhe can chalenge by no reaſon, ſeing ſhe refuſeth to be tried by their doctrine vttered in their writings, in ſteede of paſtors &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ſhe hath wolues, du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me dogges, or falſe prophets, which either teach not at all, or elſe teach the doctrine of deuills &amp; the dreames of men. And further I would deſire none other
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:23111:19"/>place in all the Scripture, to ouerthrow the popiſh Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie (which is the greateſt glory of their Church) then this place of <hi>Paule, Epheſ.</hi> 4. he ſpeaketh of Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, Prophets, Paſtors and teachers. But where are Popes, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls, popiſh archbiſhops, Biſhops, Preeſtes, Deaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Subdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, Exorciſtes, Cantors, Acolyts, Oſtiares, Monkes, Friars, Chano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Nunnes, &amp;c. Wherfore I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude that all theſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh orders are no offices in the Church of Chriſt. And eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſeeing the Apoſtle both in this place <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. by theſe offices proueth the vnitie of minde, he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth no Pope as one ſupreme head in earth, which might be very profitable (as the Papiſts ſay) to mainteine this vnity: for if there had bene any ſuch office appoynted of God, <hi>S. Paule</hi> in no wiſe woulde haue omitted it, eſpecially when it made ſo notably for the confirmation of his purpoſe, which was vnitie. To conclude if it be ſufficient, or any thing worth, to rehearſe the names of them that haue orderly ſucceded in all ages in the biſhops ſees, in an outwarde face of the Church, the Greeke Church is able to name as many as the Latine Church, and in as orderly ſucceſſion. Wherefore if you be as ready to performe as to promiſe, you recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="article">
                  <head>The nynth article may be deuided into nyne demaundes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>And for the neceſſary vſe and execution of the foreſayd of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, they muſt further be aſked, what Sacramentes the Proteſtants miniſtred for the ſpace of a thouſand yeares togither, in which they confeſſe their congregations to haue bene neare or elſe wholy hidden.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THey miniſtred thoſe Sacramentes which Chriſt did inſtitute, namely the Sacrament of baptiſme, and the Sacrament of the body and blood of Chriſt, at ſuch times as the cruell tyrannie of you Papiſtes did not hinder them, to come togither for ſuch purpoſes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>VVhat correction they kept and diſcipline for offenders.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:23111:20"/>
                     <p> THey did vſe ſuch diſcipline as was vſed in <hi>S. Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> time, when perſecution hindered not the free courſe of it. As he doth often complaine in the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aboue rehearſed. They did admoniſh ſecretly, before witneſſes, and when perſecution ſtayed them not, they did alſo excommunicate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>To whome they did preach their Fayth.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>TO ſuch as woulde geue them hearing, as <hi>VVickleue</hi> to the Engliſhmen: <hi>Iohn Hus</hi> to the Bohemians: <hi>VValdo</hi> to the Frenchmen, and ſo of the reſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="demand">
                     <head>4 <hi>How did they reproue hereſies?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THey reproued hereſies, by the worde of God, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſufferinge of your tyrannie: the one you may reade in their workes, that are yet extant of <hi>VVick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, Bertrame, Hus, &amp;c.</hi> The other in hiſtories of your owne writers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="demand">
                     <head>5 <hi>VVhere did their principall Paſtors ſit in Iudgement?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Might aſke you where the Apoſtles did ſit in iudgement and you are neuer able to ſhew me, for I reade as one ſayth: that they ſtoode often to be Iudged, but I neuer reade that they ſat in iudgement vpon others: And ſo I aunſwere of the principall Paſtors of our Church, eſpecially in time of perſecution.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="demand">
                     <head>6 <hi>VVhere did they gather as in Councells to try the trueth of doubtfull matters?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AS God gaue them reſpight, from your tyrannie, they had conference one with an other: and as for doubtes, they tried them by the worde of God, and not by number of voyces, as you do in your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, as for the places where they met, is nothing at all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall, at Prage, at Lyons, at Merindol, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="demand">
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:23111:20"/>
                     <head>7 <hi>How might Chriſtian men, iuſtly offended with ſome of their brethern, haue ſought out your officers or Congregation, to make complainct of him?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>YOu are void of all reaſon that in a perſecuted church, will require all thinges to be ſo formall and orderly, as in time of peace and quietnes, I could choke you with putting like caſes of your Church. If a number of Papiſtes be carried priſoners into Barbarie, or Turkey, what Sacraments, what diſcipline, what Iudgement haue they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, if one be offended with his brother how ſhall he come to your officers, or to your Church to complaine. In ſuch caſes where the ordinary authoritie of the Church is hindred by perſecution, or otherwiſe, the rule of <hi>S. Paule.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. may ſerue and ought to be obſerued: <hi>If any that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a brother be a fornicator, or couetous, or an Idolater, or a ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, or a drunkard, or an extorcioner with ſuch one eate not.</hi> So that if a Chriſtian be iuſtly offended with his brother, he ought to abſteine from his company. And if he may haue ordinary au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, he may complaine further.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="demand">
                     <head>8 <hi>Or how if it had liked any man to haue ben baptized of them, or to haue receiued the communion of them, or to haue bene married of them, or to haue ioyned them ſelues in Fayth and Religion to them, how might I ſay that ſecret, contemptible, and vnknowne company, be founde in this caſe?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HE muſt haue ſought them out as well as he could, &amp; if he had bene perſwaded, that they onely miniſtred the Sacraments, &amp; Eccleſiaſticall rites, ſincerely, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word of God, it were no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for him to find them, ſeing he knew by whom he was ſo perſwaded, and of them might alſo be informed where he ſhould haue them. I maruell you are not aſhamed to demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theſe queſtions, as though it were materiall to diſcuſſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vs hath the Church, to haue the Church ſo manifeſt,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:23111:21"/>that euery man may ſee it. Doe you not remember how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſchiſmes haue bene euen in the popiſh church, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> twenty, and ſometime two Popes at once, ſometime three, &amp; ſometime fower, which of them ſhould a ſimple Papiſt take for head of the Church, eſpecially in the 22. ſchiſme, which laſted 39. yeares: one Pope ſitting at Rome, an other at A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinion, either hauing his court, either hauing and making Cardinals, either curſing other. Or in the 23. ſchiſme, when the queſtion was of one of the higheſt pointes in all popery, and is not yet throughly decided among them: Whether the Pope be aboue the Councell, or the Councell aboue the Pope. In the time of theſe ſchiſmes how might a man haue founde out, which was the true Church, which was Chriſtes vicare in earth, which had the right Sacraments and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentalls, to which Popes court ſhould he appeale, where did the principall Paſtors ſit in iudgement, &amp;c. How ſhould coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells be gathered, which Pope ſhoulde confirme their actes, &amp;c, When you are able to aunſwere theſe queſtions, for your owne church, then you may better require them of ours. As for that ſecrete, contemptible, and vnknowne company of our Church, in the ſight of the world, was neuertheleſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, glorious, and knowen to our Sauiour Chriſt, and the liuely members of his body.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="demand">
                     <head>9 <hi>If therefore you can ſhew me, that any man euer ſought Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or knowledge of trueth, ſacrament, or faith, or any helpe of Saluation at the Proteſtants ſecret and cloſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, or any other where, but of Gods knowen Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ALthough it be to litle purpoſe to aunſwere this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande, becauſe it is no reaſon to ſay, theſe thinges hath not bene, becauſe chronicles make no mention of them: yet that all men maye ſee, how farre you ouerſhoot your ſelfe, I wil partely ſatisfie your requeſt. <hi>Charles</hi> the great ſought knowledge of the trueth of the ſacrament of <hi>Bertramus. Iohn,</hi> Duke of Lancaſter, and diuers other noble men were inſtructed in our Religion by <hi>VVickleue.</hi> The land
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:23111:21"/>of Bohemia, was conuerted by <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi> and <hi>Hieronym</hi> of <hi>Prage,</hi> and ſought the ſacraments of them. Finally, you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes forget the Greeke church, which you do not accompt parte of the Catholike church, and yet you can not deny but men haue ſought Iuſtice, ſacramentes, faith, &amp;c. of it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if a man might truſt you vpon your worde, you recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="article">
                  <head>The 10. article conteyneth in effect but 2. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Moreouer I aſke whether for all theſe many hundreth of yeares or euer els before there was any temporall Prince or Potentate, that offered to be vnder God a miniſter of Iuſtice and an executor of Chriſtian lawes in the right of your Congregation, that euer maintained by lawes Ciuill or other, your Faith and Congregation, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BEfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> general defection, it is an eaſy matter, to name you the Emperours and Princes which both offered, to be miniſters of Iuſtice in the right of our church, and alſo mainteyned our faith and Congregation, by Ciuill lawes, as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the greate, <hi>Iouinianus, Valentinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Theodoſius, Archadius, Honorius, Marcianus, Iuſtinianus, Mauricius,</hi> and diuers other. But when the kinges of the earth had committed fornication with the great whore of Babylon (as the holy Ghoſt foreſheweth <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17. and 18.) it is no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice to our cauſe if we can not ſhew, any of them that haue mainteined our Religion. Yet becauſe you make ſo gentle an offer vpon the triall of ſuch a matter, which is of ſmall force either to the hurt of our cauſe or the maintenance of yours, I will let you vnderſtande what I haue reade for this purpoſe. Not doubting but other which haue reade much more, and ſeene more auncient hiſtories than I, can ſhew you a great deale more. I paſſe ouer as to well knowen, how many of the Grecian Emperors reſiſted the ſetting vp of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, in ſo much that in the Greeke church to this daye they can abide none in their temples, likewiſe I paſſe ouer <hi>Charles</hi> the great, who wrote a booke againſt Images, which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:23111:22"/>is in printe, who alſo declared, that he liked not the hereſie of the reall preſence and tranſubſtantiation, which in his time was in forging, in that he called <hi>Bertrame,</hi> to declare his minde of that matter, as appeareth by his booke, which is alſo in printe. I will not rehearſe thoſe princes, that contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Popes lawes, defended their prieſtes, that were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried: For although theſe and ſuch like defended ſome parte of the trueth, which we holde againſt you, yet leſt you ſhould obiect, it was but in ſome one or two pointes, I paſſe them ouer with ſilence. But <hi>VVickleue,</hi> I wene, you will not deny, but he was of our Church and Religion. And I reade that king <hi>Edward</hi> the third, both in his Parliament holden <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1371. and at other times with diuers other noble men defended his cauſe: in ſo much that ſo long as he liued, all the popiſh byſhops, coulde do him no harme, yet did he openly inueigh againſt the Pope, calling him Antichriſt, and all popiſh doctrine without any couller or diſſimulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both in the vniuerſitie of Oxeford, where he was reader, and alſo in his ſermons abroade, as appeareth by his bookes and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh homilies, which yet are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to be ſeene, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnleſſe he had bene ſupported, and maintained by the kinge and other potentates, coulde neuer haue continued ſo long as he did. Further, haue you not hearde of <hi>Ziſca,</hi> and <hi>Procopius,</hi> two mighty Capitaines, which defended the Bohemians from the tyrannie both of the Emperour, the Pope, and almoſt all the Princes of Germanie? For what cauſe did <hi>Paule</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1466. condemne <hi>George,</hi> a noble and a worthy Prince, king of Bohemia for an heretike? and depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him of his kingdome? was it not for defending the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes in his dominion? Thus you ſee that ſome Princes and Potentates haue not onely offered but haue in deed, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hand to defend our church, which you thought vnable to be ſhewed, wherfore I chalenge your promiſe, you muſt recante.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="article">
                  <head>The 11. article is ſo confuſe that it is harde to bring it into any certeine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:23111:22"/>
                     <head>1 <hi>Againe I requier of the Proteſtants to declare by good hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, or by reaſonable likelihoode when the true church, as they compt theirs, decayed?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Anſwer, euen in the Apoſtles time, there aroſe many he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies which did not a litle trouble the Church, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after the Apoſtles time, while the fathers of the church were earneſtly occupied, in reſiſting of horrible hereſies, by the craft of Satan, ſome errors and abuſes crept into the true Church of Chriſt, which at the firſt becauſe they were ſmall, and men occupied in greater matters, were either not eſpied, or not regarded: as may be knowen by the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges of <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> Martyr, and <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> two of the moſt aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient writers, ſence the Apoſtles time. <hi>Iuſtinus,</hi> was in this er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, that he thought that the Angells luſted after women and therefore were turned into Deuills. It ſeemeth alſo, that the Church in his time, was in ſome error, about ſecond ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages and diuorcements. <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> affirmeth, that our Sauiour Chriſt liued here 50. yeares, which he ſayeth was receyued of them that heard it, euen of the Apoſtles mouthes. Alſo both he and <hi>Papias,</hi> which was before him and was the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>S. Iohn:</hi> are charged by <hi>S. Ieronym, in Catalogo Script. Eccl</hi> to haue held this error, that Chriſt ſhould raigne a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares after the Reſurrection here in the fleſh, whereby it is manifeſt, ſeeing theſe auncient fathers, and pillers of the Church were thus ſtayned with errors, that the Church in their time, could not be free from the ſame. And ſo it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the true Church decayed immediatly after the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>VVhat yeare the Religion of the Papiſtes came in and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ALthough many abuſes and corruptions were entred into the church of Chriſt immediatly after the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, which the deuill planted as a preparatiue for his eldeſt ſonne Antichriſt. Yet we may well ſay,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:23111:23"/>that the religion of the Papiſtes came in, and preuailed, that yeare in which the Pope firſt obteyned his Antichriſtian ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation, which was in the yeare of our Lord 607. when <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> the third, for a great ſumme of mony, obteyned of <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas,</hi> the trayterous murtherer, and adulterous Emperour, that the Biſhop of Rome ſhould be called and counted, the head of all the Church. Since that time, that deuiliſh hereſie hath alwayes increaſed in error, vntill the yeare of our Lord 1414. in which the Councell of Conſtance decreed, to robbe the people of the Sacrament of Chriſt his blood. From this time it hath againe decaied, being mightely ſubdued by the bright beames of the Goſpell, ſhining in the world, and at the length ſhall be vtterly deſtroyed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>VVhether all their true Church was ſo ſoundly ſleeping, that none could preach againſt it as it firſt entred.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHen the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of Antichriſt was in all power of lying ſignes,
<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 2. Math. 24.</note> and wonders, in ſo much (that if it were poſſible) the very elect ſhould be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and a general departing from the faith was foreſhewed, and the Church to be driuen into the wildernes, what maruell were it? if none of our Church could preach againſt it, as it firſt entred: yet becauſe you ſpeake of the firſt entring of popiſh religion, which dependeth chiefly vpon the Popes authoritie, you ſhall heare, that when it firſt began to aduaunce it ſelfe, there wanted not ſome, either to preach or write againſt it. When <hi>Victor,</hi> biſhop of Rome about the yeare of our Lord 200. paſſed the bondes of his authoritie, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicating of all the Churches of Aſia, many biſhops withſtoode him, and eſpecially <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> biſhop of Lyons, and <hi>Policrates</hi> of Epheſus, as witneſſeth <hi>Euſebius, libro</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 25. <hi>Eccle. S. Cyprian,</hi> alſo reproueth <hi>Cornelius,</hi> biſhop of Rome, for that he was moued by threatning of heretikes to receiue their letters, &amp; did not ſend them backe into Africa, to their own biſhop <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 3. Alſo when <hi>Stephanus,</hi> biſhop of Rome, was bold to communicate with <hi>Baſilides,</hi> and <hi>Martialis,</hi> two Spamards, that were iuſtly excommunicated and depoſed by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:23111:23"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhops of their owne prouince, &amp; ſought to reſtore them: <hi>Cyprian</hi> and his felow biſhops of Aphrica, being required to giue their aduiſe, gaue counſell, that in no wiſe they ſhoulde be receiued, not a litle blaming <hi>Stephanus,</hi> that beinge far of, and ignorant of their cauſe, he would take vpon him, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend ſuch wicked men. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 4. Likewiſe when the ſame <hi>Stephanus,</hi> threatned excommunication to <hi>Helenus</hi> and <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milianus,</hi> and almoſt all the Churches of Aſia, becauſe they thought that ſuch as were baptized by heretikes, ſhoulde be baptized againe: he was miſliked by <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of Alexandria, and diuers other godly biſhops, as appeareth by his Epiſtle wrytten to <hi>Xyſtus. Euſeb. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ap.</hi> 5. Cyprian alſo reproueth him very ſharply, for the ſame opinion, accuſing him of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and contumacy <hi>Epi.</hi> ad <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>npeium,</hi> and in his epiſtle to <hi>Quintinus,</hi> he ſayth plainly, that Peter himſelfe was not ſo arrogant, nor ſo preſumptuous that he would ſay he held the primacy, &amp; that other men ſhould obey him as his inferiors. When <hi>Anaſtaſius, Innocentius, Zozimus, Caeleſtinus,</hi> biſhops of Rome all on a row, chalenged prerogatiue ouer the biſhops in Aphrica, by forginge a faiſe Canon of the Nicene Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, they were withſtoode by all the biſhops of Aphrica, who decreed, that none vnder paine of excommunicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould appeale to any biſhop, beyond the ſea, <hi>Concil. Aphrican. cap.</hi> 92. and that the biſhop of the chiefe ſee, ſhould not be called prince of prieſtes, or higheſt prieſt, but onely biſhop of the chiefe ſee. <hi>Conc. Aph. cap.</hi> 6. When <hi>Celeſtinus</hi> by ſhop of Rome dealt hardly with the Nouatians, <hi>Socrates</hi> teſtifieth, he could doe not good with them, becauſe they enuied his ambition, ſaying that the biſhoprike of Rome, like as of Alexandria, was long before growen beyonde the bondes of prieſtbood, into foreine lordſhip. <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. By theſe examples it is plaine, that although the myſterie of iniquitie, beganne to worke in <hi>Victor, Cornelius, Stephanus, Anaſtaſius, Innocentius, Zozimus, Bonifacius,</hi> and <hi>Caeleſtinus,</hi> yet it was reproued, by ſome godly men: as <hi>Irenaeus, Polycrates, Dionyſius Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus, Cyprianus,</hi> the Councell of Aphrica, and <hi>Socrates</hi> the Hiſtoriographer.</p>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:23111:24"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:23111:24"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="demand">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:23111:25"/>
                     <head>4 <hi>VVHether all nations ſodenly and in one yeare were moued to the doctrine of the Papiſtes, no one man of all their true Church neither preaching, teaching, writing, nor attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any thing againſt it, or making mention of it.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHen the ſcripture telleth vs, that the myſterie of iniquitie, preparing for the generall defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and reuelation of Antichriſt, wrought euen in <hi>S. Paules</hi> time 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. it is foly to aſke, whether ſodenly and in one yere all Religion was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted. And yet all nations neuer conſented to the doctrine of the Papiſtes, for as it hath bene often ſaide, the Greeke church, and other Orientall churches, hath neuer receiued the Popiſh religion, in many cheefe pointes, and eſpecially, in acknowledging the Popes authoritie: what preaching, teaching, and writing hath bene againſt it, is ſhewed before, and ſhalbe more declared hereafter.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="demand">
                     <head>5 <hi>VVhether ſodenly all bookes of ſeruice were altered?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>NO forſoothe, but by litle and litle, in the Latine Church: as for the Greeke &amp; Orientall Churches, neuer receyued nor vſed your Latine ſeruice bookes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="demand">
                     <head>6 <hi>VVhether in a moment, the Maſſe was ſaide in ſteede of other Apoſtolike Communion?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHen <hi>Durande,</hi> your owne doctor, ſheweth what Pope ſewed on euery patche, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to your Maſſe, it were foly for vs to ſay: it came in ſodenly, and impudencie in you, to affirme that it came whole from the Apoſtles, which was ſo long a framing in ſo many peeces.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="demand">
                     <head>7 <hi>VVhether men beganne ſodenly to praye for the ſoules de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:23111:25"/>
                     <p> FIrſt it is manifeſt, that men had no warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t out of God his worde to pray for the dead: and it can not be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for 200, yeares after Chriſt, by any credible au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, that it was vſed in the Church: wherefore it is certeine, that it was firſt planted by the deuill, as were other abuſes: And becauſe it hath a pretence of Charitie, decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſimple men the ſooner. Yet did it not ſo preuaile, in the primitiue Church, that they durſt define, what profit the ſoules receyued thereby: for <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his 3. Homelie, vpon the firſt Chapter of the Epiſt. to the Philippians, ſayeth: <hi>Procuremus eis aliquid auxilij, modici quidem, attamen iuuemus eos.</hi> Let vs procure them ſome helpe, ſmall helpe truely, but yet let vs helpe them. Likewiſe, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in the 9. booke and 13. Chapter of his confeſſions, where he prayeth for his father and mother, declareth how vncertaine he was of that matter, one while he feareth the danger of euery ſoule that dieth in <hi>Adam:</hi> An other while he beleueth, that they neede not his prayer, yet he deſireth God to accept the ſame, and moue other men to remember them in their prayers: Thus it is neceſſary that they wander, which leane vnto mens tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions without the worde of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="demand">
                     <head>8 <hi>Sodenly required the helpe of Sainctes in heauen?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>VVHether ſodenly or by litle and litle, men were brought to ſuch ſuperſtition, that they requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red helpe of Sainctes, it maketh litle matter, ſeeing it is contrary to the worde of God, and the example of the primitiue Church, for 200. yeares after Chriſt. Yet it is to be thought, that it grew vp, as other er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, by litle and litle. And <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> in his booke, <hi>De cura pro mortuis agenda,</hi> wearieth him ſelfe, and in the ende can define nothing, in certeine, how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sainctes in heauen ſhould heare the prayers of men, on earth. Such doubtfulneſſe they fall into, that leaue the word of God, and leane to traditions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="demand">
                     <head>9 <hi>Sodenly the tongue of common prayers altered?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:23111:26"/>
                     <p> FIrſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Greeke church, &amp; other churches both in Aſia, &amp; Aethiopia, neuer receiued the Latine tongue: but to this day continue in their vulgare tongue. The We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne Church, for the moſt parte all ſpake and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode Latine, as the ſea coaſt of Aphrica, Italye, Fraunce, Spayne, Britayne: as for Germany, was lately conuerted to the faith. Then ſeeing they ſpake Latine, and had their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer in Latine: The tongue of their common prayer was not altered, but their ſpeach was altered from the tongue of their common prayer: and this was not ſodainely, for it was more than twelue hundred yeares after Chriſt before it was taken for a Catholike doctrine, that common prayer ſhould be vſed in latine. <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> preached in latine &amp; all the people vnderſtoode him, and that they might the better vnderſtand him, he doth vſe ſuch phraſes and termes which were not pure latine, but commonly vſed of the people as <hi>Oſſum,</hi> and <hi>Faenerare, &amp;c.</hi> But ſoone after his time, when the Gothes, and Vandalles, oueranne the Empire, the latine tongue which before was not pure among the people, began daily to be more corrupted, and yet remained after a ſort la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, vntill the yeare of our Lorde 768. when <hi>Charles</hi> the great began to raigne in France, and long after: for within the time of his reigne, which was 47. yeares, a Councell was hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at Turon, in France, what yeare it is not certeyne, but it is probable, that in the latter ende of his empire, in which it was decreed, that euery biſhop, ſhould haue certeine homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies <hi>Et eaſdem quiſque apertè ſtudeat transferre in ruſticam Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manam linguam aut Theotiſcam, quo facilius cuncti poſſint intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere quae dicuntur. Turon.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. And that euery one ſtudye to tranſlate them plainly, into the ruſticall Romane tongue or into the Theotiſce tongue, that all men may more eaſily vnderſtand what is ſayd. By this Canon, it is euident, that at this time, the people vnderſtood the Latine tongue, though it were very rude and ruſtical. And where the Canon preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth the ſame homilies to be tranſlated either into the rude latine tongue, or into the Theotiſce tongue. Although this word <hi>Theotiſca,</hi> ſeeme to be corrupted, yet it is moſt certeine
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:23111:26"/>that they meant Dutch tongue, for as much as <hi>Carolus mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> had a great part of Germanie vnder his dominion, and the Germanes, as neuer throughly ſubdued by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, neuer throughly receiued the latine tongue. Yet it is manifeſt, that they vnderſtoode their common prayer in the latine tongue, though not perfectly, becauſe the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non ſayth: <hi>Quo facilius &amp;c.</hi> That all men may more eaſely vnderſtand, ſignifying that they vnderſtood the pure latine tongue though hardely and not perfectly. About the yeare of our Lorde 813. the knowledge of the latine tongue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne more and more to weare awaye, from amongeſt the common people, which when the biſhops perceiued, they decreed in the Councell of Magunce, <hi>cap.</hi> 25. that euery Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye, and holy daye, there ſhoulde be a ſermon in ſuch ſorte, that the common people might vnderſtand it: and in the 45. Canon. they decreed, that euery Chriſtian, ſhoulde learne the Creede, and the Lorde his prayer, <hi>Et qui aliter non potue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, vel in ſua lingua hoc diſcat,</hi> that is, And he that can not, yet let him learne it in his owne tongue. Whereby they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that they deſier to reteine the latine tongue ſtill, but rather than the people ſhoulde be ignorant, they commande them to learne their prayers and beleefe in their mother tongue. Alſo by the 43. Canon, wherein they iudge that no preeſte can ſaye Maſſe alone, it appeareth that the people commonly vnderſtood the latine ſeruice: for they aſke how he ſhoulde ſaye: <hi>Dominus vobiſcum,</hi> and admoniſh the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to lifte vp their heartes, and diuers like ſayinges, where there is none by him but him ſelfe. Nowe if the people vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode not theſe ſayinges, it were all one, whether they were preſent or abſent. Alſo in the Councell of Rhenes, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in Fraunce about the ſame time, the like decree was made <hi>cap.</hi> 15. that biſhops ſtudie to preache ſermons, and homelies of the holy fathers ſo that all men maye vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, according to the property of their tongue. Finally in the Councell of Laterane holden vnder Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1215. in which Councell tranſubſtantiation was firſt eſtabliſhed, the 9. chapter, it was plainely decreed that foraſmuch as within one citie and dioceſſe people of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:23111:27"/>diuers languages be mingled together, hauing vnder one Faith, diuers rites, and maners, we ſtreightly commande, that the biſhops of ſuch cities and dioceſſes, prouide able men, which according to the diuerſitie of their rites, and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, celebrate vnto them, the diuine ſeruice, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſacramentes, inſtructing them both by worde and example. Hereby it appeareth, that when the latine tongue, was either almoſt, or altogether growen out of the common peoples vnderſtandings, order was taken that common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhould be ſayed and ſacramentes miniſtred in the mother tongue of euery nation. But the biſhops which ſhoulde haue ſeene it put in execution, either negligently omitted it, or willingly refuſed to doe it, becauſe it was more for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to kepe the people in blinde ignorance. So thus I haue ſhewed, that ſodenly the tongue of common prayer, was not altered.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="demand">
                     <head>10 <hi>Tell me what yeare of our Lorde, vnder what Emperour, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what Pope, by whome theſe thinges were wrought, vpon what occaſion, this marueillous mutation was made?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHo can tell the originall of euery blind cuſtome and peuiſh tradition, of euery olde error and fooliſh faſhion it is ſufficient to ſhew, that theſe thinges haue no grounde in the ſcripture of God, they were not taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, nor receiued in the church that followed immediatly after them, and then we are bolde to ſay, with <hi>Tertullian:</hi> This preiudice there is againſt all hereſies, how ſoeuer they came vp or when ſoeuer they ſprange vp, That is true that was firſt, and that is falſe, that is latter, therefore from the beginning it was not vſed to praye for the deade nor to the deade, from the beginning common prayer was not in an vnknowen tongue. Wherefore prayer for the deade and to the deade, with prayer in a ſtrange tongue are falſe, when ſoeuer they beganne, or how long ſoeuer they continued.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="demand">
                     <head>11 <hi>VVho preached againſt it, what hiſtorie maketh mention
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:23111:27"/>of it, who of all your Paſtors preached againſt it, was God his Church ſo voide of the ſpirit of Trueth, and ſtrength, that euen then when it moſt floriſhed, it had none that durſt open againſt ſuch corruption of religion, as it entred in, and when it might ſoone haue bene repreſſed?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BEfore you demande what yeare the religion of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes came, in and whether it came in ſodenly: and as though we ſhoulde aunſwere that it came in ſodaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you demande, who preached againſt it &amp;c. This is to fight with your owne ſhadowe: for we ſay not that it came in ſodainely, but that it entred by ſmall degrees at the firſt and therefore was leſſe eſpied by the true Paſtors, eſpecially being earneſtly occupied againſt great hereſies, and open aduerſaries, that ſought to beate downe the cheefe founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Chriſtian faith, as the Valentinians, Marcioniſtes, Manichees, Arrians, Sabellians, and ſuch like monſters. So when Satan had gotten in one foote, by ſuch craftie pollitie, he neuer reſted, vntill he had thruſt in his whole bodie, with the power of Antichriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="demand">
                     <head>12 <hi>If it coulde not, ſhew me then what yeare of the Lorde this mutation was made, and who of all the true preachers did with ſtand this doctrine?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>SO often as you demande one thinge, ſo often muſt I aunſwere after one ſorte, this mutation was not all in one yeare, nor in one hundreth yeares, nor in one thouſand of yeares, for tranſubſtantiation no ſmall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of your religion, was not decreed vntill the yeare of God 1215. what preachers haue withſtoode your doctrine at diuers times are declared before in the aunſwere to the 8. Article 2. demande.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="demand">
                     <head>13 <hi>Or note the name of him that euer firſt preached any article of our doctrine: and if we note you not by their names, euery one of your Capitaines, and the ſeuerall errors that they tought and the time, and the yeare when they aroſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:23111:28"/>againſt the former receyued trueth and the Councells in which they were orderly condemned if I, ſaye this can be done of your ſide towarde vs, or if we doe it not for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of your Church and religion, I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Haue noted in the anſwere to the 6. article 3. demande, the names of diuers heretikes, that firſt preached diuers articles of your religion, and further I note vnto you <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius,</hi> and <hi>Coeleſtius,</hi> which tought that free will without grace coulde doe ſomewhat towardes eternall ſaluation, and that grace was geuen according to merite, which article you teach alſo with culler of a diſtinction <hi>De congruo &amp; condigno,</hi> which is a meere cauill: for God is as much bounde vnto congruitie, as to dignitie or worthineſſe, and as he can doe nothing againſt worthineſſe, no more can he doe any thing againſt congruitie, which is a kinde of Equitie. And whereas you bragge, to note vnto vs euery one of our Capitaines &amp;c. except you note vnto vs the Patriarches, Prophets, Apoſtles, Euangeliſtes, and Chriſt himſelfe, you ſhall neuer be able to performe that you promiſe, for we teache nothing but the eternall trueth of God, wherefore we refuſe not to be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted heretikes, if you can proue, that we holde any one arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of faith, contrarie to the ſcripture: you may perchaunce note the names of them, that preaching the trueth of our doctrine, againſt your receyued errors, were accounted of the world for heretikes, but you muſt proue that their opinions are contrarie to the worde of God, or els all your labour is in vaine: we confeſſe alſo, that ſome articles of our doctrine, were taught by heretikes, as there was neuer no hereſie, which had not many thinges common with true Religion, but yet in thoſe poinctes they were no heretikes, neither did they erre. Yea but you will ſaye, they were condemned for thoſe opinions, as erroneous. I will not diſſemble, that which you thinke the greateſt matter. <hi>Aerius</hi> tought, that prayer for the deade was vnprofitable, as witneſſeth both <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtinus,</hi> which they compte for an error, but neither of them both, reproueth it by the ſcripture. Wherefore, if <hi>Aerius</hi> had not bene an Arrian, this opinion coulde not haue
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:23111:28"/>made him an heretike. Alſo he tought that faſting dayes are not to be obſerued, if he eſpied the ſuperſtition of faſting dayes and reproued it, that was no error at all. But if <hi>Aerius</hi> was an heretike, for denying prayer for the deade to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, why were the <hi>Heracleonites,</hi> accuſed of hereſie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they buried their deade with inuocations <hi>Epiph. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 36. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> alſo by authoritie of <hi>Philaſter</hi> chargeth the ſame <hi>Aerius,</hi> with abſtinence from fleſh, if this be an hereſie, then be all Papiſtes heretikes, which compte abſtinence from fleſh an holy faſt. Againe you will bring in <hi>Iouiniane,</hi> which affirmed that virginitie was no better than mariage, which if it be well vnderſtoode, is no error at all: for although virginitie in ſome caſes and reſpectes, and for ſome perſons is better than mariage: yet is it not ſimply, that is in all reſpectes and caſes, and for all perſons better than matrimonie. And if he tought further that ſuch as coulde not conteine, though they had vowed Virginitie, ſhoulde neuertheleſſe be maried, this was the doctrine of <hi>S. Paule:</hi> It is better to marry than to burne. And <hi>Epiphanius</hi> was of the ſame iudgement, although he compte it an offence to marrie after their vowe, yet he ſayeth: It is better to marry then to burne. <hi>Melius eſt itaque vnum peccatum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere, &amp; non plura, &amp;c.</hi> It is better to haue one offence, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then many. It is better for him that is fallen from his courſe, openly to take a wife according to the lawe, and to repent longe time that vowe of his virginitie, and ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine be brought into the Church, as one that hath done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, as one that is fallen and broken, and hauing neede to be bound: rather then to be wounded daily, with priuy darts of that wickednes, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuill putteth into him. So know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Church to preach, theſe are the medicines of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. <hi>Ep. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Haer.</hi> 61. this medicine the popiſh church wil not acknowledge, but will ſeparate them from their wiues, as they did in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> times. <hi>S. Ieronym</hi> alſo, who was a moſt bitter enemy vnto <hi>Iouinian,</hi> plainly affirmeth, that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they which haue profeſſed virginitie, ſhoulde liue incontinently, they ought to marrie. <hi>Sanctum Virginum propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitum &amp; coeleſtis angelorúmque familiae gloriam, quarundam non
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:23111:29"/>bene ſe agentium nomen infamat. Quibus aperte dicendum eſt, vt aut nubant, ſi ſe non poſſunt continere, aut contineant, ſi nolunt nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere. Epi. ad Demetriadem.</hi> That is: The name of certeine vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines, which behaue them ſelues not well, doth blemiſh the holy purpoſe of virginitie, and glory of the heauenly and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelike family. To whom muſt be plainly ſayd that either they ſhould marry, if they can not conteyne, or elſe conteyne if they will not marry. Note well this ſaying of <hi>S. Ieronym,</hi> the great aduancer of virginitie, and diſpraiſer of mariage. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer if <hi>Iouinian</hi> taught that faſting, abſtinence from certeyne meates, and other bodily exerciſe of them ſelues profit litle, his doctrine agreeth with <hi>S. Paul.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. but if he taught (as he is charged) that ſuch thinges profited nothing at all, we agree not with him in that opinion. Laſt of all <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> ſhall be brought in, who wrote againſt inuocation of Saincts, ſuperſtition of reliques, and other ceremonies, him <hi>Ieronym</hi> reproueth or rather rayleth on him: for his reaſons are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth that he hath againſt him, therefore howſoeuer <hi>Ieronym</hi> eſtemed him in his rage, if he had none other opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions contrary to the truth: we doubt not to acknowledge <hi>Vigilantius</hi> (as many godly and learned Biſhops of his tyme did) for a true preacher and reprehender of that ſuperſtition whereunto <hi>Ieronym</hi> was to much addict, although he doe ſomewhat qualifie the matter. If any man thinke his reaſons to be effectuall, let him marke this one, that he vſeth, and thereby iudge the reſt, he ſayth of the Martyrs: <hi>Sequuntur ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, &amp;c.</hi> They follow the lambe whether ſoeuer he goeth. If the lambe be euery where, therfore they which are with the lambe, are to be thought to be euery where. Beſide this euill conſequence, conſider what perilous aſſertions theſe be: that the lambe is euery where, &amp; that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> martyrs are euery where, this is to deſtroy the humanitie of Chriſt, and to giue diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnto the Martyrs: for Chriſt concerning his humanitie, according to which, he is called a Lambe, is not euery where, but in one place alone, as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſayth <hi>Ep. ad Dardanum</hi> 57. <hi>Secundum hanc formam non eſt putandus vbi<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> diffuſus,</hi> that is: According to this forme it is not to be thought, that he is diffuſed euery where. Againe no creature is euery where, in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:23111:29"/>more places than one, at one time. Wherefore to ſay that the ſoules of Martyrs, be euery where, is to deny them to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures and ſo make them gods. I doubt not but <hi>S. Ieronym</hi> if he had quietly conſidered theſe abſurdities, would haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked them as erroneous and hereticall: but while he rather followed affection, then iudgement, you may ſee how he was deceaued. Thus ſeeing we haue noted to you the names of diuerſe heretikes, which firſt preached certeyne articles of your doctrine, and you are not able to name any, which prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched any article of our doctrine, but the ſame was conſonant to the Scripture. If you were as ready to performe, as you are to promiſe, you ſhould recant.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="demand">
                     <head>14 <hi>And for that purpoſe becauſe the gouernment of the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome is moſt miſliked of them, and yet moſt noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly knowne by euery hiſtorie, let them name the Pope that firſt brake of the courſe of his forefathers beleefe, &amp; regiment in any article of fayth or neceſſary Chriſtian v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Haue named before <hi>Victor,</hi> which was the firſt that went about to vſurpe authoritie ouer other Churches. Alſo I haue named <hi>Boniface,</hi> the third, which was the firſt that chalenged to be vniuerſall biſhop: For <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great ſayeth: <hi>Nemo meorum deceſſorum hoc prophano vocabulo vti voluit,</hi> That is: None of my predeceſſors woulde vſe this prophane worde. The ſame <hi>Gregorie,</hi> as <hi>Hulderichus,</hi> biſhop of Auſpourge doth teſtifie, was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt that compelled prieſts to liue vnmaried, which afterwarde when he ſaw the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience, he reuoked. Thus hauing named diuers Popes that firſt brake the courſe of their fathers faith, and regiment &amp;c. and more coulde rehearſe but for auoyding prolixitie, I cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge your promiſe that you muſt recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="article">
                  <head>The 12. article hath 3. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Item I aſke what kinde and order of ſeruice, or common prayer, what waye of miniſtring of the ſacraments your
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:23111:30"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="47" facs="tcp:23111:30"/>
                           <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                              <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="48" facs="tcp:23111:31"/>Church had: before Papiſtry (as you call it) did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in the worlde?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IVſtinus</hi> Martyr, in his ſecond Apollogie to the Emperour, declareth plainely what order of ſeruice and miniſtration of ſacramentes our Church had before Papiſtry preuay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. On the daye called Sonday (ſayth he) there is a mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting together of all them that dwell in the Citie or in the countrie, and the monumentes of the Apoſtles, or the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges of the Prophetes are reade vntill it be thought ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, when the reader hath made an ende, he that is our ouerſeer (or cheefe miniſter) maketh a ſermon of admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and exhortation to follow thoſe good thinges that are reade. After this we all ſtande vp together and make our prayers, and as we haue ſaide before, when our prayers are ended, there is brought forth bread and wine &amp; water, and the cheefe miniſter, doth likewiſe with all his might yelde pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and thankesgeuing, and the people aunſwereth Amen. Then is made diſtribution to euery one and receyuing of thoſe thinges for which thankes was geuen, and to them that be abſent, it is ſent by the deacons. Such as are riche and willing doe geue almes what they will, &amp;c. By this one autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, it may be ſeene though other might be brought, what order of ſeruice and miniſtration of ſacraments our Church vſed before Papiſtry gat the vpper hande.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>Shew one booke of Communion or what els you liſt that was in Engliſh, or lacked prayer for the departed, or inuocation of Sainctes in heauen, or that wanted oblation, or ſacrifice, or that charged a number to receyue, or els that the preeſt coulde not conſecrate nor ſay Maſſe, himſelfe, or ſhew any note in a Communion booke, that the people ſhoulde take the ſacrament for plaine breade, or that they ſhould geue no honor to it, ſhew this booke or any leafe or line of this booke.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT may trouble a wiſe man to aunſwere all the queſtions that a foole can propounde: you requier to ſee a booke of Communion in Engliſh, or that lacked &amp;c. When it is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:23111:31"/>confeſſed, that the Engliſh nation receiued their religion firſt from Rome, at ſuch time as Religion there was verie corrupt, what marueill is it, if we can not ſhewe you ſuch a Communion booke as you require, but we can eaſily ſhew you out of the ſcripture, the the Communion ought to be miniſtred in the vulgare tongue, that prayer for the deade and to the deade ought not to be vſed, that the ſacrament ought not to be turned into a ſacrifice, that there ought to be a communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of many receauers and not a priuate maſſe, that the ſubſtance of the bread is not changed, that the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the ſacrament are not to be honored: theſe I ſay we can proue out of the worde of God, the Catholike wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the olde Church. And though perchaunce, it wilbe harde to finde a communion booke in Engliſh, yet haue I founde you a canon of the Laterane Councell, that it ought to haue bene tranſlated into Engliſh; yet are there founde diuers monumentes of Antiquitie, as Prayers, Pſalmes, and Homilies, &amp;c. in the olde Engliſh or Saxons tongue, in which the reall preſence, tranſubſtantiation, and other poinctes of Popiſh doctrine are plainly confuted. There may be ſhewed you alſo Bybles both the olde Teſtament and New in the Engliſh tongue of diuers tranſlations, in olde written hande. Alſo great bookes of Engliſh homilies inueighing directly againſt the Pope and all Popiſh doctrine in olde Engliſh written hande, with diuers other ſmall treatiſes and pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets of like matters, if theſe woulde do you any good, you might haue the ſight of them, when you pleaſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>Or any Church or Congregation that euer had any Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſeruice but ours, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe Church of the Brytannes before <hi>Auguſtine</hi> came in, with Romiſh ſeruice, had they not trow you Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall ſeruice? which continued in the faith of Chriſt euen from the Apoſtles time. The Grecians alſo &amp; Orientall churches, haue they not vnto this day, their Authenticall ſeruice? which is not yours? If you can not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny this, you ſhould recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="article">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:23111:32"/>
                  <head>The 13. article hath 2. demaundes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Furthermore I requier to know what ſhoulde be the cauſe that the Proteſtants themſelues, doe receiue all Byſhops, Prieſtes, Deacons, and other officers ſpirituall of all ſortes of our Catholike church, and doe admit them as men law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and ſufficiently ordered, both to preach, miniſter ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and to exerciſe ſpirituall iuriſdiction no leſſe, but rather more, than if they were of their owne ordering, where we of the Catholike church, doe not acknowledge any man of their calling to be any whit more fitte for any ſpirituall function than other lay men.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>ALthough all godly men wiſhe more ſeueritie of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline to be vſed, in receyuing them that come out of hereſies to ſerue in the Church, than is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſed in England: yet you are highlie decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, if you thinke we eſteeme your offices of Biſhops, prieſts, deaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, any better than the ſtate of lay men, but farre worſe: for we iudge them to be nothing els but Antichriſtianitie, hereſie, and blaſphemie. And therefore we receiue none of them to miniſter in our church, except they forſweare your religion: And ſo their admiſſion is not an allowing of your ordering, but a new calling vnto the miniſterie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>Therefore vpon this preſumption that they doe not onely admit our miniſtring of ſacraments, but alſo the lawfull ordering of the miniſters for the ſame, if they can ſhew me why our church hauing by their owne conſent and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing lawfull prieſtes and biſhops ſhould not be the true church, I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>YOu preſume to much as I ſaide before to thinke that we receiue your orderinge to be lawfull or your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring of ſacraments to be pure. And if you gather, that we admitte your miniſtration of ſacraments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we doe not rebaptize them that were baptized by you,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:23111:32"/>we maye likewiſe gather that you admit our miniſtration of ſacraments, becauſe you doe not rebaptize them that are baptized of vs, nor marrie againe thoſe that are married in our Church: wheras you compt mariage to be a ſacrament, ſo that our accepting of your doings doth no more allow your church, than your accepting of our doinges, doth allow our Church. And as touching the ſacrament of Baptiſme, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you reteyne the Inſtitution, in baptizing in the name of the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt: and in aſmuch as the ſacraments take not their effect of the miniſter, but of God, we receiue it: as of other heretikes which likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine the Inſtitution. Wherefore there is no cauſe why you ſhoulde thinke we allow yours to be the true Church there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by: So that there is good cauſe why you ſhoulde recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="article">
                  <head>The 14. article hath 5. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Alſo I demande what furniture or commodity in ſeruing God the Chriſtianity of any age, or any part of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome had euer by your Congregations?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe ſeruice of God hath ſmall neede of furniture in outwarde thinges: for God being a ſpirite, is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped with outward pompe but with ſpirituall and inwarde reuerence. And as for other furniture that is neceſſary, was decreed to the Church by the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and his ſucceſſors, that were of our Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Antichriſt. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the Church was in better caſe, before ſuch furniture was graunted, than it was ſince. Therefore it is a ſmall reaſon to chalenge the Church of Chriſt by outwarde furniture.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>VVhat Churches did you builde for your aſſemblies and ſeruice?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>OVr aſſemblies were kept in ſecret places, long time after Chriſtes Aſcenſion, in moſt cuntries, that were ſubiect to the Romane empire. Wherefore the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:23111:33"/>of materiall churches proueth nothing at all the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to be members of the myſtical Church, that is the body of Chriſt. Howbeit in ſuch realmes and cuntries where the faith of Chriſt, was receiued by publike authoritie, as in this lande of Brytaine, there were churches builded as our Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles declare. And when <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> had geuen peace to the Church: he alſo builded Oratories and great Synagoges called <hi>Baſilicas,</hi> for our aſſemblies and ſeruice.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>VVhat Biſhoprickes for the gouernment of the Church did you finde?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AS the church continued longe without materiall churches, ſo alſo without large poſſeſſions, for the lyuing of biſhops, yet in Brytiſh Church our hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries make mention that the poſſeſſions and places of the Pagane Flamines, and Archiflamines were conuerted to the vſe of Eccleſiaſtical biſhops and archbiſhops, ſo ſoon as <hi>Lucius,</hi> the king receiued the faith. Alſo the ſame hiſtories do teſtifie, that when <hi>Auguſtine</hi> came into Britayn, there were ſtill 7. biſhops and one archbiſhop among the Britaines. And in the Romane Empier <hi>Conſtantinus,</hi> and other Chriſtian Emperors appointed great poſſeſſions for the mainteyning of the miniſters of the Church.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="demand">
                     <head>4 <hi>VVhat Vniuerſities, Schooles, or Colledges, did you euer erect?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe Church of God hath alwayes had ſchooles, or Vniuerſities for the mainteinance of godly learning. For the firſt Colledges of monkes in ſolitary places, were nothing els, but Colledges of ſtudentes, that were after, as occaſion ſerued, taken to ſerue in the Church, as appereth by <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> in his booke <hi>De Sacerdotio,</hi> where he ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                        <hi>Baſilius,</hi> who was a Monke with him, was taken by violence and made a miniſter of the church, as he him ſelfe was afterwarde. Alſo in the biſhops houſe was a col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſtudentes: and our hiſtories teſtifie, that at Bangor, in Wales was a great Vniuerſitie of learned men. Alſo of late
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:23111:33"/>dayes, you may heare that diuerſe Vniuerſities, Scholes, and Colleges are erected by Proteſtants, in Germanie, and other contries that haue receiued the goſpel: As at Wittemberge, Geneua, Zuriche, Conigſperge in Pruſſia, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="demand">
                     <head>5 <hi>Name one Church, not builded in all faſhions, as well for the making of the chancells, the forme of the aultars, the vſe of the chalices, the ſignification of the veſtiments, as alſo for the ſpeciall intent of the builders thereof. Name one of them in the whole Church of Chriſt, either erected for your Faith, Church, &amp; ſeruice, or not prepared, in all ſorts for catholike practiſes: Proue vnto me that any of all thoſe thinges were euer prouided for any other ſeruice and Religion then ours, or that they be monuments of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Fayth and Church then the common Catholike, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HEre are many wordes to litle purpoſe. What if it were graunted that all churches that now remaine were builded by Papiſtes, and for popiſh vſes, what had you wonne thereby. The ſame chalenge might the Idolaters haue made to the Apoſtles: Shew vs a temple in all the worlde that was not builded by Idolaters, and to mainteyne Idolatrie? Certeinly they could ſhew none when the Temple of Ieruſalem was deſtroyed. But for all your bragges, we are able to ſhewe that ſuch Churches as were builded by true Chriſtians were not builded to ſuch ende as yours are: for they were all builded in the honour of God, and the moſt of yours in the honour of creatures: for wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as you haue one Church in the honour of Chriſt, you haue neare a thouſand in the honour of Sainctes: For <hi>Baſilius ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnus</hi> in his 141. epiſtle proueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt to be God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath a Temple. For <hi>Omne Templum Dei Templum eſt.</hi> Euery temple is the temple of God. Alſo <hi>Didymus,</hi> in his booke <hi>De ſpiritu ſancto,</hi> which <hi>S. Ieronym</hi> tranſlateth, vſeth the ſame reaſon and to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> in the ſame matter is very plentifull: as in his booke <hi>De vera Religione cap.</hi> 55, ſpeaking of the Sainctes he ſayth: <hi>Quare honoramus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:23111:34"/>charitate non ſeruitute, nec eis templa conſtruimus, &amp;c.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we honour them with loue and not with ſeruice, neither doe we build temples vnto them: for they wil not be ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored of vs becauſe they know that we our ſelues when we are good, are the temples of the higheſt. In this ſaying beſide his iudgement for building of temples, note that he will not haue Sainctes to be honored with ſeruice, which he calleth <hi>ſeruitus,</hi> and is the ſame that <hi>dulia</hi> is, contrary to the Papiſtes which will worſhip them with ſeruice called <hi>dulia,</hi> or <hi>ſeruitus.</hi> Alſo in his 174 epiſtle to <hi>Paſcentius,</hi> he ſayth, the holy Ghoſt could not haue our bodies to be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples except he were God, And in his Enchiridion <hi>ad Laurentium, cap.</hi> 56. he ſayth: <hi>howe ſhould he not be God which hath a temple?</hi> Alſo in the 8. booke <hi>cap.</hi> 27. <hi>De ciuitate Dei. Nec tamen nos ijſdem martyribus templa, &amp;c.</hi> he ſayeth: Chriſtians builde no temples vnto Martyrs which were to make them gods. And in the 22, booke <hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>De ciuitate Dei. Nos autem Martyribus noſtris non templa ſicut dijs, ſed memorias ſicut hominibus mortuis, quorum apud Deum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uunt ſpiritus fabricamus. Nec ibi erigimus altaria in quibus ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficemus martyribus, ſed vni Deo &amp; martyrum &amp; noſtro ſacrifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um immolamus: ad quod ſacrificium ſicut homines Dei, qui mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum in eius confeſſione vicerunt, ſuo loco &amp; ordine nominantur, non tamen à ſacerdote qui ſacrificat inuocantur, Deo quippe non i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſis ſacrificat quamuis in memoria ſacrificet eorum, quia Dei ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos eſt non illorum. Ipſum verò ſacrificium corpus eſt Chriſti quod non offertur ipſis quia hoc ſunt &amp; ipſi.</hi> that is: We truely do not build temples to our martyrs as vnto gods, but memories as vnto dead men whoſe ſoules liue with God. Neither doe we there ſet vp aultars in which we ſhould ſacrifice vnto the martyrs, but to God onely which is God both of the martyrs and of vs, doe we offer ſacrifice: at which ſacrifice they are named in their place and order, as men of God which haue ouercome the world in his confeſſion: yet are they not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon by the Prieſt that doth ſacrifice, for he offereth ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God and not to them although he doe ſacrifice in their memorie, becauſe he is the Prieſt of God and not of them, and the ſacrifice is the body of Chriſt which is not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto them becauſe they them ſelues are the ſame. Here
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:23111:34"/>alſo beſide building of churches, note that no ſacrifice ought to be offered to Martyrs, but prayer is a ſacrifice, therefore it ought to be offered onely to God. Secondly, that Martyrs were not called vpon in tyme of the ſacrifice but onely na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for remembrance. Thirdly, that Altares were not buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the honor of Martyrs or other Sainctes as they be in Popiſh churches: as our <hi>Ladies</hi> altar. <hi>S. Peters</hi> altar. <hi>S. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences</hi> altar &amp;c. Fourthly, that the bodie of Chriſt, which he ſayeth was the ſacrifice that was offered, was not the naturall body of Chriſt but his myſticall bodie, becauſe he ſayeth the Martyrs and it are all one, whereby it is manifeſt, that he meaneth the ſacrifice of thankes giuing offered to God for the redemption of his church by the death of Chriſt. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if this one place were well wayed, it will interpret and aunſwere all places of the auncient doctors, where mention is made of ſacrificing the body of Chriſt at the time of the communion. But to returne to building of churches the ſame Auguſtine, <hi>contra Maximinum Arrianum. Lib. Titul.</hi> 11. hath theſe wordes: <hi>Nunc ſi templum alicui ſancto angelo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentiſſimo de lignis &amp; lapidibus faceremus, anathematizaremur a veritate Chriſti, &amp; ab Eccleſia Dei, quoniam creaturae exhibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remus eam ſeruitutem quae vni tantum debetur Deo? Si ergo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegi eſſemus faciendo templum cuicun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> creaturae, quomodo non eſt Deus verus cui non templum facimus, ſed nos ipſi templum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus?</hi> that is: If we ſhoulde builde a temple of wodde and ſtones to any holy and moſt excellent Angel, ſhoulde we not be accurſed from the Trueth of Chriſt and from the Church of God, becauſe we ſhould ſhew that ſeruice vnto a creature which is due onely vnto God? Therefore if we ſhoulde be ſacrileges by making a temple to any creature, how is he not true God to whome we doe not make a temple, but we our ſelues are a temple. If this be true, how be not the Papiſtes accurſed from the Trueth of Chriſt, and from the Church of God which builde and vpholde churches to Angells, as <hi>S. Michaels, S. Gabriels, &amp;c?</hi> So that to builde churches as Papiſtes doe, is church robbing or ſacrilege. Furthermore whereas you will vs to name one church whoſe chancell is not builded in all faſhions to ſerue poperie. Firſt it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:23111:35"/>that the firſt Churches which were builded for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians had not the ſame faſhion of chancels and other partes that moſt churches haue in Englande, for that purpoſe reade the Panegyricall oration made before <hi>Paulinus</hi> byſhop of Tyrus. <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. In which is deſcribed the faſhion of that church builded in that citie farre vnlike the moſte parte of churches at this day in all partes, and ſpecially in the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel which was in the middeſt of that church, a place com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed in with grates or wodden lateſſes called <hi>Cancelli,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this worde chancel is deriued, and the aultar ſtoode in the middeſt of it wherof ſome ſimilitude remaineth yet in olde Cathedrall churches. Contrariwiſe your chancells in moſt churches be at the Eaſtende and the aulter hard at the wall, there was alſo but one alter in that church, but you in euery church muſt haue many, it is certaine alſo in their church the Miniſters and Deacons ſtoode rounde about the table or aulter, but ſo they can not about your aultars except ſome of them ſtande on the toppe of the wall or in the windowe. Moreouer if you marke the moſt parte of olde churches in Englande you ſhall plainely ſee, that the chancells are but additions builded ſence the churches, of likelihoode by the parſons that diſdained to haue their place in the middeſt of the people as the olde manner was. Alſo you may ſee ſome churches builded rounde: as at London the Temple, and an other is at Cambridge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And ſome churches haue the ſteple at the Eſt ende, very vnhandſomely for pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the roode lofte. Againe many churches haue croſſe Iſles in which the people can not ſee the chancell, nor the high aultar, which argueth that there was no vſe of ſuch chancells when they were builded: For ſuch churches as are latelie erected haue the chancell and church all of one buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and are made of ſuch faſhion that men maye ſee the highe aultar in euery parte of them: Beſide this, in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientall church, as their ceremonies are diuers from yours, ſo no doubt the faſhion of their temples differeth from yours. As for chalices, the church in the beginning was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with wodden cuppes, and then came <hi>Zepherinus</hi> and brought in the vſe of glaſſes. <hi>Acacius Amidenus</hi> is commended for ſelling
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:23111:35"/>the golden and ſiluer veſſells of the church, to redeme cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues. <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> alſo <hi>Offic. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. ſayth the church hath golde, not to kepe it but to be beſtowed for neceſſarie vſes, for which it is lawfull to breake, melt, and ſel, euen the holyeſt veſſells of all. But of your church it is true that one ſaid of olde time: ye had wodden chalices, and gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den prieſtes but now you haue golden chalices, and wodden prieſtes: your veſtimentes are of as good ſtuffe as your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lices. The olde church knew none ſuch, but as your owne Authors write: when they wente to celebrate they changed the affection of their minde rather than the garmentes of their body: as <hi>Antoninus</hi> witneſſeth of <hi>Fulgentius.</hi> Howbeit we are content that your church by her gorgeous garments as well as by other thinges ſhoulde declare it ſelfe to be that woman which is deſcribed to be clothed in purple, golde, perles, and ſuch like ornamentes <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17. Finally wheras you will vs to name one church that for the ſpeciall intent of the builders, was not prepared in all ſortes for Popiſh practiſes: Although I could name many, yet for examples ſake, I name <hi>Pantheon,</hi> a church in Rome, prepared by the ſpeciall and onely intent of the builders for <hi>Cybelle,</hi> the great mother of the gods and for all falſe gods of the heathen, which now is called the church of Mary and Alhalowes. Then this church with many other in Rome, and other places, being monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the faith and religion of the Paganes and not of yours, except yours and theirs be all one, as they are very like, you are bounde by your promiſe to recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="article">
                  <head>The 15. article conteyneth in effect 3. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Againe name any one company of men in the Chriſten world that in all articles of Faith, be in one meaning and belefe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT is an eaſie matter to name diuers companies agreeing in one meaning &amp; beliefe: as the church of the Grecians, the church of the Aethiopians, the church of the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans, Moſcouites, &amp;c. But eſpecially the whole company
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:23111:36"/>of Proteſtantes in Europe doe agree in all neceſſary articles of true faith, by which we are iuſtified.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>Or in thinges where they doubt, be contented to ſubmit their ſeuerall meaninge to the iudgement of their Superiours.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe Greeke church in doubtes will be ruled by the Patriarch of Conſtantinople, and ſo will the reſt of the Orientall churches by their cheefe Patriarches and biſhops. And the Proteſtants in Europe will alſo be ruled by their Superiours, ſo farre as their ſuperiors are ruled by Gods his worde.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>And to that communion and companie wherof they be, name any companie of men agreeing and thus humbly affected in Chriſtes Religion, ſauing the bleſſed fellowſhip and members of the Catholike communion, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>TO the communion and company of the Grecians, I name the Moſcouites and Ruſſians agreeing in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and ſo humbly affected, and theſe are not of the fellowſhip, that you call the Catholike commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: Among the Proteſtants, to the church of Saxonie, I name the church of Dennemarcke, or to the church of Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetia, the church of France, or to the church of England the church of Scotlande, but ſo, that none of theſe allow any conſent or ſubmiſſion, but to the Truth, which muſt be tried onely by God his worde. And ſeeing none of theſe are of the Popiſh communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if your promiſe be any thing worth, you muſt recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="article">
                  <head>The 16. article conteyneth one demande, and one chalenge.</head>
                  <div type="demand">
                     <head>Furthermore name any one man that is confeſſed on both ſides by the iudgement of the world, to be holy and learned, &amp; a member of the true Church, in what age ſoeuer you liſt ſence Chriſtes time, and proue him to haue bene in all ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith of the Proteſtants meaninge.</head>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:23111:36"/>
                     <p> SEeing you geue ſo large ſcope, I will name <hi>S. Paule,</hi> who I thinke is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed on both ſides to be holy and learned, and a member of the true Church, whome I can proue by his writinges, that in all articles of faith, he taught the ſame, which we beleeue. And for triall of this, becauſe it woulde requier a whole volume, if I ſhoulde proue euery particular article, wherein we diſſent from you Papiſtes: If you will name an article, wherein we agree not with <hi>S. Paule,</hi> If I be not able to proue that we agree with him in the meaninge thereof, I will reuoke that article and agree with you therein.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="challenge">
                     <head>Yea if I bring not the aduerſaries them ſelues to acknowledge in the ende him to be wholy againſt their doctrine in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of articles of great importance, and therefore that he coulde not be of their church, I recant.</head>
                     <p>YOu ſhall neuer bring vs, neither in the beginning, nor in the end to acknowledged that <hi>S. Paule</hi> is againſt vs in any article of our Faith, but we agree wholy with him. Neuertheleſſe I know what you meane, &amp; will not be afraide to vtter. Foraſmuch as immediatly after the Apoſtles time, corruption entred into the Church, which was hardly kept out, while they liued: as we maye learne by the Epiſtle to the Corinthians, you thinke that we dare not depende vpon any one mans iudgement: and therein you are not deceiued: for we muſt depende onely vppon Gods worde. But where you ſaye there is none but he diſſenteth from vs in diuers articles of great importance, you ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truely: for you are not able to proue that <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> Martyr, or <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> two of the moſt ancient authenticall writers, that the Church next vnto the Apoſtles had, are againſt vs, in any point of doctrine wherein we differ from you? Yet are there certaine errors in them, which neither you, nor we allow, as is touched before in the anſwere to the 11. article 1. deman. But they are both wholly againſt you in diuers articles of your doctrine, and namely in tranſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is one of the greateſt articles of Poperie: as <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> in the 34. <hi>cap.</hi>
                        <pb n="60" facs="tcp:23111:37"/>of his 4. booke <hi>Contrahaereſes: Quemadmodum enim qui eſt a terra panis &amp;c.</hi> Euen as the breade which is of the earth after it hath receyued the inuocation of God, is not now common breade, but the Euchariſtie, or (breade of thankes geuing) conſiſting of two thinges earthly &amp; heauenly, ſo our bodies receyuing the Euchariſtie, are not now corruptible, hauing hope of reſurrection. Here you ſee plainely, that <hi>Irenaeus</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth the ſacrament, after conſecration to conſiſt of the earthly ſubſtance of breade: which maye better be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode, when we know that he reaſoneth againſt ſuch here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes as denied the world to be made by God, ſaying that he woulde neuer haue made ſo great a myſterie of bread, which is a creature of the world, if the worlde had not bene made by him. <hi>Iuſtinus,</hi> in his ſecond Apologie to the Emperour. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We doe not receiue theſe thinges as common breade and a common cuppe but euen as Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour was incarnate by the worde of God and tooke vpon him fleſh and bloude for our ſaluation: So we are taught that this meate for which thankes is geuen by the worde of prayer from him of which our fleſhe and bloude are nouriſhed by tranſmutation, is the fleſhe and bloude of Ieſus that was incarnate. Here, he plainely affirmeth that the ſubſtance of the Sacrament is turned into the nouriſhment of our bodies. Therfore it remaineth ſtill after the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The other writers of later yeares, as they haue ſome er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors which neither you nor we doe allow in them, ſo we are not afraid to confeſſe that they haue ſome corruption, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you may ſeeme to haue colour of defence for inuocation of Sainctes, prayer for the dead, and diuerſe ſuperſtitious and ſuperfluous ceremonies, yet not ſo addict to theſe, nor ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſuch abſurdities as yours are. But for the chiefe pointes of Chriſtian Religion, and the foundation of our faith, that is, for the honour of God, the offices of Chriſt, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, Iuſtification, Satisfaction, the fruites of Chriſt his paſſion, Grace, faith, workes, authoritie of God his word, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Pope, reall preſence, tranſubſtantiation, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in both kindes, Images, &amp;c. the moſt approued wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>Tertullian, Cyprian, Origen, Epiphanius, Hilarius, Chryſoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:23111:37"/>Ieronymus, Ambroſius, Auguſtinus, &amp;c.</hi> are vtterly againſt you, and therfore can not be of your church. But for as much as they hold the foundation, that is Chriſt, though they haue diuerſe errors &amp; ſuperſtitions, they were doubtles, the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the true Church of Chriſt, which becauſe you are not able to diſproue, reaſon would you ſhould recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="article">
                  <head>The 17. Article conteyneth 5. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>I aske of them whether the Lutherans, Zuinglians, Illirians, Calueniſtes, Confeſſioniſtes, Swenkefeldians, Anabaptiſtes and ſuch like, be all of one Church?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BEcauſe you would make ſimple men beleue, that there be ſo many diuerſe ſectes of Proteſtantes, as you haue giuen them names, I will firſt diſcuſſe theſe ſectes, and afterwarde aunſwere your queſtion. Lutherans, you meane them that follow <hi>Luthers</hi> opinion of the Sacrament. Zuinglians, follow <hi>Caluines</hi> iudgement of the ſame. Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oniſtes, them that exhibited their confeſſion at Auſpurge, which were both the Lutherans and Zuinglians, ſo theſe 3. names may be contracted into two: Lutherans and Zuingli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. As for Illyrians, if you call them of <hi>Flaccius Illyricus,</hi> they be Lutherans, in opinion of the Sacrament, and differ onely in ceremonies, which can not diuide them from the faith. <hi>Caluine,</hi> and they that be of his iudgement, agree plainly with <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> ſo that of fiue names, there remaine but two ſortes differing in opinion, whereunto you ioyne the Swenkefeldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Anabaptiſtes. Now to your queſtion, theſe be not all of one Church, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Swenkefeldians &amp; Anabaptiſts be dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable heretiks, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lutherans &amp; Zuinglia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (as it pleaſeth you to cal the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) are of one true church, although they differ in one opinion, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for although the one affirme a real preſence, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other deny it, yet they both co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent in this, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Chriſt, is receiued ſpiritually, not corporally, with the hart, and not with the mouth. Wherfore, this diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not ſo great (though there be error on the one ſide) but that they may be both of the Church of Chriſt, as well as <hi>S. Cyprian,</hi> the Martyr, and all the Biſhops of Africa, and a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:23111:38"/>great many of Aſia, differing with <hi>Stephanus,</hi> biſhop of Rome, and the reſt of his opinion in rebaptizing ſuch as were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by heretiks.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>And if either they can proue vnto me, that theſe, being of ſuch diuerſitie in faith and religion make one Church.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WE haue alwaies abhorred the hereſies of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſtes, Libertines, Swenkefeldians, Daui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, Seruitians, and all ſuch. But that <hi>Luther</hi> &amp; <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> may be both of one Church, differing onely in one opinion of the Sacrament, is declared before.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>Or that each of their ſects may giue ſaluation to their folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, being ſo diſagreable, one with an other in high points of our Religion.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>SAluation is the gift of God, and not in the power of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny company, or ſect of men: but this we affirme, that out of that Church, whereof we count <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius,</hi> notwithſtanding their diuerſe opinions (which is but in one matter of the Sacrament) to be members, there is no ſaluation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="demand">
                     <head>4 <hi>Or that I ſhould beleue all theſe rather then the Catholike Church, or one of theſe more then another, all making ſuch a bold chalenge of the truth and Goſpell.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>NO man requireth you to beleue all theſe, but the true Catholike Church onely. Neither doe we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you to beleue any one company of men, more then an other: but to beleue the trueth before fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood. Now, which of them hath the truth, that they all brag of, you muſt ſearch in the word of truth, deſiring the ſpirite of truth that you may vnderſtand and beleue the truth, and ſo without doubt, you ſhall come to the knowledge of the truth, and of the Church of God, which is the piller and ſtay of truth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="demand">
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:23111:38"/>
                     <head>5 <hi>Let the Proteſtants of all theſe kindes put their heades toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſhew me a reaſon of theſe thinges, and with all, let them among them ſelues agree, to what ſorte of theſe ſectes they woulde haue me, and I will recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>SVch is your impudencie in this matter, as in all other, that you woulde make men beleue that the Anaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſtes, Swenkefeldians, Libertins, and other abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable heretikes, be Proteſtantes: But it is well that you can make none but fooles thinke ſo: as for the Proteſtantes, they neede take no great deliberation to aunſwere your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandes but you had more neede to laye your heades toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to reconcile the Thomiſtes, Albertiſtes, Ockamiſtes, Scotiſtes, Reales, and Nominalls, which be all ſectes of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, and eſpecially your Canoniſtes, and diuines, about the articles of your religion, that is: whether the Pope be aboue the Councell, or the Councel aboue the Pope. Whether the Pope may erre and not the Councell, or whether the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell maye erre and not the Pope. Theſe two: the Popes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination and the Councells determination, being the rules of trueth in your religion and not agreed vpon: how can any trueth be certeine in your Church? At for <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> they agree vpon one rule of trueth, that is the worde of God, and differ onely for the applying or laying of this rule, &amp; yet but in one matter &amp; that not the greateſt. But you Papiſts, ſome holding of the Pope, and ſome of the Councell, as rules of truth, can haue no ground nor certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof. Therefore if you woulde haue me, or any man, to be of your belefe. Firſt determine how I ſhal know when I am in a right beleefe: one ſayeth, if the councell alloweth it, an other ſayeth if the Pope alloweth, what ſhall I doe, when one of theſe is againſt an other? yea when one Pope is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an other, and one councell againſt an other, ſhall I thinke that trueth changeth ſo often as they change. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer when one Pope graunteth, that the councell is aboue the Pope and that the Pope maye erre. Likewiſe one coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell graunteth, that the Pope is aboue the councell and that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:23111:39"/>the councell may erre, as it hath bene within the 200. yeares, the councells of Conſtance and Baſill, determined that the councell was aboue the Pope and that the Pope maye erre. Contrariwiſe, the councell of Ferraria, and Florence, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined that the Pope was aboue the councell and that the councell might erre. <hi>Martinus</hi> 5. the Pope choſen by the councell of Conſtance, was of the ſame iudgement that the councell: But <hi>Eugenius</hi> 4. that gathered the councell of Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raria, and Florence againſt the councell of Baſill, was of the contrarie iudgement. Nowe I woulde ſaye he were a wittie fellow, that coulde reconcile this geare together. For, if he be a Canoniſt that holdeth this opinion: that the Pope can not erre, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pope him ſelf graunteth that he may erre, which waye ſhall he turne him ſelfe? For, if this propoſition be true: the Pope can not erre, then this is true alſo, that the Pope may erre: for if he can not erre he can not erre in ſaying ſo: And if the Pope erred in ſaying, he coulde erre where he can not erre, then this propoſition is falſe, the Pope can not erre, ſo one propoſition ſhalbe both true and falſe, which is impoſſible. Likewiſe if he holde that hilde that the councell can not erre, and the councell it ſelfe confeſſeth it that it may erre. Gentle maiſter N. reconcile me theſe together, which concerne a caſe that hath bene in practiſe and ſtill is, in the Papiſtrie, and maye here trouble a mans conſcience that woulde beleue your church, and if he haue any wit, reſtraine him for euer comming into your church: If you can not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie this knot nor winde your ſelfe out of this maze, vnleſſe you will be ſtill obſtinate, it were wiſedome for you to recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="article">
                  <head>The 18. article hath but one demande.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>I demande whether they were euer of the true Catholike church, which either tooke to them ſelues newe names of religion according to the calling of any ſecte maiſter, or liked not ſo well the name of Catholike or Chriſtian as of their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall teachers, as to be called of <hi>Arius,</hi> Arians, or of <hi>Caluine,</hi> Caluiniſtes, or of <hi>Luther,</hi> Lutheranes, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants &amp;c. if any man therefore can proue vnto me that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:23111:39"/>men which haue choſen to themſelues to declare their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of faith, from the common knowen Catholike church ſuch newe names, ſhoulde be of the Catholike church, I recant.</head>
                     <p>I Aunſwere that they which can not be content with the name of Chriſtians, but choſe vnto them ſelues newe names after the calling of their ſecte maiſters: as Arrians, Pelagians; Franciſcanes, Dominicanes, Benedictines, Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines, Auguſtinians, Scotiſtes, Thomiſtes, Albertiſtes, &amp;c. are none of the Catholike church: But the true Chriſtians which deſier moſt of all to be ſo called, and compting it a moſt honorable name without choſing any other name, be of the Catholike church, although in reproch, they be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of you Caluiniſtes, and Lutherans. As for the name of Proteſtants, came firſt of them that made proteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the decree of Spires in Germanie, and from that time hath bene attributed to the profeſſors of the Goſpell: which name they doe not ſo much delight in, as you doe in the name of Papiſtes. Therefore, if nothing els do let you but the name, there is no cauſe why you ſhoulde not recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="article">
                  <head>The 19. article hath but one demande.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>Againe, if theſe, which by the common calling and iudgement of Chriſtian people, be named and commonly taken for heretikes, haue not in all ages proued them ſelues in the ende to be heretikes in deede, notwithſtanding their cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Gods worde, and therefore that the Proteſtants being ſo taken and called, proue not ſo in deede, I recant.</head>
                     <p>THoſe that by true Chriſtians, haue bene called and counted for heretikes, haue proued ſo in deede, and therefore the Papiſtes, being called and counted he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes of true Chriſtians, without doubt, are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes in deede. But it hath not bene alwayes true, that they, which of the people commonly called Chriſtians, were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and taken for heretikes, proued ſo in deede. For the true
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:23111:40"/>Chriſtians of the Arrian people, that were called Chriſtian people, were called and taken for heretikes, and in reproch, were called Homouſians, and Athanaſians, yet they proued and were in deede, true Chriſtians and no heretikes. So the true Chriſtians at this day, being of the Papiſtes, which after a ſorte, are named Chriſtians: called heretikes, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch Proteſtants, and Caluiniſtes, in that their faith agreeth with the worde of God, proue them ſelues in deede, to be true Chriſtians, &amp; no heretikes. Therefore you haue bound your ſelfe to recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="article">
                  <head>The 20. article hath 3. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Likewiſe, if any man can proue vnto me, that either thoſe be not true Chriſtians, which by the conſent of nations, and by olde preſcription of ſo manye yeares as be ſith their conuerſion, be and euer hath bene called Catholikes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>YOu your ſelues, will not accompt the Grecians for true Chriſtians, and yet by conſent of nations, and preſcription of as many yeares as you can preſcribe, they be, and euer haue bene called Catholikes, if you ſay: they are not called by you, I aunſwere: no more are you ſo called by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And ſence the time that you departed from them, as great a portion of the worlde, and as many nations, haue called them Catholikes, as you are able to ſhewe on your ſide. Therfore either you muſt compte them true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, or els you muſt graunt that they, which haue ben long called Catholikes, are not alwayes true Chriſtians.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>Or that thoſe can be any true members, or children of the Catholike church, which do miſlike and miſtruſt ſo farre-forth theſe holy names, as wel of Church, as Catholike that they haue turned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into Congregations, and Goſpellers, and Proteſtants, and ſuch like.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HE is a fooliſh ſophiſter, that reaſoneth from names to things, as you doe moſt vainely and childiſhly: we miſlike the names of Church, &amp; Catholike, becauſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:23111:40"/>we do ſometimes vſe theſe names: Congregation, and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers or Proteſtantes, and therefore be no true members of the Catholike church: we neither miſlike nor miſtruſt thoſe names as you ſclaunder vs, neither doe we boaſt and truſt onely in theſe names, without the thinges them ſelues, as you doe, and as your forefathers the wicked Iewes, crying: the Temple of the Lorde, the Temple of the Lorde, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lorde: when they had nothing leſſe than the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord, but rather a denne of theues: So, you crie, the Catholike church, the Catholike church, the Catholike church, when you haue nothing in deede but the ſynagoge of Sathan. But becauſe you make ſo much of theſe two names, Church, and Catholike, let vs ſee what great myſteries are conteined in them. This worde, Church, commeth of the Greeke worde <hi>Kyriaka,</hi> in Latine <hi>Dominica,</hi> in Engliſh, <hi>the Lorde his houſe:</hi> for ſo were they wonte, in olde time to call their temples, or oratories, ſo that this worde, church, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prely ſignifieth a materiall temple, and can not ſignifie the fellowſhip and communion of Chriſtian people, but by a figure. Therefore if we other whiles vſe this worde, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, which can not denie, but it is the Engliſh worde of this Greeke name <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> that the Scripture vſeth, and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifieth without figure y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thing that this word, Church, doth by a figure, you may be aſhamed, if you were not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, to finde any fault with vs for ſo doinge. Likewiſe this worde, Catholike, commeth of the Greeke worde, and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth Vniuerſall, or ouer all, which worde the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doth not vnderſtande. Therefore we expounde it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſaye: that the Catholike Church, is the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt, diſperſed ouer all the worlde. What reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man can reprehende this doinge, and not rather your folly, which thinke it inoughe, if the people can prate like parates: Catholike, Catholike, and vnderſtande not what Catholike meaneth. Thus, as we doe not refuſe theſe wordes: Catholike, and Church, becauſe they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly receiued, ſo doe we interprete them, by Vniuerſall, and Congregation, becauſe they are not elſe, commonly vnderſtanded.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:23111:41"/>
                     <head>3 <hi>If therefore any thing can proue our true Church better than the honorable name of Catholike, or more condemne them to be out of Chriſtes church tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that not only the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worlde geueth it not to them, but they in a name, do refuſe the ſame them ſelues, then do I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HEre you bewraye your ſelfe euidently, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that we doe not ſclaunder you, when we ſay: you boaſt onely of the Catholike church: For you declare plainely, that you haue no better argument then the very name of the Catholike Church, to proue, that you be the Catholike Church: if this be the beſt argument, all the reſt is litle worth. For if the onely name of an honeſt man, is enough to proue an honeſt man, many a knaue may proue him ſelfe an honeſt man, and if the very name of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, make a learned man, many an aſſe may proue him ſelfe to be a learned man, or if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of a good Chriſtian, proue a man to be a good Chriſtian, euery hypocrite may proue him ſelfe a good Chriſtian. Likewiſe if you haue no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter argument, that can more condemne vs, then that we are not called the Catholike Church, then can you no more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs, then Chriſt and his Apoſtles, that were not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not called the true Church, but alſo were called heretikes &amp; deceiuers by the people of the Iewes, which were as right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called God his people, as they that giue you the name of Catholike Church, are called the Chriſtian world. It is well you haue nothing better to proue your Church, then the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable name of Catholike, nor any thing more to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne our Church, then that we are not called Catholike, and yet we haue as many nations, and more then you haue, that by publike authoritie, call vs Catholikes, and you heretikes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though you moſt ſhamefully ſclaunder vs, that we doe refuſe the name being offered vnto vs. Seeing you boaſt ſo much of the name, Catholike; you ſhall heare what ſome of the old writers iudged thereof. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> in an homelie, that he writeth of <hi>Adam,</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> in the later ende hath theſe words, after he hath tolde them that he hath no neede to repeate
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:23111:41"/>ſuch depe queſtions, as thoſe men haue handled which haue fought againſt heretikes: <hi>Satis ſufficere credimus quicquid ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum praedictas regulas Apoſtolica ſcripta nos docuerunt, vt pror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus opinemur Catholicum, quod apparuerit praefixis ſententijs eſſe contrarium,</hi> that is, we beleue that what ſo euer the Apoſtles haue taught vs according to the foreſayd rules is ſufficient, in ſo much that in no wiſe, we thinke that to be Catholike which ſhall appeare to be contrary to the ſentences before determined. By this you may ſee that <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> thought it not ſufficient to haue the name of Catholike, for he iudged nothing to be Catholike in deede, that was contrary to the rule grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the writings of the Apoſtles. Wherfore how ſo euer you boaſt of the honorable name of Catholike, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you can proue that your opinions agree with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they are not Catholike in deede, by <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> alſo, in his booke <hi>de Geneſe ad literam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfecto cap.</hi> 1. ſpeaking of the Catholike faith, ſayth: This is an article thereof, that we ſhould beleue. <hi>Conſtitutam ab eo matrem Eccleſiam quae Catholica dicitur, ex eo quia vniuerſaliter perfecta eſt, &amp; in nullo claudicat &amp; per totum orbem diffuſa eſt.</hi> That he hath appoynted a mother Church, which is called Catholike, of this, becauſe it is vniuerſally perfect, &amp; halteth in nothing, and is diſperſed ouer all the worlde. <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> here, is not content that the Church be onely called Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, but ſheweth when it is that, which it is called, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the popiſh Church, not being vniuerſally perfect, as moſt Papiſts will confeſſe, that many thinges in their church haue neede of reformation, &amp; halting in many thinges from the truth of God his worde, neither yet being diſperſed ouer all the world but conteyned in a corner of Europa, is not by <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> rule the Catholike Church. Furthermore <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Epiſtolam Fundame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti cap.</hi> 4. againſt the Manichees plainely declareth, how farre forth, not onely the name of Catholike, but alſo how farre vniuerſally, conſent, ſucceſſion, antiquitie, are to be allowed: <hi>Vt ergo hanc omittam ſapientiam, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore to omitte this wiſedom which you do beleue to be in the Catholike Church, there be many other things which may hold me moſt righteouſly in her boſome. The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:23111:42"/>of people and nations holdeth me, the authoritie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun with miracles, nouriſhed with hope, encreaſed with cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, confirmed by antiquitie, doth hold me. The ſucceſſion of Prieſtes from the very ſeate of <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, vnto whom our Lord after his reſurrection, committed his ſheepe to be fedde euen vnto this preſent biſhopricke, doth hold me. Laſt of all that very name of Catholike doth hold me, which name, not without a cauſe, this Church alone hath ſo obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, among ſo many hereſies, that wheras all heretiks would be called Catholikes, yet when a ſtranger ſhall aske: where men meete at the Catholike Church, none of the heretikes dare ſhew him, either their principall temple or houſe. All this, you will ſay maketh exceeding much for vs: yea, but heare that which followeth: <hi>Apud vos autem, vbi nihil horum eſt quod me inuitet ac teneat, ſola perſonat veritatis pollicitatio: quae quidem ſi tam manifeſta monſtratur, vt in dubium venire non poſſit: proponenda eſt omnibus illis rebus, quibus in Catholica te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neor,</hi> that is: But among you where there is none of theſe thinges, that may prouoke or holde me, there ſoundeth the onely promiſe of truth, which if it be ſhewed ſo manifeſt that it can not come in doubt, is to be preferred before all thoſe thinges, by which I am holden in a Catholike Church. By this you may plainly ſee, that though conſent, antiquitie, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, and the name of Catholike, be good confirmation, when they are ioyned with the truth, yet when a truth is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from them, it is more to be regarded then they all: &amp; it is truth that maketh Catholike, to be eſtemed, and not Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, that giueth authoritie to truth: Wherefore, ſeeing it were better to proue your Church, to be Catholike, then to boaſt, that it is ſo called, &amp; to diſproue our Church ſo to be, then to ſay: it is not ſo called: The beſt way for you, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="article">
                  <head>The 21. article conteyneth but one demande.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Moreouer, I aſke of the Proteſtants: whether in that time, in which they holde the true church to haue bene hidden or loſt: the people that learned this article of their Creede
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:23111:42"/>(I beleue the Catholike church) was bounde to goe from that church which they ſawe, and taught them both the article, and all other thinges touching their faith and by which they were Chriſtened, and receyned all other ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and commodities of ſaluation, whether they were bounde, I ſay, to beleue this vnknowen and cloſe Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, which they coulde neuer come vnto, nor by which they euer receiued, or coulde receiue any benefit, and ſo forſake that church by whom and in whom, they receiued both their faith and ſacraments: Shew me therefore that the Chriſtian men of theſe dayes, were charged to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue any other church than that, which taught them the article of the church, and baptized them, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis demande, is like a drunken mans dreame, hauing neither heade nor foote: whether they ſhoulde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue the church was loſt: whether they ſhoulde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue the church that was vnknowen to them, &amp;c. But if your demande haue any ſenſe in it: This is my aunſwere. The church was neuer loſt, but hidden from the eyes of the worlde: Therefore, if the people that where taught that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle: To beleue the Catholike church, and were baptized to your church, vnderſtood that this church, was not the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike church, which was ſo commonly called, but that God had a ſecret Congregation, which was in deed, the true Catholike church, they were bound to forſake your church, and to beleue the ſecret Congregation: for if a man had ben baptized of the Arrians and being brought vp by them, had learned that article, to beleue the Catholike church, which the Arrians would expound to be them ſelues, if afterward, by God his helpe, this man vnderſtood, that the church of the Arrians, was not the catholike church, as he was taught it was, but that <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and a few other, that were bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and perſecuted, were the true Catholike church: he was bounde to leaue the Arrians, commonly called the church, and to ioyne him ſelfe with the ſecret, baniſhed, hidde, and perſecuted church of Chriſt. But as for your Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh church, in that time of blindeneſſe and error taught not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:23111:43"/>the people that article, nor any other but kept them backe from the knowledge, as well of that article, as of all other thinges that were neceſſary to their ſaluation: for you taught them nothing els, but to pronounce, and that full ilfauoredly, like popingeys, certeine latine wordes, which they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode no more than ſtockes or ſtones. So that the people had no inſtruction of you, no not of the name of God, in many places but that they receiued by vncertaine talke of their parentes, as it were from hande to hande: for how many thouſand pariſhes are there in Englande, that within theſe 60. yeares woulde declare, that they neuer hearde ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in their life. As for that they hearde of their ſeruice, they learned as much of it, as of the ringing of their belles, which was a ſounde without vnderſtanding. Therefore you may be aſhamed to ſpeake of teaching the people, their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe and all thinges neceſſary for ſaluation, when you haue counted it hereſie to learne their creede in Engliſh, or to reade the ſcripture in Engliſh, in which is conteined all thing neceſſary to be knowen for euerlaſting ſaluation. Finally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you requier me to ſhew you that the Chriſtian people of thoſe dayes, were bounde to beleue any other: church than that, which taught them the article of the church and baptiſed them, I trow I will ſo ſhew it you, that for both your eares, you dare not deny it: how ſaye you? The Chriſtian people of the Greeke church, which were taught by the Greeke church, that article of the church, and by the ſame Greeke church were baptiſed, whether ought they to beleue any other church but the Greeke church? If you ſay no: then you acknowledge the Greeke church to be the true church which denieth the Popes authoritie, if you ſaye yea: Then you are welcome home, you recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="article">
                  <head>The 22. article, although it be very confuſe, yet it conteyneth in effect 3. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>I aske alſo whether any man for the ſpace of that</hi> 1000. <hi>yeres of blindenes could be ſaued, out of that ſecrete and ſmall Church, which they ſay was the true Church, if they aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:23111:43"/>me, there might be ſome ſaued, with our Sacraments, and in the Communion or fellowſhip of the Papiſtes out of the Proteſtants Church, then there was a way to heauen, out of Gods Church: if they ſay that none could be ſaued by our Sacraments out of their cloſe Church, then all men yong and old periſhed for thoſe yeares without any hope of mercy, becauſe they could not vnite them ſelues, and be incorporate to that company and Congregation, whereof they neuer neither hearde, nor coulde by any meanes ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. Therefore let any man aliue proue vnto me that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any man could out of the true Church be ſaued.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>NO man aliue that knoweth what the true Church meaneth, will ſay, that any man can be ſaued out of the true Church, for he that is not a member of the body of Chriſt, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by no meanes receiue any benefit of Chriſt to his ſaluation. Therefore how long ſo euer the true Church were hidden, whether it were a thouſand yeres (as you beare men in hand that we ſhould ſay) or two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares it is not materiall, this is certeyne, that out of this Church, none could be ſaued, and though you count it ſmal, as in deede in reſpect of the world, it is but a ſmall flocke, and fewe are elected, and fewe finde the ſtreit gate of life. <hi>Luke</hi> 12. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. yet is the number of it greater, then mans eye commonly can diſcerne. As when <hi>Elias</hi> thought that he only had bene left alone of the true Church: God anſwered, that he had yet reſerued 7000. that neuer bowed their knee to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al.</hi> 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 19. And as <hi>Eſay</hi> declareth when the people ſhoulde be almoſt all deſtroyed, yet a remnant ſhould be ſaued, which though it ſeemed to be ſmall, yet it ſhould ouerflow and fill all the world with righteouſnes, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 10. and though it ſhal be like a gathering of grapes when vintage is ended, or the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of an oliue tree when men thinke they haue left nothing vppon it, yet there be two or three in the toppe amonge the boughes, &amp; foure or fiue vnder the leaues in the higheſt bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>Or that any other company could be knowne for the true and onely Church but our common Catholike ſocietie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:23111:44"/>
                     <p> THe true Catholike Church was neuer ſo ſecrete or hidden but it might be knowne of all thoſe that had eyes to ſee it, whoſe hartes were lightened with the ſpirite of God and were enſtructed by the worde of God, that they might vnderſtande the trueth, and knowe the ſpouſe of Chriſt from the common ſtrompet of Antichriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>Or that all men were damned for a thouſand yeares togither becauſe they coulde not finde, nor ſurmiſe of any other Church, then that which practiſeth all holy functions, which Chriſt left for our ſaluation in the world, and I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WE take not vpon vs to medle with God his iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whom he condemneth, &amp; for what cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, further then the word of God teacheth vs, namely that as many as haue not beleued in the onely ſonne of God, are condemned for their vnbeliefe, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecret cauſes we remit to his ſecrete counſell and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. And wheras you ſay that the popiſh church practiſeth all holy functions that Chriſt left for the ſaluation of his Church, it is moſt falſe: for firſt you doe not preach remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinnes in the bloode of Chriſt onely, for either you preach not all, or elſe you preach remiſſion of ſinnes in any thing, rather then the onely merites of Chriſt, as in mens owne merites, workes of ſupererogation, pardons, maſſes, beggarly ceremonies, as holy water, auriculer confeſſion &amp;c. Secondly, you miniſter not the Sacraments purely according to Chriſt his inſtitution, but either corrupt and defile them with mans traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as you do Baptiſme, or elſe cleane chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the vſe of them, as in the Lordes Supper, which you make a Sacrifice, an idoll, a Prieſtes breakfaſt, and defraude the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the one halfe of the ſacrament, as though you were wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer then he, that inſtituted it in both kindes. Thirdly, diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline you haue conuerted into tyranny and couetouſnes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning nothing but the name of it alone: Wherefore ſeeing you exerciſe no holy function after Chriſt his inſtitution, but cleane contrary to the ſame, and doe obſtinately defend the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:23111:44"/>filthy whore of babylon againſt the cleare light of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, &amp; the true ſpouſe of Chriſt, ye ſhall be damned except you recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="article">
                  <head>The 23. article conteyneth 2. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Againe ſhew me any Church, or imagin if you can by good reaſon, a church of Chriſt in which there is no gathering together for preaching, no ſpirite of propheſying, no rodde of correction, no order of miniſtring nor any ſpirituall functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that can be named, proue me that there ſhould be a true Church for a thouſand yeares together, and lacked all theſe thinges.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>YOu would faine haue a great nombre of Articles and therefore you bring in one matter often times in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers phraſe of words, that it might ſeeme a new mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter when it hath bene vttered twiſe or thriſe before: as this Article is conteined before in the 5.8. and 9. Articles, where you ſhall finde it more largely aunſwered. But let vs ſee, what this ſtrange demande requireth, we muſt ſhew him a church, or els imagine by good reaſon a church of Chriſt without preaching, miniſtring, and diſcipline for a thouſand yeares together. Although we will not graunt that it hath ſo longe continued without theſe exerciſes, yet becauſe you geue vs leaue to imagine, we can imagine that it may as well continue without publike preaching, miniſtring, and diſcipline for a thouſand yeares, as it did for three hundred yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Conſtantine.</hi> But you will ſay there was preaching mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring, and correcting, though it were not knowen to the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes and perſecutors, ſo ſay I vnto you, for that thouſand veres there was gathering together for preaching, miniſtring, and correcting, though the Pope and his perſecuting Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates coulde not alwayes ſee it, nor come to the knowledge of it: for if they had once intelligence of it they ſmarted for it, as is knowen by the ſtories of the Waldenſes, Bohemians, &amp;c. Furthermore continuall exerciſe of preaching, miniſtring of ſacramentes, and executing of diſcipline, are notes of a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:23111:45"/>quiet and peaceable Congregation, not of a diſperſed, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, and diſquieted Church. How often doth <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, that the brethren could not be gathered togither for executing of diſcipline, whereby it is certeyne, that likewiſe they coulde not be gathered togither for other exerciſes. Therefore the intermiſſion of theſe exerciſes in a perſecuted Church, doth not proue the ſame to be no true Church: But where ſo euer there be two or three gathered togither in the name of Chriſt, there is he in the middeſt of them. But whereas you require the ſpirite of propheſie (except you meane the gift of interpreting the Scriptures) the Church in the moſt quiet and flouriſhing ſtate, may want the ſpirite of ſhewing things to come, as well as the giftes of tongues, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>And withall, that there was an other vntrue Church which for thoſe many dayes onely practiſed to the ſaluation of many, all theſe offices: and geue me a good reaſon why this Church, that alwayes hath had theſe thinges ſhould be a falſe Church, and the other that wanted them, to be a true Church, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WE vtterly denye, that beſide the true Church, there was an vntrue church, that practiſed thoſe offices to the ſaluation of any man: for once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine I tell you, you haue neither the preaching of the word, nor miniſtring of Sacraments, nor execution of diſcipline, according to the truth of God his inſtitution, but either altogither changed, or elſe greatly corrupted. And whereas you ſay, that the popiſh church onely hath practiſed theſe offices: I aske you againe whether the Greeke Church be a parte of your Church, and whether the Papiſtes in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land be a part of your Church. The Grecians you will ſay, are not: but the Engliſh Papiſtes are. Then haue I founde out by your owne iudgement, the Church of the Grecians, practiſing theſe offices being an vntrue church, &amp; the church of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Engliſh Papiſtes not practiſing the ſame, yet graunted of you to be a true Church. Therfore you are bound to recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="article">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:23111:45"/>
                  <head>The 24. article conteyneth 10. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Moreouer let any man ſhew how that Church can be the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of truth, which durſt not for a thouſand yeares clayme either preaching of Gods word or miniſtring of Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts or ſhew her ſelfe againſt falſhood or ſuperſtition.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AS the number of your articles doth draw to an ende, ſo your matter is farre ſpent, and therefore to make vppe your number, you muſt repete one thing twiſe. This demaund is conteined before in the 11. and 12. articles, where alſo it is fully aunſwered. Notwithſtanding, ſeeing it commeth againe it ſhal be briefly aunſwered in this place. The Church is not called the piller of truth, becauſe it ſhould ſtand alwayes in the ſight of the world: for then the defection, which <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of, could not haue come, neither ſhould the Church flie into the wildernes, as was declared to <hi>S. Iohn:</hi> But it is called the piller of truth, becauſe that where ſo euer the Church is, either viſible or inuiſible, there is the truth. So though the Church were hidde a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne time in the wildernes, yet there was trueth with the Church. You ſeeme to be a good Arithmetrician: for no number ſoundeth in your mouth but a thouſand. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe how long ſo euer it was, the piller of truth decayed not, And as God gaue his ſpirite, diuers times was bold to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge preaching and miniſtring of the Sacraments, yea, and ſo boldly, that it coſt many of the chalengers their liues. As <hi>Berengarius, Bruno, Marſilus de Pandua, Ioannes de Gaudano, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annes VVickleffe, VValdo, Ioannes Hus, Ieronymus de Praga, &amp;c.</hi> Thus it is manifeſt that the Church hath diuers tymes chalenged her right, and withſtood falſhood.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>Let any man ſhew that all giftes of the ſpirite, and functions of the holy Ghoſt haue bene taken from her, a thouſand yeares togither, and onely practiſed to the peoples vſe by an aduouterous Church.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:23111:46"/>
                     <p> THere is no man can ſhew this: for it is a falſe lye, that all giftes of the ſpirite, &amp; function of the holy Ghoſt were either taken from the true Church, or giuen to the adulterous church. And this hath bene ſhewed more then once or twiſe before.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>Let it be declared, how the gates of hell haue not preuailed, or Chriſtes promiſe and warrant for her, not bene voyd &amp; fruſtrate, if a baſtard Church exerciſing idolatry, as they ſay, hath ſpoyled the true Church of all holy actions, and the whole gouernment, and the whole name of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, almoſt euer ſince Chriſtes tyme.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe Deuill hath bent all his force and ordinance, he hath armed all the power of darkeneſſe, he ſtirred vp ryrantes, heretikes, Popes, Saracenes, and Turkes to deſtroye the Church, the dragon, that olde ſerpent Satanas, the Deuill, ſtoode before the woman to deuoure her childe, he perſecuted her into the wilderneſſe, he caſt out of his mouthe, a great riuer to cary her awaie, he made warre with the reſt of her ſeede that keepe the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of God. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12. but yet in deſpight of the deuill, the Pope, and all her enemies, ſhe is to this day preſerued, and ſhalbe to the worldes end: Therefore the gates of Hell, haue not preuailed againſt her, nor the promiſe of Chriſt hath failed. And whereas you ſay, that your baſtard church hath ſpoiled her of all holy actions, gouernment, and Chriſtian name, it is a moſt impudent lye, as it is true, that you ſawe a baſtard church vſurped her holy name, counterfaicted her holy actions, and turned her gouernment into tyrannie.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="demand">
                     <head>4 <hi>Let me ſee therefore howe the onely dearling and ſpouſe of Chriſt ſhoulde be neglected of him ſo long.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>SHe hath not bene neglected of him, but felt his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall aide, he hath geuen her ſafe deliuerance of her childe, &amp; taken it vp from the crueltie of the Dragon, he hath prouided her a place in the wilderneſſe, he
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:23111:46"/>hath made warre with the Dragon for her ſake, and driuen him out of heauen, he hath geuen her Eagles wings to flie into the wilderneſſe, he hath cauſed the earth, to ſwallow vp the water that ſhoulde haue caried her awaie, he hath geuen the remnant of her ſeede, Victorie ouer the Dragon. Finally, his mercifull protection and louing care ouer her, hath neuer more notably appeared than that againſt ſo many daungers and enemies all this while he hath preſerued her, vntill ſuch time as he hath thought good, now to bring her out of her ſecret place in the wilderneſſe, into the open ſight of the worlde againe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="demand">
                     <head>5 <hi>Let the aduerſarie ſhew that the Church ſhoulde euer by ſuperſtition and falſhood commit adultery or be deuorced from him.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe true church, conſiſting of God his elect, and the liuely members of the bodie of Chriſt, ſhall neuer commit ſuch adultery that ſhe ſhalbe diuorced from him. But the viſible church, by Idolatrie and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition may ſeparate her ſelfe from Chriſt, and be refuſed of him, as God ſpeaketh by <hi>Eſay</hi> to the church of Ieruſalem <hi>cap.</hi> 1. How is the faithfull Citie become an harlot? It was full of iudgement, and iuſtice lodged therein, but now they are murtherers. Thy ſiluer is become droſſe, and thy wine is mixed with water. Thy Princes are rebellious and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of theeues &amp;c. euen ſo maye he ſay to the church of Rome: how is that faithfull church become an harlot, true Faith and Religion haue dwelled in her, but now Idolatrie and ſuperſtition: thy ſiluer is turned into droſſe, and thy wine is mixed with water, thou haſt nothing pure and vncorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, thy Princes be rebellious Antichriſtes &amp;c. Thus I haue ſhewed that the viſible church, may become an adultereſſe, and be deuorced from Chriſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="demand">
                     <head>6 <hi>Or that Chriſt ſhould euer want his ſpouſe in earth.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis hath bene often aunſwered before, Chriſt hath neuer wanted his ſpouſe in earth, though the blinde world can not alwayes ſee her, or when they ſee her,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:23111:47"/>will not acknowledge her to be his ſpouſe, but perſecute her, as if ſhe were an adultereſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="demand">
                     <head>7 <hi>Or that he ſhoulde be a heade either without a bodie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THeſe are but one thing in diuers phraſes, as he hath neuer wanted his ſpouſe in earth, ſo hath he neuer bene an heade without a bodie, and ſeeing theſe wordes in this ſence are relatiues (for Chriſt is called a heade in reſpect of the Church which is his body, and the Church is called a bodie, in reſpect of Chriſt that is her heade) I aunſwere you by a rule of the Logicians: No man knoweth a relatiue, except he know the correlatiue thereof, Therefore, though Chriſt had a bodie in earth, yet coulde it be knowen of none, but ſuch as knewe Chriſt the heade of that bodie. Of whome, when the Papiſtes were ignorant, ſpecially when they appointed an other heade in earth, it is no marueill, if they could not ſee the bodie of Chriſt, though he haue neuer bene without it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="demand">
                     <head>8 <hi>Or ſuch an vnknowne and ſmall bodie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis hath bene anſwered immediatly before, it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth that it be knowne to Chriſt the head. As he ſayeth: <hi>My ſheepe heare my voyce and I know them. Iohn</hi> 10. And to them that be of the members of the ſame body. As for the reſt, it is not neceſſary that they ſhould alwayes ſee it, which will neuer acknowledge it. Neither is it ſo ſmal, as it is thought of, it is diſperſed in many places ouer all the worlde, and yet fewe in compariſon of the malignant church, whoſe number is as the ſand of the ſea, &amp;c. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 20.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="demand">
                     <head>9 <hi>Or that Chriſtes only kingdom ſhould become ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temptible.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>NOthing elſe is to be looked for of the worlde, but hatred and contempt, as Chriſt him ſelfe ſayth: <hi>You ſhall be hated of all men for my names ſake. Matth.</hi> 10. &amp; <hi>S. Paule</hi> biddeth vs looke on our calling, not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:23111:47"/>wiſe men, according to the fleſh, not many mighty men, &amp; not many noble men: but God hath choſen the fooliſh thinges of this world to confound the wiſe, and the weake of this worlde to conſounde the ſtronge. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. And what hath the true church to boaſt in but in the Croſſe of Chriſt. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. than the which, nothing is more ſhamefull, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible or reprochefull to the wiſedome of this worlde: what knowledge or preaching hath the true church but Ieſus Chriſt crucified, which to the Iewes is an offence and to the Greckes fooliſhneſſe, but to them that be called, both Iewes and Greekes it is the power and wiſedome of God to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſaluation 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. So that as the church in the ſight of God and his Sainctes is moſt glorious and honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo in the ſight of the worlde it hath alwayes bene moſt baſe and contemptible.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="demand">
                     <head>10 <hi>Or that his ſpouſe in earth ſhoulde euer lacke the ſingular prerogatines of Gods ſpirite, ſhewe me theſe thinges, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis alſo hath ben declared before in the ſecond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande of this Article. There be certeine ſingular prerogatiues, which are not continually with God his Church: as the gift of tongues, the gift of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, the gift of healinges &amp;c. but there be other preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues of God his ſpirit, that are neceſſary for the ſaluation of God his elect, as the gift of vnderſtanding, the gift of Faith, the ſpirit of adoption, &amp;c. and theſe the ſpouſe of Chriſt hath neuer wanted. Wherefore if you wilbe partaker of thoſe benefits which are receiued in the church of Chriſt, you muſt forſake your Romiſh religion, and recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="article">
                  <head>The 25. article hath 2. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Shew me that the Church, which ought to be a Chriſtian mans ſtaye, in all troubles and tempeſtes of doctrine might become ſo hidde or ſo cloſe that no man coulde finde her.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:23111:48"/>
                     <p> THe reader muſt not be offended with me for any te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious repetition of mine aunſweres, ſeeing you geue the occaſion, by propounding your demandes ſo often. This demande hath a falſe principle: that the church ought to be a Chriſtian mans onely ſtaie in all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and tempeſtes of doctrine: for when ſoeuer any ſuch tempeſtes doe ariſe, there is as great queſtion and doubt of the Church, as there is controuerſie of the doctrine: for as euery heretike chalengeth vnto him ſelfe the trueth of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, ſo alſo doth he chalenge the poſſeſſion of the church, ſo that the church is alwayes in as great queſtion as the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. And then is it to be ſought out and tried onely by the ſcriptures, as we haue declared at large in the aunſwere to the 4. Article, 2. demande. Secondly whereas you demande: whether ſhe coulde be ſo hidde or cloſe that no man coulde finde her, becauſe I haue aunſwered to this demande ſower or fiue times already, I will now aunſwere in one worde: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhe was hidden and cloſe from the worlde, yet was ſhe knowen to them that were her children.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>Or ſo harteles that ſhe coulde ſuccour no man nor inſtruct any man in his doubt of conſcience or diſtreſſe of Faith, proue me that there maye be ſuch a decay of Gods ſpirite, trueth, and Church, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe Church hath neuer bene afraide to do her office towardes her children and true members, in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, exhorting, comforting, confirming, &amp;c. nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath the ſpirite of God failed to leade her into all trueth, and Chriſt hath bene with her euer more, and ſhalbe to the worldes end. But that the ſpirite of God, truth, and the Church of Chriſt, ſhoulde departe from the greateſt numbre of the worlde, is proued by <hi>S. Paule,</hi> 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. and by the Reuelation of <hi>S. Iohn. Apoc.</hi> 12. Therfore if the ſpirite of trueth did leade you, you ſhoulde recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="article">
                  <head>The 26. article conteyneth in effect but 3. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:23111:48"/>
                     <head>1 <hi>Shew me againe whether any man of yeares may be ſaued, except he beleue the Catholike Church?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THere is no man of what age or yeares ſoeuer he be that can be ſaued, except he be a member of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike church. But how neceſſary it is to beleue the Catholike church, it is very doubtfull, as you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande, and as the concluſion of this article ſeemeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. If you meane that it is neceſſary to beleue the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like church, that is to ſay, that God hath an holy vniuerſall Congregation, I graunt it is neceſſary to beleue. But I vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romiſh church is that holy Catholike church. But if you meane (as it ſeemeth) and as the reſt of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes doe interprete that article, I beleue the Catholike church, that is: I beleue, what ſoeuer the church doth allow, to be true: I deny that it is neceſſary to ſaluation, that a Chriſtian man ſhould ſo beleue the Catholike church, both becauſe the church may erre, &amp; alſo becauſe ſomething may be commonly receiued of the church, which is not materiall to ſaluation. And that this is a falſe interpretation of this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of our Creede, I beleue the Catholike church, that is: I beleue what ſo euer ſhe doth ſet forth or maintaine, to be true, appeareth manifeſtly by the wordes them ſelues: For who euer was ſo ignorant in the Latine tongue, to thinke that <hi>Credere Eccleſiam,</hi> and <hi>Credere Eccleſiae,</hi> were all one in ſignification. In deede if the wordes were: <hi>Credo Eccleſiae Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicae,</hi> in the datiue caſe, this interpretation might take place, but when it is in the accuſatiue caſe, <hi>Credo Eccleſiam Catholicam,</hi> A boy that woulde conſter it otherwiſe than thus: I beleue that there is a Catholike church, were worthy to haue a dooſen ſtripes for his labour. Moreouer this common diſtinction of <hi>Credere in Deum,</hi> that is: to put our truſt in God. <hi>Credere Deum,</hi> that is: to beleue that there is a God, and <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere Deo,</hi> that is: to geue credit to God, that he ſpeaketh the trueth, plainely ouerthroweth this fooliſh and falſe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation: For we ſay not: <hi>Credo in Eccleſiam,</hi> that is: I put my whole truſt in the Church, for that were blaſphemie,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:23111:49"/>againſt God, in whome only we muſt beleue, neither do we ſay: <hi>Credo Eccleſiae,</hi> that is: I geue credit to the Church, as though ſhe ſhoulde alwaies ſpeake the trueth: But we ſaye and confeſſe againſt all heretikes and ſciſmatikes: <hi>Credo Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam &amp;c.</hi> that is: I beleue, that there is one Holy, Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and Apoſtolike church, whereof I am a member &amp;c. Finally, when the articles following, are ſpoken in one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text and phraſe, it can not be choſen, but that they muſt haue one kinde of interpretation <hi>Communionem Sanctorum, Remiſſionem peccatorum, Carnis reſurrectionem,</hi> that is: I beleue the Communion of Sainctes, the forgeueneſſe of ſinnes, the Reſurrection of the body, &amp;c. whereof the interpretation muſt needes be this: I beleue that there is a Communion of Sainctes, that there is forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, &amp;c. Euen ſo I beleue, that there is a Catholike Church, which is an article of our crede, neceſſary to be beleued of euery Chriſtian man, but to beleue all and euery thing that the Catholike church, by commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſent doth maintaine, is no article of our Faith, and therefore not neceſſary to ſaluation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>And that is it which hath in the face of all the worlde pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed preaching: the conuerſion of nations to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Goſpell: that hath alwaies had the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of ſacraments, the hearing of matters in controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, power Iudiciarie in Eccleſiaſticall cauſes, the orderly ſucceſſion of Byſhops, vniformitie in ſolemne ceremonies, vnity in faith, that hath in her ſelfe all holy functions of the ſpirite, as working of miracles, remiſſion of ſinnes, the true ſence and interpretation of Gods word that is bewti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the diuerſitie of ſtates, commended by Chriſt in the Goſpell, as with Virgines, with Martyrs, with Confeſſors, and the reſt.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BEcauſe theſe colewortes haue bene ſodden twiſe or thryſe already, they are not worthy to be ſhewed in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall diſher, but euen as they are here mingled all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither in an hochpotte. Of theſe notes that you make proper to the Catholike Church (as it hath bene declared before) ſome are not alwaies neceſſary in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholike church:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:23111:49"/>As open preaching in the face of the world, open miniſtring of Sacraments and execution of diſcipline, theſe are not to be required in a perſecuted Church. Some were proper for a time, and then ceaſed, as working of miracles, and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther functions of the ſpirite. Some are neuer neceſſary in the Church, as ſucceſſion of Biſhops, vniformitie in ceremonies, &amp;c. But of all theſe notes, there is not one that is proper to the Church of Rome: for ſhe hath not alwaies practiſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen preaching, and neuer preached the worde of truth, ſhe hath conuerted but few nations to her Religion, from Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and them rather by warre, than by preaching: ſhe neuer had ſence ſhe firſt aroſe, the miniſtring of ſacraments accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſt his inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhe hath hard matters in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, not for furtherance of Iuſtice, but for loue of money. Her iudiciarie power, may be diſpenſed withall for money. She hath had no orderly ſucceſſion of Biſhops, except an hore be an orderly Biſhop of the Church of Rome: And except ſo many ſchiſmes as they write of, be orderly ſucceſſions: ſhe hath not vniformitie in all ceremonies, for diuerſe nations, and diuerſe Churches in theſe nations haue diuers ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, as Sarum, Yorke, Bangor, &amp;c. in England: ſhe hath not v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in faith: for it is not yet determined, of one of the greateſt articles of Popiſh faith, whether the Pope be aboue the church: ſhe hath no holy functions of God his ſpirite, but prophane vſages of mens inuentions: ſhe hath no true miracles, but the power of Antichriſt in lying ſignes and wonders. She hath nothing leſſe then the true ſenſe of God his worde, which ſubmitteth the ſame to her owne corrupt and changeable iudgement. She is not bewtified with eſtates commended in Scripture, as Apoſtles, Euangeliſts, Prophets, Paſtors and Teachers, but with Popes, Cardinalls, Monkes, Chanons, Fryers, &amp;c. In ſteede of virgines, ſhe hath filthy ſtrumpets, her Nunnes, or elſe ſuch fooliſh virgines as bring no oyle in their lampes: ſhe hath no Martyrs, but obſtinate traytors, as <hi>Becket, Fiſher, More, &amp;c.</hi> ſhe hath no confeſſors of trueth, though ſhe haue ten thouſand mainteyners of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood and lyes: Wherfore if theſe be the notes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of Rome can in no wiſe be that ſame.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:23111:50"/>
                     <head>3 <hi>Proue vnto me that this is not the true Church, or that we be not bound to obey this Church and no other in all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies, and doubtes rayſed either by the difficultie of the Scripture, or by the vayne contention &amp; pride of hereſie, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>I Haue proued, euen immediatly before that not one of thoſe notes, which you count to be markes of the true Church, is proper to your Church. And therefore it is not the truth, neither ought it to be obeyed in any thing. And as for doubtes that ariſe by difficultie of Scripture, or conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hereſie, muſt be reſolued and determined, as it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly declared before, onely by the Scriptures: for the hard places of the Scripture muſt be opened by eaſie places, and heretikes muſt be confuted, by the Scriptures: for there is neuer hereſie, but there is as great doubt of the Church, as of the matter in queſtion, onely the Scripture is the ſtay of a Chriſtian mans conſcience, which I woulde wiſh that you would truely embrace and recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="article">
                  <head>The 27. article conteyneth 5. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Moreouer let any man proue vnto me, that the true &amp; onely Church of God, may at any time be voyd of God his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe true and onely Church of Chriſt, can neuer be voyd of God his ſpirite, and yet ſhe may erre from the truth, and be deceiued, in ſome thinges, euen as there is no true Chriſtian man that is voyd of God his ſpirite, for he that hath not the ſpirite of Chriſt, is none of his. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. yet may euery true Chriſtian erre, and be decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in ſome things, according to the ſaying of the Scripture, euery man is a lyar. Wherefore the whole Church militant conſiſting of men, which are all lyars, may erre all togither, as euery part thereof, although neither the whole Church nor any true member thereof be voyd of God his ſpirite.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:23111:50"/>
                     <head>2 <hi>Or falſely interprete any ſentence of holy Scripture.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis gentle offer muſt needes be taken, I will proue vnto you, that the church of Rome, hath falſely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted diuers ſentences of ſcripture, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by that which ſhe hath done, it cannot be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but that ſhe may do it. <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> was in this error, that he thought Infantes muſt receiue the ſacrament of the body and bloude of Chriſt, vnder paine of damnation, and was deceiued by falſe interpretation of this ſcripture: <hi>Except ye eate the fleſhe of the Sonne of man and drinke his bloude &amp;c. Ioan.</hi> 6. This error and falſe interpretation, he affirmeth to be common to all the Weſterne church, &amp; to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> him ſelfe. <hi>Contra duas epiſt. Pelag. ad Bonifacium lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Iulianum lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. Furthermore the ſecond Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Nice, how many textes of ſcripture doth it falſely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete, which it were to tedious to repete, yet for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſake I will reherſe ſome of them. God made man to his owne image <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. therefore we muſt haue images in the church. No man lighteth a candle and ſetteth it vnder a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell <hi>Math.</hi> 5. therefore images muſt be ſet vpon the altars. As we haue heard, ſo we haue ſeene in the City of our God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48. that is: God muſt not be knowen by onely hearing of his worde, but alſo by ſight of images. If theſe be not true interpretations I reporte me to you. Beſide theſe, I will bring you a ſentence of holy Scripture, not onely falſely interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſence, but alſo falſified in wordes, and concerning not a ſmall matter, but euen one of the cheefe articles of our Faith. It is written in the 10. chapter of the Goſpell after <hi>S. Iohn</hi> the 29. verſe <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. My Father which gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me (ſpeaking of his ſheep) is greater than all. This ſentence, hath the Councell of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane, holden vnder Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3. where were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent 70. Metropolitanes, 400. Biſhops, 12. Abbates, and 800. Priors commentualles in all 1300. Prelats, falſified in wordes, after this maner, <hi>Pater quod dedit mihi, maius eſt omnibus,</hi> that is: That which the Father hath geuen me, is greater than all.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:23111:51"/>This ſentence they alleage, to proue that God the Father begetting his Sonne from euerlaſting, gaue his owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance vnto him, the wordes be in the 2. Canon. <hi>Pater enim ab aeterno filium generando, ſuam ſubſtantiam ei dedit, iuxta quod ipſe teſtatur: Pater quod dedit mihi, maius eſt omnibus. At dici non poteſt, quod partem ſuae ſubſtantiae illi dederit, &amp; partem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuerit ipſe ſibi, cum ſubſtantia Patris indiuiſibilis ſit &amp;c.</hi> that is to ſay: For the Father, begetting his ſonne, from euerlaſting, gaue him his owne ſubſtance, according as he himſelfe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth: that which the Father gaue me, is greater than all. But it can not be ſaid, that he gaue him part of his ſubſtance, and kept parte vnto him ſelfe, when as the ſubſtance of the Father is indiuiſible &amp;c. Goe your wayes now and perſwade vs, that your church can not interprete any ſentence of the ſcripture, falſely, when the Laterane Councell, which is your repreſented church hath thus both falſefied, and falſely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted, this ſcripture. Perſwade men, that they may ſafely leane to the interpretation of your church, when among a thouſand and three hundred Prelates, gathered canonically in a Councell, not one was founde that coulde eſpie ſuch groſſe abuſing of the worde of God, but let it paſſe in a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, vnder the name of the whole Councell. Perſwade men, that in all controuerſies, &amp; condemning of errors, they muſt be ruled by the determination of your Church, When the Fathers of the Laterane Councell, can not confute the error of <hi>Ioachim</hi> Abbot, concerning the Diuinitie of Chriſt, but by falſefying and falſe interpreting of ſcripture. Theſe few ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of an infinite numbre, I haue ſet forth, becauſe they are ſufficient, both to ſatisfie your chalenge, and to perſwade the ſimple, that the church of Rome may falſely interprete the ſcripture, which you woulde beare them in hande were impoſſible.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>Or induce any error among the people.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe true and onely church of God, is ſo guided by God his ſpirite and directed by his worde that ſhe can not induce any damnable error to continue. Yet,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:23111:51"/>as it is declared before, ſhe hath no ſuch priuilege graunted, but that ſhe may be deceiued, in ſome thinges: for her know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is vnperfect, and her prophecying is vnperfect. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. And it is true that <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſayeth: euen the whole church is taught to ſaye: <hi>Forgeue vs our treſpaſſes.</hi> And if generall Councells be the church repreſented (as you Papiſtes doe teache) <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> plainely affirmeth that they may erre: <hi>De Baptiſmo contra Donatiſtas, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Quis autem neſciat ſanctam ſcripturam Canonicam tam veteris quam noui Teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti &amp;c.</hi> And who knoweth not, that the holy Canonicall ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, as well of the olde, as of the newe Teſtament, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined within her certeine boundes: and that it is ſo prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, before all later writinges of byſhops, that of it, no man may in any wiſe doubt, or diſpute, whether it be true, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be right, what ſo euer is knowen to be written therin: and that the writings of biſhops, which haue bene written, or are now in writinge, maye be reprehended, if they haue gonne aſtraie, any thing from the trueth, both by the ſaying that is perhaps more wiſe, of any man, that is more ſkilfull in that matter, and by the more graue authoritie and wiſedom of other better learned biſhops, and alſo by Councells: and that euen thoſe Councells which are gathered in euery re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or prouince, ought to geue: place without all doubt, to the authoritie of the generall Councells, which are gathered out of all the Chriſtian worlde: and that euen the very ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councells, may often be amended, the former by the later, when as by any triall of thinges, that is opened, which before was ſhut, and that is knowen which before was hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, without any ſwelling of wicked pride, without any ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berneſſe of arrogance, without any contention of peuiſhe enuie: with holy Humility, with Catholike peace, with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charity. Thus farre, <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> which cleerely affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that generall Councells may often erre, which maye often be amended, but that the authority of God his worde, is to be preferred before the writings of all Doctors, and Decrees of all Councells, and that it onely can not erre. The Councell of Carthage the 3. ca. 23. determined, that all pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers at the altar, ſhoulde be directed onely to the Father, and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:23111:52"/>not to the Sonne, or the holy Ghoſt, whether this be an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to define that it is vnlawfull to pray to God the Sonne, and God the holy Ghoſt, let euery man iudge. But you will except, that this was a prouinciall Synode, and not a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell. But I aunſwere you, it hath the authoritie of a generall Councell, becauſe it was confirmed in the ſixt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell holden at Conſtantinople in Trullo. And as for the Popiſh church, that it maye erre, what neede we better proofe than the prayer, which it maketh, after the ending of euery generall Councell, <hi>Precamur ſcilicet vt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiae parcas &amp; errori indulgeas,</hi> that is we praye truely that thou wouldeſt ſpare our ignorance &amp; pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our error. And againe, <hi>Et quia conſcientia remordente tabeſcimus, ne aut igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia nos traxerit in errorem, aut praeceps forſitan voluntas im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulerit a Iuſtitia declinare, ob hoc te poſcimus, te rogamus, vt ſi quid offenſionis in hac Concilij celebritate attraximus, condonare, &amp; remiſſibile facere digneris.</hi> that is: And becauſe we are gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with remorce of conſcience, leſt either ignorance haue drawen vs into error, or perhaps raſh will hath driuen vs to decline from Iuſtice, therefore we praye thee, we beſeech thee, that if we haue drawen vnto vs any offence in the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of this Councell, thou wouldeſt vouche ſafe to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and to make it remiſſible &amp;c. If it be impoſſible for the generall Councell to erre, what neede they pray to God to pardon their error, and when their owne conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth them and compelleth them to confeſſe, and that before God, that they may erre, what impudence is it in any man, to contend that they can not erre? Furthermore the ſecond Councell of Nice, determined that Angels, and ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of men had bodies, were viſible, and circumſcriptible, and therefore might be painted, and this it affirmeth to be the iudgement of the Catholike church, <hi>Con. Nice.</hi> 2. <hi>Actione</hi> 5. If this be not to induce an error, to make men beleue that Angells and ſpirites haue bodies viſible and circumſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, there was neuer anye error ſence the worlde beganne. Finally, when they ſay the Pope can not erre, they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that ſuch generall Councells as condemned Popes, for heretikes, did erre, as the ſixt generall Councell of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:23111:52"/>in Trullo, which condemned and accurſed Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> for an heretike, <hi>Actione</hi> 13. Euen as Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> the 2. did alſo, as appeareth in his epiſtle, to the Emperour <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine.</hi> Alſo the Councell of Conſtance did erre, which condemned Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the 23. for denying the immortality of the ſoule, and the reſurrection of the body. <hi>Seſſion.</hi> 11. which Councell, Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> him ſelfe affirmed to be moſt holy, and that it coulde not erre. <hi>Seſſion.</hi> 12. And the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Baſile did erre, which depoſed Pope <hi>Eugenius,</hi> the 4. <hi>Seſſion.</hi> 34. the ſame Councell being confirmed by Pope <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colas</hi> the 5. <hi>Seſſion.</hi> 43. If you ſay: theſe two laſt Councells did not erre, in condemning and depoſing theſe Popes: Then the great generall, and OEcumenicall Councell of Ferra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, and Florence, did erre, in diſallowing the determination of theſe Councells. Thus it is manifeſt that the Romiſh church, which they them ſelues confeſſe, to be repreſented in a generall Councell, may erre, which hath ſo often erred. And if it may erre, and be deceiued it ſelfe, what man is he, that neede to doubt: Whether it maye iuduce any error a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="demand">
                     <head>4 <hi>Or approue any vnprofitable or hurtefull vſage among Chriſtians.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IF the church had not approued many vnprofitable and hurtefull vſages, among the people in <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> time, what neede had he to complaine, that many of God his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, were litle regarded, &amp; mans preſumptions ſo highely eſteemed, <hi>Sed hoc nimis doleo &amp;c.</hi> But herewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all I am to much greued, that many thinges which in God his booke are moſt holſomly commanded are leſſe regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and all thinges are ſo full of ſo many preſumptions, that he is more greuouſely reproued, which in his vtas hath tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the earth, with his bare foote, that he that hath buried his minde in dronkenneſſe. Therefore if it be an vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and hurtefull vſage, to preferre mans traditions before God his commaundementes, the Church in <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> time approued an vnprofitable and hurtefull vſage. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:23111:53"/>if the Church can not approue an vnprofitable or hurtefall vſage, wherefore are ſo many ceremonies, as were approved in <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> and <hi>S. Ambroſes</hi> times, abrogated and diſanulled, either becauſe they were vnprofitable, or elſe hurtful. Laſt of all, what ſuperſtitious vſages, doth the church of Rome ſtill approue? euen ſuch as the wiſer ſort of Papiſtes are aſhamed of.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="demand">
                     <head>5 <hi>Or that ſhe ſuffereth any man, damnably abuſing her religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without open reprehenſion thereof, proue any of theſe thinges, and I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe true Church of Chriſt, in ſuch places as ſhe is, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth no man damnably abuſing her Religion, with out open reprehenſion, as in the dayes of <hi>VValdo, VVickleffe, Huſſe, &amp;c.</hi> whereof ſufficient mention is made before, but becauſe ſhe is not in all places at all times, many men, yea whole nations, may damnably erre, and not be reprehended of her, As all the Mahometiſtes, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie the greateſt part of the world, who doth, or hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies openly reprehended them. And the Romiſh Church, can well enough abide, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true Religion of Chriſt, to be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably abuſed, not onely without reprehenſion, but alſo with allowing: For when the Friars, Dominicanes, &amp; Franciſcans, had forged a newe Goſpell, out of the doctrine of <hi>Ioa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>himus,</hi> and the viſions of <hi>Cyril,</hi> which they called the Goſpell of the holy Ghoſt, the Goſpell that ſhould endure hereafter, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting Goſpell: which diuiliſh goſpell they affirmed to be ſo much more perfect, then the Goſpell of Chriſt: as the Sunne is more perfect then the Moone, &amp; a kernell of a nut, before the ſhell: yet did not the Church of Rome, once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it. So that it was cultiued 55, yeares, and at length ſet forth to be openly expounded in the Vniuerſitie of Paris, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1255. without open reprehenſion of any, but ſuch as were counted heretikes for their labour, As <hi>Gulielmus de S. Amore, Gerardus Sagurellus, &amp;c.</hi> And finally, when the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was brought before the Pope, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1256. by <hi>Guliel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus de S. Amore,</hi> and other ſent from the Vniuerſitie of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:23111:53"/>the Pope and the Cardinalls, tooke order that it ſhoulde be priuily burned, and not openly reprehended, for ſhaming their orders. <hi>Mathaeus Pariſ.</hi> Whereby it is clearely proued, that the Romiſh Church hath ſuffered wicked men, damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to abuſe Religion, without open or priuie reprehenſion for the ſpace of 55. yeares, and at length without open repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, when there was no remedie but it muſt needes be reprehended, wherefore if there be any grace in you, you will recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="article">
                  <head>The 28. article conteyneth 3. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>If vnitie in Faith, auſteritie of life, ſharpe diſcipline, great penance, much faſting, large almes, godly deuotion, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to higher powers, grauitie and conſtancie in all caſes, be not the ſignes of the true Church.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IF you aſke of true Faith, repentance, diſcipline, &amp;c. theſe might be ſignes of the true Church, but if you meane v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie in any faith, &amp;c, as it ſeemeth by your wordes, the Mahometiſtes and Turkes, are the true Church, for they haue vnitie in their faith, auſteritie of life, ſharpe diſcipline, faſting, almes, deuotion, obedience, grauitie, Conſtance, &amp;c. as much, or rather more then the popiſh church.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>Or be not more in our Church then in their Congregation, I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>YOu haue not vnitie in true faith: for you knowe not what it meaneth, but are vtter enemies vnto it, and in your owne principles, there is no vnitie, whether the Pope or the Councell be ſuperior, &amp;c. you may, as all hypocrites, pretende auſteritie of life, when you are moſt lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urious riotors, as the world knoweth: your diſcipline is not ſo ſharpe, but money wil make it blunt: you haue great penance but no true repentance, you haue much abſtinence from meates, which is the doctrine of diuills, but you faſt as litle as other men: your almes are large but without faith, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:23111:54"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="93" facs="tcp:23111:54"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="94" facs="tcp:23111:55"/>ſinne: your deuotion is blinde, and not godly, but like her mother Ignorance: you are diſobedient to Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, ſubmitting your ſelues to Antichriſt: your grauitie and conſtancie in all caſes, is better commended of yourſelf, then knowne of other men: Wherefore being voyde euen of theſe, which you make the ſignes of the true Church, you are none of the true Church, except you recant.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>But if diſcorde in religion, licentiouſnes in lyuing, contempt of Diſcipline, reiecting of penance, lotheſomneſſe of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, lacke of zeale and deuotion, diſobedience to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, ſacriledge, apoſtacie, breach of vowes, vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full luſtes, wantonneſſe in all life and maners, if theſe thinges, I ſay, agree not better to the Proteſtants, than the Catholikes, or if theſe be not the plaine ſignes and fructes of a falſe church, and doctrine, I recant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WE acknowledge that in the outward face of our church, be many hypocrites, chargeable with theſe crimes that you ſpeake of, and we yelde our ſelues guiltie before God of greuous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, that our life is not aunſwerable vnto our doctrine: Neuertheleſſe we doubt not, but God for Chriſt his ſake, will haue mercy vpon vs. But if in life and conuerſation we be compared with you Papiſtes, euen the cheefeſt of your church, as Popes, Cardinalls, Byſhoppes, Monkes, &amp;c. We dare approue our life to be honeſter both before God and men. You ſhall neuer be able to charge vs with ſuch ryot, whoredome, adulterie, inceſt, ſodomitry, beſtiality, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, poyſoning, necromancie, apoſtaſie, blaſphemie, &amp;c. as both the worlde ſeeth to ouerflowe in your Prelates at this daye, and we are able to bring forth of your owne Cronicles and Hyſtories, to haue ben committed in times paſt: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for very ſhame, leaue of this compariſon. We meinteine no ſtewes, neither of males nor females, we ſet forth no bookes in commendation of Sodomitry, we exact no tribute of Courtiſans, to kepe open bawdrie, we priuiledge no writinges that teache men to committe vylanie, worthy of a
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:23111:55"/>thouſand deathes. Therefore be not ſo impudent, to charge vs with theſe crimes aboue the Papiſtes, but rather forſake that filthie whore, the mother of all fornication, and recant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="article">
                  <head>The 29. article conteyneth 8. demandes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="demand">
                     <head>1 <hi>Let any Proteſtant in the worlde, proue vnto me, that their church coulde rightly be called Catholike, which was ſo particular, that no man aliue coulde name a place where any ſuch church was.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHy might not our Church, when it was moſt hidden, be as rightly called Catholike, as the Church of the Apoſtles, when it was ſo parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, that it was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in the narrow bondes of Iury: for it is not called Catholike, becauſe it ſhoulde be euery where, for that it neuer was nor ſhalbe: But becauſe that where ſo euer it be, in partes, it is one body of Chriſt. The Popiſh church is not in euery parte of the worlde: For <hi>Mahomets</hi> ſect is in the greateſt parte. Many cuntries are I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters and the moſt parte of them that profeſſe the name of Chriſt, are not in the felowſhip of the Popiſh church: And whereas you ſaye: that no man aliue coulde name the place where it was, you make an impudent lye: For although it were vnknowen, to the Papiſtes, and enemies thereof, yet was it knowen to the true members therof. It was in Italie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Marſilius</hi> of <hi>Padua,</hi> preached: in France, when <hi>VValdo</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at Lyons, and there about. In England, when <hi>VVickliffe</hi> taught: in Bohemia, when <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi> and <hi>Ieronyme</hi> of <hi>Prage</hi> did floriſhe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="demand">
                     <head>2 <hi>Or that it might be called holy, which neuer had Baptiſme, or other ſacramentes, to ſanctifie any of her followers withall.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IT had the ſpirite of God to ſanctifie the true members of it, and it had ſacramentes to teſtifie the ſame: Alſo did not the Bohemians baptiſe: Were not <hi>pauperes de Lug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duno</hi>
                        <pb n="96" facs="tcp:23111:56"/>baptiſed? &amp;c. But if you count their Baptiſme no Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme, why did you not rebaptize in <hi>Queene Maries</hi> time, all thoſe that were baptized by our Church in <hi>King Edwards</hi> time?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="demand">
                     <head>3 <hi>Or that it ſhould be one, which as ſoone as it grew vp in the world, was diuided into ſo many ſundry ſectes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>NOne of vs will graunt you, that our Church began firſt to grow, when it was laſt brought to light, and knowledge of the world: for it hath continued e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſince Chriſt. But if there aroſe, or were renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many hereſies, with it, that is no new matter, but an olde practiſe of the deuill. For as ſoone as the Church of Chriſt beganne to grow vp after his aſcenſion, euen in the Apoſtles time, there were many ſectes and hereſies, As the Iewes that mainteyned the lawe, they that denyed the Reſurrection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Corinthians <hi>Hymenaeus</hi> and <hi>Philetus, Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, Cerinthus, Ebion, Marcion, Baſilides, Valentinus, Carpocrates, &amp;c.</hi> So that there were many more hereſies, at the firſt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell, in, and immediatly after, the Apoſtles time, then at the laſt reſtoring of the publike preaching ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of vnto the worlde in our dayes: And yet the Apoſtolike Church was one Church, and ſo is ours at this day one and the ſame.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="demand">
                     <head>4 <hi>Or that it might be called Apoſtolike, which could neuer cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by orderly ſuceſſion from any Apoſtle, or Apostolike man.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>YOu are neuer able to anſwere the arguments that are brought to proue that <hi>Peter</hi> was neuer Biſhoppe at Rome. And then where is all your braggs of Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſea, and ſucceſſion, &amp;c. But be it that <hi>Peter</hi> was there, except you proue ſucceſſion of doctrine and faith as wel as ſucceſſion of men, your ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not worth a ſtraw. And our Church, which holdeth all the doctrine of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and none other but the doctrine of the Apoſtles, ſhall be truely called, and founde, the Apoſtolike Church,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:23111:56"/>when your with all her ſucceſſion of Antichriſtes whore, whoremongers, heretikes, Sodomites, blaſphemers, coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, &amp;c. ſhabe Apoſtaticall, rather than Apoſtolicall.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="demand">
                     <head>5 <hi>Or the ſecret, baſe, contemptible, defaced, and diſordered Congregation, was euer of that maieſtie, that it might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the obedience of all Nations.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>HOw baſe, and contemptible ſoeuer it be, in the eyes of the wicked deſpiſers of it: yet did it not only require, but alſo ſubdue all nations to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the Faith, ſo many as were euer ſubdued, in the dayes of the firſt Chriſtian Emperors, and before. And ſence, when it was moſt defaced by the tyrannie of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, it was of ſuch maieſtie, that it both required and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined the obedience of the realme of Bohemia, and in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of time, hath obteined the obedience of almoſt all the nations of Europe. If the churche of Rome reteine the like maieſtie, why doth it not now, requier the like obedience of all nations, both Chriſtians and Turkes. you will ſaye: It requireth, but it can not obteine. Euen ſo, I aunſwere of our Church, it hath alwayes bene worthy to requier: but it hath not pleaſed God, that it ſhoulde alwaies obteine.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="demand">
                     <head>6 <hi>Or that it was euer able to gather generall Councels.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe foure beſt generall Councells were gathered by our Church, and the Emperors, that were defenders of the ſame, and not by the byſhops of Rome. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were they Preſidentes in them, as it is manifeſt, that other men were Authors of the Canons, or diſtinctions: As of the Nicene, <hi>Alexander</hi> Biſhop of Conſtantinople of the Conſtantinopolitane. <hi>Nectarius</hi> byſhop of the Epheſine. <hi>Cyrillus</hi> byſhop of Alexandria of the Chalcedonenſe. <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolius</hi> of Conſtantinople &amp;c. and in other generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells where the biſhop of Rome was preſident, I aunſwere as <hi>Iohn</hi> Patriarche of Antioche did, in the Councell of Baſile, his preſidence was: <hi>Honoraria ad beneplacitum Concilij eis data:
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:23111:57"/>non authoritatiua, niſi ex conceſſione aut permiſſione habente vim conceſſionis aut ex tolerantia,</hi> that is: For honor ſake graunted to them ſo long as it ſhoulde pleaſe the Councell, and not of authority but either by graunt or permiſſion being of the force of a graunt or els of ſufferance. And I conclude as he doth, the Pope was neuer Preſident either of honor, or of authority, but by the graunt or permiſſion of the Councell. And how is the Popiſh church able to gather general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells at this daye? who will come at her calling? Except a few Spaniardes, and a ioly company of buckram biſhops of Italie? generall Councells of all the worlde, can neuer be gathered, but either whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is a Monarchie, or els (which is not to be looked for) that all the Princes of the worlde, will conſent together.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="demand">
                     <head>7 <hi>Or exerciſe Diſcipline.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BEcauſe this demande hath bene aunſwered ſo often before, I will ſaye the leſſe nowe. The free courſe of diſcipline, in time of perſecution may be hindred: As it was in <hi>S. Cyprians</hi> time, when the members of the Church be diſperſed: but the power of diſcipline, hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes remained, and when occaſion ſerued, bene executed: As the Bohemians, excommunicated the Adamites, and the ciuill Magiſtrates puniſhed them by the ſworde.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="demand">
                     <head>8 <hi>Or that theſe names, proper by ſcripture and Doctors of the true Church, coulde be euer chalenged, by any right to their ſaide Congregation.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>AS many of theſe names as are proper to the Church by ſcripture, or Doctors agreeing, with ſcripture, haue bene alwayes iuſtly chalenged of right to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine to our Church and Congregation.</p>
                     <p>I meane theſe:</p>
                     <div n="1" type="name">
                        <head>1 <hi>Corpus Chriſti.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <pb n="99" facs="tcp:23111:57"/>
                        <p> OVr Church doth rightly chalenge, to be the body of Chriſt, which acknowledgeth Chriſt to be her only head, Sauiour, Redeemer, Prieſt, King, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor. &amp;c. The Popiſhe church can not chalenge this name, becauſe ſhe doth not acknowledge Chriſt to be theeſe only and wholly.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="name">
                        <head>2 <hi>Sponſa Chriſti.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe ſpouſe of Chriſt, heareth the voice of Chriſt, and is ruled thereby, ſo doth our Church, therefore ſhe is ſpouſe of Chriſt. But the Romiſh church goeth a whoringe after her owne inuentions, committeth groſſe idolatry, and will in no wiſe be ruled only by the voice of Chriſt, there ſhe is not the ſpouſe of Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="name">
                        <head>3 <hi>Vinci dilecta Chriſto.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>HOwe tenderly Chriſt loueth his Church, the true members thereof, which haue receiued the firſt frutes of his ſpirit, do better vnderſtand in hart tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can be expreſſed with words, &amp; howe he abhorreth the whore of Babylon the Romiſhe Synagoge, the Scripture doth plentifully declare.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="name">
                        <head>4 <hi>Columba ſpecioſa.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>OVr Church, expreſſing the ſimplicitie of a fayer doue, may iuſtly chalenge this name: But the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonicall Strompet your church, in crafte and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitie, is more like a foxe than a doue.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="name">
                        <head>5 <hi>Domus Dei.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe true Church, in which we are, is the houſe or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie of God, which he gouerneth by his ſtewardes, the ſincere preachers of his word. The popiſh church is the Synagoge of Satan, where the preaching of God his word is deſpiſed, and the word it ſelfe, made ſubiect to mens determinations and authorities.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="name">
                        <pb n="100" facs="tcp:23111:58"/>
                        <head>6 <hi>Columna veritatis.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>SAinct Paule</hi> by this title doth admoniſh Paſtors, and Preachers, how great a burthen and charge they ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyne, that the truth of the Goſpell can not be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in the world, but by their miniſterie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of God, which is the piller and ſtay of truth, this their duety true preachers conſidering, are diligent in their calling to ſet forth the Goſpell and to preach the truth. But the popiſh church, which is not the vpholder, and mainteyner, but the ouerthrower &amp; oppreſſor of the truth, compelling it to giue place to falſhood and error, can by no equitie chalenge this name, to be called the piller and ſtay of truth, but rather of falſhood and lyes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="name">
                        <head>7 <hi>Ciuitas Dei.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>OVr Church is the citie of God, builded vpon the foundations of the Patriarkes, Prophets, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Ieſus Chriſt being the head corner ſtone: ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the lawes of God onely, reteyning that forme of regiment and common wealth, that Chriſt him ſelfe hath preſcribed. The Church of Antichriſt, is founded vppon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hilles, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17. vpon the traditions, dreames, phantaſies, and deuiſes of men, refuſeth to be ruled onely by the lawes of God, hath cleane altered and changed the forme of regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment preſcribed by God, &amp; ſet vp an other, full of Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian pride, crueltie, and tyrannie. Therefore in no wiſe may be called the citie of God, But Babylon the mother of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, Sodoma and Egypt, where our Lord is daily crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his members.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="name">
                        <head>8 <hi>Ciuitas ſupra montem poſita.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THis ſaying of our Sauiour Chriſt in the 5. of <hi>Mathew,</hi> is not properly meant of the Church, but of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles &amp; their ſucceſſors the miniſters of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:23111:58"/>euen as theſe ſayinges: <hi>You are the ſalte of the earth, you are the light of the worlde, A citie builded vppon an hill can not be hidden, neither is a candle lighted to be ſet vnder a buſhell.</hi> By which wordes, he teacheth them aboue all other men, to looke diligently to their life and conuerſation: for as they excell in place and dignitie, ſo the eyes of all men are ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them. As a citie builded vppon an hill, muſt needes be ſeene of all them that come neare it, ſo they being placed in ſo high an office and dignitie ſhall be noted and marked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other men. As a candle is not lighted but to be ſet on a candleſticke &amp; to giue light vnto all them that come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe, euen ſo a Miniſter and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>cher of God his word is not ordeyned for any other ende but that he ſhould ſhine before men in true doctrine and good maners. Hereby it appeareth how fondly ſome Papiſts would ſeeme to proue out of this place that the Church muſt alwayes be viſible, when the wordes are not applyed to the Church, but to the miniſters thereof, I know ſome of the doctors expound this place otherwiſe, but the context of the wordes doth plainely confute their error.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="name">
                        <head>9 <hi>Hortus concluſus.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>AS a garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or orchard walled in or incloſed with hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, is more eſtemed of the owner, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great broad fieldes, and the trees and flowers that growe therein are preſerued and kept more ſafely, then ſuch as are wilde and grow abroad, right ſo the Church of Chriſt ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the reſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, though it be ſmall in compaſſe, yet is it more eſtemed of him then all the world beſide. But the Church of Rome, which will not be encloſed with the walls or hedges of God his word, but wandreth at large after her owne inuentions, can not be called the incloſed garden of Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="name">
                        <head>10 <hi>Fons ſignatus,</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe true Church of Chriſt is alſo compared to a ſpring or founteine, which is ſhutte in or ſealed vppe from the prophane waters of worldly vanities, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:23111:59"/>the water of life to all the children of God. But as for the popiſh church, which iſhueth out of the bottomles lake, is a ſtincking puddle of all falſe doctrine and hereſie, whereof the whore beareth a cupp full. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17. out of which all nations haue dronk, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18. So farre is it, that ſhe ſhould be a well, ſealed vp by Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="name">
                        <head>11 <hi>Sponſa Agni.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe deſcription of the Spouſe of the Lambe, ſet forth in <hi>S. Iohns</hi> Reuelation, doth in all pointes moſt aptly agree vnto our holy Church and congregation. But the popiſh church, which is not content to be clothed in that white ſhining ſilke, which is the Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Saincts made white in the blood of the Lambe, but with the filthy ragges of mans righteouſnes, <hi>Eſay</hi> 64. is no Spouſe of Chriſt, but the darling of the deuill.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="name">
                        <head>12 <hi>Mulier amicta Sole.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>NO place in all the ſcripture doth more plainely ſet forth the eſtate of our Church than this 12. of the <hi>Apocalyps.</hi> She is clothed with the ſunne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe Ieſus Chriſt, which is her bewtie. She trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnder her feete, the Moone of mutabilitie, changea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe, and inconſtancie, ſhe is crowned with 12. ſtarres, which is the doctrine of the 12. Apoſtles, the worde of God. She is alwaies fruitefull, and perſecuted by the deuill and his members, but yet by Chriſt defended, protected, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for in all daungers and aduerſities. But the church of Rome, is that whore of Babylon clothed in purple and ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, golde, precious ſtones, and perles, deſcribed <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17. ſitting vpon the beaſt with ſeuen heades, which are the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hilles, and is the great cytie that had dominion ouer the kinges of the earth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="name">
                        <head>13 <hi>Habitatio fratrum in vnum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <pb n="103" facs="tcp:23111:59"/>
                        <p> ALthough this ſaying be not proper nor peculiar vnto the Church onely, but common to euery ſocietie and fellowſhip of men that continue in godly vnity, yet doth it moſt aptly agree vnto our Church, which holdeth one vnity of doctrine, faith, and religion of Chriſt. But the Popiſh church how ſo euer it bragge of vnity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their agreement is not in verity, can not be that coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of brethren, which the Pſalmiſt doth ſo highely commende.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="14" type="name">
                        <head>14 <hi>Mons Dei mons pinguis.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe hill which <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo extolleth <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. is the mount Zyon, which though it be ſmall, yet it excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the high and frutefull hill of Baſan, becauſe God had choſen it to place his tabernacle therupon: euen ſo the church of Chriſt, though it ſurmount not ouer king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes in worldly dignities and commodities, yet to ſuch as Dauid was, the litle hill of Zyon is more worth, than all the ſeuen hilles of Rome.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="name">
                        <head>15 <hi>Sacra anchora.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>IN all the Scripture the Church is not compared to an holy Anchore, but in the ſixt to the Hebrues Fayth in God his promiſes, is compared vnto a ſure &amp; ſtedfaſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chore of our ſoules, vpon which Faith ſeeing our Church is builded we may truely ſay that in our Church only is this ſure anchore, which the popiſh church doth ſo much deſpiſe that ſhe counted it hereſie for vs to flie vnto Fayth, <hi>tanquans ad ſacram anchoram,</hi> that is: As to our only ſure refuge.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="name">
                        <head>16 <hi>Vinea Domini.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe Vineyard of the Lorde is of his owne plantinge, dreſſed &amp; tilled by ſuch husbandmen, as he hath pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in it, which will yeelde him frute in time conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient. This agreeth aptly vnto our Church, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:23111:60"/>no plant, but ſuch as is planted by our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. This Vineyarde ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not the popiſh church be compted, which plucketh vppe the vines planted by God, and in the ſteede of them ſetteth thornes and thiſtles after the deuiſes of men.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="name">
                        <head>17 <hi>Terra viuentium.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe land of the lyuing in ſcripture ſignifieth this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, as: <hi>I truſted to ſee the goodneſſe of the Lorde in the lande of the lyuing.</hi> that is: Although I was neare death, yet I beleued that God woulde preſerue me in this life <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. And vnto <hi>Doeg,</hi> he ſayeth: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52. <hi>God ſhall deſtroy thy roote out of the lande of the lyuing.</hi> that is: Out of this life. Alſo <hi>Ezechias,</hi> in his pſalme. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 38. <hi>I ſhall not ſee the Lorde, euen the Lorde in the lande of the lyuing.</hi> that is: I ſhall no more praiſe God in his temple here in this life. And when you ſhall bring forth a place of ſcripture where it is proprely applied vnto the church, it ſhalbe an eaſie matter to proue that we onely are the liuely members of Chriſt, which abide in his body receuing all benefites of life from him which is our heade: And eaſie it wilbe to proue that you are the lande of the deade men, which are ſtrangers from the life of God <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. which are aliue in this worlde and not deade vnto Chriſt.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="18" type="name">
                        <head>18 <hi>Regina in veſtitu deaurato circundata varietatibus.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>ALthough this ſaying alleaged out of the 45. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> be figuratiuely ment of the church, as it is literaly ſpoken of <hi>Pharaos</hi> doughter whom <hi>Solomon</hi> maried: yet being alleaged not after the trueth of the Hebrue but after the error of the olde tranſlation, I will not interprete it contrarie to my conſcience (as <hi>S. Ieronym</hi> fayeth) accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that corrupt verſion but according to the trueth of the text, which is: <hi>The Queene in a garment of golde of Ophir,</hi> As for compaſſing with varieties, it is not in the text. By this figure the ſpirituall magnificence of the church of Chriſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:23111:60"/>of the Gentiles is ſet forth vnto vs, and therefore let not the Papiſtes dreame that material golde is the ornament of Chriſt his ſpouſe, but as it is before ſayed, of the whore of Babylon.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="19 20" type="name">
                        <head>19 <hi>Eccleſia magna.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <head>20 <hi>Populus grauis.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>DAuid</hi> in the 35. <hi>Pſalme</hi> promiſeth that he will geue thankes vnto God after his deliuerance, in a great companie and ſolemne aſſemblie of people, ſuch as was wont to come together at the holy meetings in the Sanctuarie. This is the true and the ſimple meaning of this text. And it were to violent an interpretation to inforce it to be a propheſie of the church of Chriſt, although it be true that the church is a great congregation and a mighty people, yet remembring therewith that in comparizon of all the worlde it is as Chriſt him ſelfe calleth it: A litle Flocke.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="21" type="name">
                        <head>21 <hi>Archa Noe.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>IN the Arch of <hi>Noe,</hi> as <hi>S. Peter</hi> teſtifieth 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. but a fewe, namely 8. ſoules were ſaued in the water, euen as many as were obedient vnto the voice of God, the whole worlde beſide were drowned. Wherefore how fewe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we be: As the Papiſtes ſay we are not many, ſo long as we obey the voice of God, we doubt not but we ſhalbe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Arch. And the Papiſtes with all their vniuerſality and multitude, deſpiſing the lawe of God, ſhall periſhe with the wicked worlde.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="22" type="name">
                        <head>22 <hi>Tabernaculum altiſſimi.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe old Tabernacle was a figure of the true Church, and we know that none ſhall dwell therein but ſuch as be deſcribed in the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. Therefore let the Papiſtes bragge as long as they liſt of the Tabernacle of the higheſt, yet ſhall they not dwell there, neither ſhall
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:23111:61"/>they reſt in his holy hill, becauſe they be not indued with ſuch vertues, ſpringing of true, and a liuely faith: As in that <hi>Pſalme</hi> be ſet forth.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="23" type="name">
                        <head>23 <hi>Ager &amp; area Dei.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe church is the feelde and flower of God, in his feelde he ſoweth none but good ſeede, &amp; the chaffe ſhalbe purged from his flower. The Papiſtes are ſome of theſe tares, whome the enuious man hath ſowed while men were a ſleepe, and the chaffe, which after it be purged from the corne together with the tares ſhalbe burned in the vnquencheable fire.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="24" type="name">
                        <head>24 <hi>Mater fidelium.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>IEruſalem that is from aboue is free, which is the mother of vs all, which embrace Ieſus Chriſt as our onely Rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer from the bondage and curſe of the lawe. As for that ſteppe mother of Rome which bringeth men into captiuitie through ceremonies and traditions of men: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth vnto bondage as <hi>Agar</hi> did, and is become the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, not of the faithfull, but of abhominable fornication <hi>Apocalip.</hi> 17.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="25" type="name">
                        <head>25 <hi>Nutrix Chriſtianorum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe church of Chriſt is the Nurſe of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which bringeth them vp and feedeth them firſt with milke, and afterwarde with ſtronger meates according as they are able to receue it 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. But Rome, which feedeth her babes with poyſon of mans traditions in ſteede of the milke of God his word, &amp; will rather ſee them famiſh than they ſhoulde taſte of God his worde, maye well be a nurſe of Antichriſtians, but neuer did good vnto Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="26" type="name">
                        <head>26 <hi>Eccleſia orthodoxa.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <pb n="107" facs="tcp:23111:61"/>
                        <p> TRue opinions are confirmed out of the worde of trueth, wherefore our church which holdeth no do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but ſuch as is tried by the worde of truth moſt truly may be called the true beleuing church. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe, the Popiſh church which ſo manifeſtly diſſenteth from the worde of trueth that ſhe dare not be iudged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, but moſt blaſphemouſly ſubmitteth the ſame to her cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and falſe iudgement, maye iuſtly be called a falſe belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing church.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="27, 28" type="names">
                        <head>27 <hi>Vna, Sancta, Catholica.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <head>28 <hi>Apoſtolica.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THis hath bene often proued before: And namely in the firſt, ſecond, third, and fourth demandes of this laſt Article.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="29" type="name">
                        <head>29 <hi>Vxor de latere Chriſti ſicut Eua de latere Adam.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>AS <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſayeth: The church of Chriſt is taken out of his ſide: as <hi>Eue</hi> was out of <hi>Adams</hi> ſide, which ſo long as ſhe obeyeth the voice of her busbande, is not deceiued by the ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: But if ſhe be abſent from him, that ſhe be not inſtructed by him, ſhe is deceiued by heretikes <hi>Auguſti. De Geneſ. contra Manichaeos libro.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>&amp;</hi> 26. by which place of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> it is proued that the Church may erre, if ſhe be not ruled by the worde of God.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="30" type="name">
                        <head>30 <hi>Domus Pacis.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe church may be called the houſe of Peace, becauſe there is in it Peace and agreement in the cheefeſt Articles of the Faith, or becauſe in it is taught vs the Peace and reconciliation wrought by Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we knowing that we are iuſtified by faith, haue peace with God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. But neither of theſe Peaces are in the church of Rome: for there is diſſention in doctrine and their doctrine diſſenteth from the truth: as for the peace of conſcience is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:23111:62"/>vnknowen vnto Papiſtes, euen as the iuſtification of Faith, by which onely it is obteined.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="31" type="name">
                        <head>31 <hi>Domus Refugij.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>THe houſe of Refuge or defence may alſo be applied to the Church, out of which is no ſaluation: And in whoſe boſome it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth euery man to reſt, which ſhall looke for the refuge and defence of God. But God forbidde that any man ſhould ſeeke for refuge or helpe at your church, which muſt be ouerthrowen with ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence as a great mylſtone that is caſt into the Sea, and ſhalbe founde no more <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="32" type="name">
                        <head>32 <hi>Domus Veritatis.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>AS our church is the piller and ſtaie of trueth, ſo is ſhe alſo the houſe of Trueth, which knoweth nothing but him that is the Trueth it ſelfe Ieſus Chriſt and his moſt holy Scripture: In which this trueth is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and teſtified. But your Synagoge is the houſe of lyes, where beſide mens doctrines and traditions which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but lyes, there be alſo leaden legendes of lyes, Promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuaries of lyes, Feſtiuals of lyes, and other infinite bookes of lyes.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="33" type="name">
                        <head>33 <hi>Societas Sanctorum.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>HOw ſhoulde not our Church be the ſocietie and fellowſhip of Sainctes, which is ſanctified and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the bloode of Chriſt, which hath receiued the ſpirite of ſanctification, by which we crie: <hi>Abba,</hi> Father, which is guided and gouerned by the moſt ſacred and holy worde of God. And how can the Popiſh church be the fellowſhip of Sainctes, when ſhe refuſeth the ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt his one oblation and ſacrifice, as ſufficient to make them perfect, which ſcorneth at the ſpirite of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, which can abide any thing, rather than to be dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:23111:62"/>onely by God his holy worde: Finally which acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth no ſainctes, but ſuch as the moſt vnholy Pope, for money doth canonize and make ſainctes.</p>
                        <p>Proue vnto me therefore that theſe excellent and propre callinges, can agree to any diſordered companie or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, or to any vnknowen ſociety of men: but onely to the true Church of Chriſt ſpred throughout the whole worlde by Chriſtes his promiſe, and by vertue of his ſpirit, continued in truth and grace from falſhood ſence Chriſtes time, and I recant.</p>
                        <p>AS many of theſe excellent names, as in the worde of God, or the doctors agreeing with the worde of God, are propre or perteyning to the true Church of Chriſt, ſo many haue I proued to be propre and perteyning to our moſt holy and well ordered Congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And moreouer that they can in no wiſe be rightly applied to that moſt abhominable, Idolatrous, and diſordered Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagoge of Rome, which is vtterly departed from the faith, geuing heede to ſpirites of error, and doctrines of deuills, being ſo liuely painted forth and euen pointed fotth by the ſcripture to be that Antichriſtian church, whereof the holy Ghoſt propheſieth, that no man, except he will wilfully be blinde, can be ignorant thereof, ſo that if you be not ſtarke blinde, and geuen vp into a reprobate ſence, when you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe thinges you will recant.</p>
                        <p>Let any man therefore aliue anſwer directly and plainly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out colour or fraude of wordes and vnprofitable digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the foreſayd or any of the foreſayd demandes, and I ſhall willingly leaue the knowne Church &amp; playne way of Saluation, and wander in the woodes to ſeeke after them, and their congregation.</p>
                        <p>IF you had not added this concluſion, we might haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued ſome hope, that vpon further inſtruction in ſuch matters as troubled your conſcience you would haue ben
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:23111:63"/>contented to be reformed after God his worde, and good counſell. But now you declare that you are ſo obſtinatly bent that what ſo euer be proued againſt you, you will not receiue it as truth but yeld vnto it perforce. As for me, Although I know there are very many which with more learning and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence coulde haue aunſwered your demandes, yet being ſuch as they are, I ſubmitte my ſelfe to the iudgement of all them, that be learned and godly minded, whether I haue not directly and plainely, without colour or fraude of wordes, &amp; without all digreſſion aunſwered the ſame, ſo that I doubt not, but as many as are tractable, and ſtayed vpon theſe doubtes onely, may be fully perſwaded by theſe not very long and yet ſufficient Anſwers.</p>
                        <trailer>THE ENDE.</trailer>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23111:63"/>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
